(ignoring known css parsing error)
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 23:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US Administration announces 34% tariffs on China – 20% on EU (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet</link>
            <guid>43561253</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 20:39:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet">https://www.bbc.com/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43561253">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="list" spacing="6" tabindex="0" data-testid="postList"><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:d354a1b9-a777-4992-b32f-83eccc5e3a03"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Scotch bar in New York might have to pivot to bourbon</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:25 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2022/8/26/95e08369-2529-4559-8837-91fd26c52939.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>David Wallace Lockhart</strong><br>Reporting from New York</span></p><figure><p><span><img alt="Jeff Winslow" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/86a5de7a-8f79-4639-a530-f07e637e763e.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/86a5de7a-8f79-4639-a530-f07e637e763e.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/86a5de7a-8f79-4639-a530-f07e637e763e.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/86a5de7a-8f79-4639-a530-f07e637e763e.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/86a5de7a-8f79-4639-a530-f07e637e763e.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/86a5de7a-8f79-4639-a530-f07e637e763e.jpg.webp 640w" width="640" height="360"></span></p></figure><p>I’ve
been watching the tariff announcement at the Caledonian Bar in Manhattan. </p><p>They
stock 130 Scottish whiskies, and they’ll now face a 10% tariff when it comes to
importing them. </p><p>A
typical glass would set you back about $20. But that may have to
increase. </p><p>Jeff
Winslow - who works at the bar - explains that they may have to pivot more
towards US spirits, like bourbon and rye, which won’t face a similar increase
in price. </p><p>That’s
exactly the sort of change in behaviour distillers in Scotland will be worried
about. </p><p>After the tariffs were announced, Scotland's Deputy First Minister Kate Forbes said: “We do not believe unilateral measures by the US are the answer and we are concerned about the negative impact of trade barriers on the Scottish economy. We urge the US and all parties to come together and work towards mutually beneficial resolutions." </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:78bd27a6-8502-4745-ba5a-de8016e218e3"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Switzerland will quickly decide its response - president</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:24 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><figure><p><span><img alt="Karin Selter in profile looking to side before row of flags" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/40c4415f-3e4c-45e8-b006-a1451abf1337.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/40c4415f-3e4c-45e8-b006-a1451abf1337.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/40c4415f-3e4c-45e8-b006-a1451abf1337.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/40c4415f-3e4c-45e8-b006-a1451abf1337.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/40c4415f-3e4c-45e8-b006-a1451abf1337.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/40c4415f-3e4c-45e8-b006-a1451abf1337.jpg.webp 800w" width="1022" height="575"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p></figure><p>We've just heard from Swiss President Karin Keller-Sutter, who writes on X that the country "will quickly determine" its next steps in response to the tariffs.</p><p>"The country's long-term economic interests are paramount," she wrote. "Adherence to international law and free trade remain core values."</p><p>Switzerland is considered one of the "worst offenders" according to President Trump and his trade list, and its goods will be taxed at 31% under the US plan. </p><p>The US sent $25bn worth of goods to Switzerland in 2024, and imported more than twice that amount, $63.4bn, leading to a large trade deficit. </p><p>In its annual trade report released earlier this week, the US described Switzerland as protectionist, claiming it used high subsidies, import restrictions and tariffs to keep prices low and build up its agricultural sector. </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:516b72fd-764b-4829-954e-82d971ddf747"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>A sense of relief - but no delight - among UK government ministers</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:18 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2023/11/15/b9eb2a7b-b156-46ad-b4fa-fb47dc1b0972.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Chris Mason</strong><br>Political editor</span></p><p>Just like so many others, the Business Secretary Jonathan
Reynolds was watching the telly to see what President Trump would have to say.</p><p>Folk in government in the UK had picked up a sense of the
mood music – a sense that the UK was "in the good camp rather than the bad
camp" as one figure put it to me – but they had no idea what that meant.</p><p>We now do know what it means.</p><p>I detect a sense of relief among ministers, but make no
mistake they are not delighted – the tariffs imposed on the UK will have
significant affects, and the tariffs on our trading partners will have a
profound impact on jobs, industries and global trading flows in the weeks,
months and years to come.</p><p>Negotiations with America over a trade deal continue.</p><p>I am told a team of four UK negotiators are in “pretty
intensive” conversation with their American counterparts – talking remotely,
but willing to head to Washington if signing a deal appears imminent.</p><p>Let’s see.</p><p>The other point being seized upon at Westminster, in
particular by the Conservatives, is the difference between how the UK is being
treated compared to the European Union – with plenty pointing to it as a
dividend of Brexit.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:62d1baa5-020a-41d6-95c0-644883d2873b"><header><span><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/core/website/assets/static/news/incident-types/analysis.77b314ef10.svg" alt="Analysis" draggable="false"><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Who will get hit the hardest by Trump's tariffs?</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:16 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2022/9/23/54ee2260-b13b-4764-8ffe-9da5e4b57d8a.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Dharshini David</strong><br>Deputy economics editor</span></p><p>Cambodia, Vietnam, Malaysia, Bangladesh all fall among the
list who will face the heaviest tariffs on the goods they sell to America.</p><p>Some are also among those who benefited the most from
President Trump’s trade policy during his first term. The tariffs he imposed on
China allowed production in those countries to expand, and for them to grow
their market share in America. </p><p>Now, President Trump says, it’s payback time. Being
disadvantaged in this way could cost those companies dearly. They may try to
recoup sales for their textiles and other products in other countries. And the
result, for America Is uncertain.</p><p>Only if American shoppers are prepared to wear higher prices
will President Trump gain the extra revenues he hopes for. If they change their
buying habits, that penalises those trading partners but he doesn’t get that
tariff cash. It’s one example of why he can’t have it both ways.  </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:b4db6724-0e74-4a44-afe3-9bf3d2359317"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Northern Irish leaders respond</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:12 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><strong>Catherine Moore</strong><br>BBC News Northern Ireland</span></p><p>Posting on X after the announcement, Northern Ireland First
Minister Michelle O'Neill says her priority "has always been to protect
the best interests of workers, families, and businesses on the island".</p><p>"We must ensure that our all-island economy, which has
grown substantially in recent years, continues to thrive to create better
opportunities for all our people," she adds.</p><p>O'Neill says she will "continue to speak with political
and business leaders throughout this period of uncertainty" and prioritise
"the prosperity and future of everyone who calls our island home".</p><p>Meanwhile, Democratic Unionist Party (DUP) leader Gavin
Robinson says that "Northern Ireland remains exposed to potential EU
retaliation, and local businesses must not become collateral damage".</p><p>"The government must take urgent steps to protect
Northern Ireland's interests and ensure our place in the UK internal market is
fully safeguarded," he says.</p><p>Speaking earlier, Prime Minister Keir Starmer said the UK
government was "looking carefully" at the prospect of any retaliatory
tariffs the EU may announce in response to the tariffs, and the impact they
might have in Northern Ireland.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:c84fdc71-dd7f-44a4-899d-77ad9f53c68c"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Gorka tells BBC the UK is getting a 'special rate'</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:11 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2024/2/14/ded72972-7fe9-4089-a4a1-f17d165fd4fb.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Michael Race</strong><br>Business reporter</span></p><figure><p><span><img alt="Sebastian Gorka" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/2f2ade0a-f588-4dac-8c85-a4d6eb334546.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/2f2ade0a-f588-4dac-8c85-a4d6eb334546.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/2f2ade0a-f588-4dac-8c85-a4d6eb334546.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/2f2ade0a-f588-4dac-8c85-a4d6eb334546.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/2f2ade0a-f588-4dac-8c85-a4d6eb334546.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/2f2ade0a-f588-4dac-8c85-a4d6eb334546.jpg.webp 800w" width="4856" height="2731"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>EPA</span></p></figure><p>Sebastian Gorka, an adviser to US President Donald Trump,
has told BBC Newsnight that the UK is getting a “special rate” on tariffs, and
suggested it would be “improved” in the future.</p><p>“After Brexit you have reaffirmed your independence and I
think that is been proven today by the special rate that has been afforded to
the UK,” he told the programme.</p><p>“There’s nothing to say that the current rate, the exempted
rate, the special rate you have been afforded could not be improved. It is the
beginning.”</p><p>The UK government has been in negotiations over a potential
economic deal with the Trump administration in recent weeks, but could not
reach an agreement prior to today’s announcement.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:4e4c8657-0e1b-400f-a7a3-39feb328f228"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Stocks dip and US dollar slides</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:05 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><strong>Vishala Sri-Pathma</strong><br>BBC News</span></p><p>Stocks turned lower in late hours after President Trump outlined tariffs that included a 20% tariff on the European Union, 24% on Japan and 34% on China.</p><p>The <b>S&amp;P 500 fell almost 1.5% </b>and<!-- -->the <b>Nasdaq 100 slipped 2%.</b></p><p>Investors have been concerned about the impact of tariffs and the erratic nature of how they have been announced by the Trump administration.</p><p>Stocks of companies that are big importers were hit Wednesday evening. </p><p>Shares in <b>Nike fell 6%</b> and <b>General Motors dropped 3%</b>. Chip giant Nvidia has been hit hard. After initially rallying by 2%, it is currently down by nearly 5% after Taiwan was subject to a 32% rate.</p><p>So far, it appears that this announcement has not halted the slide in the US dollar or US stocks. The gold price continues to surge, and UK and European stocks look slightly more sheltered compared to US stocks.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:2885ff16-98d7-489b-ab7a-a3b9144ce9d5"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>‘No justification’ for tariffs - Taoiseach</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:02 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><strong>Catherine Moore</strong><br>BBC News Northern Ireland</span></p><p>Taoiseach (Irish Prime Minister) Micheál Martin says he can
see "no justification" for the tariffs, adding that Ireland will
reflect with its "EU partners on how best to proceed".</p><p> Martin says action should be "proportionate" and
"aimed at defending the interests of our businesses, workers and
citizens".</p><p>"A confrontation is in no one's interests," he
adds.</p><p>"Ireland will be a strong advocate for an outcome which
enhances the existing and strong transatlantic trading relationship."</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:337f9906-2cb6-481c-9996-aba057fb18bf"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Mexico and Canada not subject to latest tariffs</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:55 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2023/1/6/a1462f87-b5c0-43b2-8a08-2f7c7a8f1bff.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Bernd Debusmann Jr</strong><br>Reporting from the White House</span></p><p>Canada and Mexico - two of the three largest US trading partners, alongside China - are not subject to these tariffs, for now. </p><p>According to senior administration officials who spoke to reporters earlier, earlier tariffs placed on those countries by the Trump administration remain in effect, as well as an exemption for goods shipped under North America's free trade pact, the US-Mexico-Canada agreement (USMCA), which Trump signed during his first term.</p><p>If those tariffs are terminated, however, the tariffs will switch to the regime announced by Trump this afternoon. </p><p>Officials were earlier asked whether the USMCA exemptions would be extended, but provided no answer. </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:8a492d58-6ca1-4569-a7da-328be4711e7d"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Tariffs 'totally unwarranted' - Australian prime minister</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:49 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>The world is beginning to react to the new tariffs announcement by Donald Trump.</p><p>We're hearing from Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese, who says the new US trade tariffs are "totally unwarranted" and will change the perception of the two countries' relationship.</p><p>Australia, a close ally of the US, received a new tariff of 10%.</p><p>"These tariffs are not unexpected, but let me be clear, they are totally unwarranted," Albanese says.</p><p>His foreign minister, Penny Wong, also says she doesn't underestimate the effect the new tariffs will have on the strategically important Asia-Pacific region.</p><p>She says Australia will respond with credibility and maturity.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:a228eb16-971b-4005-9e16-372bd2aab4b2"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>When will the tariffs come into effect?</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:43 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>As we've been reporting, the president has announced a raft of new tariffs - including a baseline tariff on all countries as well as additional tariffs of varying amounts for individual countries. </p><p>Below we've set out when these tariffs will begin: </p><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      Today, 00:01 ET (05:01 BST) <b>25% tariff on all foreign-made automobiles</b></li><li spacing="rich-text">
      April 5 12:01 (ET) (05:01 BST)<b> baseline 10% tariff for all countries</b></li><li spacing="rich-text">
      April 9 12:01 (ET) (05:01 BST) <b>higher reciprocal rates</b></li></ul></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:fedd4722-d961-4ed8-985e-670b85aa4092"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>What has Trump announced on tariffs?</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:35 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><figure><figcaption><span>Media caption, </span><p>Key moments in Trump’s ‘Liberation Day’ tariffs announcement</p></figcaption></figure><p>We've just heard from US President Donald Trump, who formally announced his plan to slap reciprocal tariffs on US trading partners around the world. </p><p>Here's a recap of what he had to say:</p><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      Trump delivered a roughly <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet?post=asset%3A2ad72ea3-4067-4cd1-9637-3b2790314e0c#post">50-minute speech from the White House Rose Garden</a> with his full cabinet in attendance as well as representatives of the US steel and auto industries
    </li><li spacing="rich-text"><a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet?post=asset%3Ae9b9017f-448e-4c89-80e6-791989289279#post">He described today as "liberation day,"</a> and part of his plan to make America "wealthy again"
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      His executive order represents<a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet?post=asset%3Ab19e2753-8d37-4aa7-bd51-e8725c134128#post"> "a declaration of economic independence",</a> he said, in a reference to America's founding document announcing its plan to secede from Britain
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Starting tonight, the US will impose<a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet?post=asset%3Aa2c85619-5a3e-447a-8be2-b93e659bb87a#post"> a 25% tariff on all foreign-made automobiles</a>, he announced
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      He singled out several countries, saying that they were "cheating" by forcing Americans to pay high tariffs
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      He said <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet?post=asset%3Aa4a667d4-0ee9-43ee-a0dc-66320fd3111f#post">Australia refuses to buy American beef,</a> the EU rejects American poultry, and Asian countries "don't want us to sell our rice there"
    </li><li spacing="rich-text"><a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet?post=asset%3A3bbf550f-286b-491a-888b-384443c725eb#post">A baseline tariff of 10% will be applied to every country</a> starting on 5 April, including the UK, Trump declared
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      On 9 April, higher tariffs will begin to be imposed on certain countries, he said
    </li><li spacing="rich-text"><a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/c1dr7vy39eet?post=asset%3A58c1f629-07ca-49b5-b9e5-4729b7ab1d09#post">He pledged that history will prove him correct</a>, and that in the future Americans will look back and realise that he was right 
    </li></ul></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:9bdc60ea-565a-43d0-b5d5-a197280de128"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>In pictures: Trump's 'Liberation Day' event at the White House</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:28 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>In the last hour, the US has announced a range of new global tariffs which will come into effect one different dates over the next week. </p><p>Steel and auto workers were among those attending the speech at the Rose Garden - some of whom were kitted out in hard hats and high-vis uniforms.</p><p>In the images below you can see some of those workers sitting in the crowd with cabinet ministers and senators. </p><figure><p><span><img alt="An image taken from behind Trump as he stands at a podium facing into a crowd. JD Vance can be seen front and centre sitting opposite him" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/9e884dfc-3b0f-43f3-bd8c-5f7133b46899.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/9e884dfc-3b0f-43f3-bd8c-5f7133b46899.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/9e884dfc-3b0f-43f3-bd8c-5f7133b46899.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/9e884dfc-3b0f-43f3-bd8c-5f7133b46899.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/9e884dfc-3b0f-43f3-bd8c-5f7133b46899.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/9e884dfc-3b0f-43f3-bd8c-5f7133b46899.jpg.webp 800w" width="6989" height="3931"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>EPA</span></p></figure><figure><p><span><img alt="Trump stands at a podium and holds a list titled 'Reciprocal tariffs' with a number of countries listed. China at the top followed by the European Union and Vietnam." src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/fc1d186a-a2d3-42e5-ac90-558ab5f45f4a.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/fc1d186a-a2d3-42e5-ac90-558ab5f45f4a.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/fc1d186a-a2d3-42e5-ac90-558ab5f45f4a.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/fc1d186a-a2d3-42e5-ac90-558ab5f45f4a.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/fc1d186a-a2d3-42e5-ac90-558ab5f45f4a.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/fc1d186a-a2d3-42e5-ac90-558ab5f45f4a.jpg.webp 800w" width="1000" height="562"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Reuters</span></p></figure><figure><p><span><img alt="A number of people sit and look ahead. In the centre is a row of people wearing hard hats of various colours" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/76cd8ee8-7644-4875-a467-92265509a216.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/76cd8ee8-7644-4875-a467-92265509a216.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/76cd8ee8-7644-4875-a467-92265509a216.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/76cd8ee8-7644-4875-a467-92265509a216.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/76cd8ee8-7644-4875-a467-92265509a216.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/76cd8ee8-7644-4875-a467-92265509a216.jpg.webp 800w" width="3984" height="2243"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Reuters</span></p></figure><figure><p><span><img alt="Trump sits at a desk and signs an executive order. He looks at his page while he does so. He wears a suit with a red tie" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/1ed424b8-54d3-4904-9145-7a1ae8bf8e8d.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/1ed424b8-54d3-4904-9145-7a1ae8bf8e8d.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/1ed424b8-54d3-4904-9145-7a1ae8bf8e8d.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/1ed424b8-54d3-4904-9145-7a1ae8bf8e8d.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/1ed424b8-54d3-4904-9145-7a1ae8bf8e8d.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/1ed424b8-54d3-4904-9145-7a1ae8bf8e8d.jpg.webp 800w" width="3984" height="2241"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Reuters</span></p></figure></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:2208223e-46de-475b-8afd-015cb553fd46"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>New tariffs listed for countries in Europe</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:25 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>European nations, including the 27 members states of the European Union, feature heavily in Trump's announcement. </p><p>The EU has drawn the ire of the president, who has previously said he believes the bloc was created to "screw the United States".</p><p>Here's a breakdown of some of the countries listed in Trump's chart:</p><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      European Union - 20%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Kosovo - 10%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Switzerland - 31%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      United Kingdom - 10%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Norway - 15%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Ukraine - 10%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Liechtenstein - 37%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Serbia - 37%
    </li></ul><p>The White House's official rapid response team has <a href="https://x.com/RapidResponse47/status/1907541343250878752">published the full list of countries<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> on its social media channels.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:b9fb9466-1af7-49eb-8abd-9860bfef0a48"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Trump's new tariffs on countries in Asia</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:16 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>Let's have a closer look at the tariffs just announced by Trump. We'll break them down by region, starting with Asian countries ranging from Singapore's relatively low 10%, all the way up to 48% on Laos.</p><p>Here's a looks at some of the countries in Asia that appeared on his chart, alongside their new US tariff rates:</p><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      China - 34%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Vietnam - 46%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Taiwan - 32%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Japan - 24%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      India - 26%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      South Korea - 25%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Thailand - 36%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Malaysia - 24%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Cambodia - 49%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Bangladesh - 37%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Singapore - 10%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Philippines - 17%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Pakistan - 29%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Sri Lanka - 44%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Myanmar - 44%
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Laos - 48%
    </li></ul></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:9b85d324-c8fa-438e-9377-7fc0a3ed8221"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Charts make briefing room appearance</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:09 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2023/1/6/a1462f87-b5c0-43b2-8a08-2f7c7a8f1bff.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Bernd Debusmann Jr</strong><br>Reporting from the White House</span></p><figure><p><span><img alt="Charts in the briefing room" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/3b288bfe-b595-4e6e-85fb-081279b025c8.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/3b288bfe-b595-4e6e-85fb-081279b025c8.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/3b288bfe-b595-4e6e-85fb-081279b025c8.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/3b288bfe-b595-4e6e-85fb-081279b025c8.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/3b288bfe-b595-4e6e-85fb-081279b025c8.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/3b288bfe-b595-4e6e-85fb-081279b025c8.jpg.webp 800w" width="2048" height="1152"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Bernd Debusmann Jr/BBC</span></p></figure><p>I'm now back in the White House, where large printed versions of the tariffs charts are now sitting on either side of the podium where Press Secretary Karoline Leavitt speaks to the press from. </p><p>Many reporters did not get accredited or approved for the Rose Garden event, which was held in a relatively tight space. </p><p>Those who didn't listened from the press area of the White House. Many of them are now running outside quickly to do their TV lives. </p><p>Today is one of the most crowded I've seen the White House, at least as far as reporters go - right up alongside Volodomyr Zelensky's visit earlier this year. </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:09cdb289-aff4-412f-804c-bcffa61c304a"><header><span><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/core/website/assets/static/news/incident-types/analysis.77b314ef10.svg" alt="Analysis" draggable="false"><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Tariffs will hurt, but UK's 10% could have been worse</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:07 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2023/11/15/b9eb2a7b-b156-46ad-b4fa-fb47dc1b0972.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Chris Mason</strong><br>Political editor</span></p><p>"It is lower than it could have been," a senior
government source tells me. </p><p>The tone was still sombre - a 10% tariff is big and
they’d rather not have them at all - it is considerably less than some others
and less than some thought it would be.</p><p>Ministers hope this announcement is a reasonable basis
for carrying on with negotiations over a trade deal that could lead to them
falling or being dropped entirely.</p><p>They hope too tonight’s news is a vindication of their
approach so far to the Trump administration.</p><p>But make no mistake - and those in government are keenly
aware of this - these tariffs will hurt, both directly and indirectly, as the
patchwork of new taxes upends global trade flows in the weeks, months and years
to come.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:3321f89a-6305-47dc-95d0-da2c2d9e4390"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Trump exits, brushing past shouted questions from reporters</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:06 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><figure><p><span><img alt="U.S. President Donald Trump holds a signed executive order, on the day of his remarks on tariffs in the Rose Garden at the White House" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/6dda43a4-a87f-4770-b515-7005e5aa1b70.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/6dda43a4-a87f-4770-b515-7005e5aa1b70.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/6dda43a4-a87f-4770-b515-7005e5aa1b70.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/6dda43a4-a87f-4770-b515-7005e5aa1b70.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/6dda43a4-a87f-4770-b515-7005e5aa1b70.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/4/2/6dda43a4-a87f-4770-b515-7005e5aa1b70.jpg.webp 800w" width="5500" height="3094"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Reuters</span></p></figure><p>Trump ends his long-awaited tariff announcement, Liberation Day, as he's called it, slow-strolling past a row of American flags and shouts from reporters. </p><p>The main question heard from the crowd of reporters is what happens if other countries retaliate, sparking a trade war that economists warn no one will win.</p><p>The unanswered question will linger in the days to come as world leaders calculate their responses. </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:58c1f629-07ca-49b5-b9e5-4729b7ab1d09"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>'A day you're going to look back on in years to come' - Trump</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:05 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>"We're going to have a very free and beautiful nation. It's going to be Liberation Day in America," Trump said, as he began to wrap up his speech.</p><p>"And it's going to be a day that you're hopefully going to look back on in years to come. And you're going to say: 'You know, he was right. This has turned out to be one of the most important days in the history of our country.'"</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:d7092ca6-8e8f-45c3-91ea-45ae6cf48382"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Trump also speaks about goal to end Ukraine war</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:04 British Summer Time</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>Trump also boasted about his administration's accomplishments as he approaches 100 days in office this term.</p><p>He mentioned some of his goals, including ending and preventing conflict around the world.</p><p>"[I'd] like to see if we can get that war ended [in Ukraine], and another war from not starting in the Middle East," he said.</p></article></div></li></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pico.sh (The ultimate SSH powered services for developers) (189 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pico.sh/</link>
            <guid>43560899</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 20:02:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pico.sh/">https://pico.sh/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43560899">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <div>
        
        <div>
          <p>The ultimate <code>ssh</code> powered services for developers</p>
        </div>
        <p><a href="https://pico.sh/getting-started">GET STARTED</a>
      </p></div>

    <div>
      <p>
        Our mission is to enable developers with services that 
        help them rapidly prototype on the web.  We want to make it
        easier than ever for developers to share their projects with the world.
      </p>

      <p>
        Our services allow users to publish content without needing to install anything.
        We accomplish this with the SSH tools (<code>rsync</code>, <code>sftp</code>,
        <code>sshfs</code>) you already have installed on your system.
      </p>

      <p>
        Use our platform entirely using SSH and our TUI.
      </p>

      
    </div>

    

    <article>
      <div>
        <h3>
          <span>
            
  
  <svg width="100" height="100" viewBox="0 0 100 100" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
    <path d="M8.48528 50L50 8.48528L91.5147 50L50 91.5147L8.48528 50Z" stroke-width="12"></path>
  </svg>
  

          </span>
          <a href="https://pico.sh/pgs">pages</a>
        </h3>
        <p>Host static sites on our global platform using SSH.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>
          <span>
            
  
  <svg width="112" height="90" viewBox="0 0 112 90" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
    <path d="M99.3013 9.00001C103.645 16.5241 105.954 25.0503 105.999 33.7382C106.045 42.4262 103.826 50.9761 99.5607 58.5452C95.2956 66.1144 89.1319 72.4416 81.677 76.9033C74.222 81.365 65.7332 83.8071 57.047 83.989C48.3608 84.171 39.7772 82.0864 32.1419 77.9408C24.5067 73.7952 18.0835 67.7316 13.5053 60.3476C8.92707 52.9637 6.3519 44.5142 6.03357 35.832C5.71524 27.1497 7.66474 18.5344 11.6899 10.835L40.2212 25.7509C38.7878 28.4927 38.0936 31.5606 38.207 34.6524C38.3203 37.7441 39.2373 40.753 40.8676 43.3824C42.4979 46.0118 44.7852 48.1711 47.5041 49.6473C50.223 51.1236 53.2797 51.8659 56.3728 51.8011C59.466 51.7363 62.4889 50.8667 65.1436 49.2779C67.7983 47.6891 69.9932 45.4359 71.5119 42.7406C73.0307 40.0452 73.8209 37.0006 73.8047 33.9068C73.7886 30.813 72.9665 27.7768 71.4196 25.0975L99.3013 9.00001Z" stroke-width="12"></path>
  </svg>
  

          </span>
          <a href="https://pico.sh/tuns">tuns</a>
        </h3>
        <p>Host public web services on localhost using SSH.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>
          <span>
            
  
  <svg width="79" height="72" viewBox="0 0 79 72" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
    <path d="M31.7058 61.5L7.89006 20.25C4.42596 14.25 8.75609 6.75 15.6843 6.75H63.3157C70.2439 6.75 74.574 14.25 71.1099 20.25L47.2942 61.5C43.8301 67.5 35.1699 67.5 31.7058 61.5Z" stroke="#F2F2F2" stroke-width="12"></path>
  </svg>
  

          </span>
          <a href="https://pico.sh/pipe">pipe</a>
        </h3>
        <p>Stream data between computers using our authenticated *nix pipes using SSH.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>
          <span>
            
  
  <svg width="111" height="35" viewBox="0 0 111 35" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
    <path d="M105.538 24.4843C68.6355 -34.027 50.7162 71.2227 5.50303 7.69397" stroke-width="12"></path>
  </svg>
  

          </span>
          <a href="https://pico.sh/prose">prose</a>
        </h3>
        <p>Serve your blog using SSH.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>
          <a href="https://pico.sh/feeds">rss-to-email</a>
        </h3>
        <p>Receive email digests for your RSS feeds using SSH.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>
          <a href="https://pico.sh/pastes">pastes</a>
        </h3>
        <p>Upload code snippets using <code>rsync</code>, <code>scp</code>, and <code>sftp</code>.</p>
      </div>
    </article>

    

    <div>
      <div>
        <h3>Deploy a site with a single command</h3>
        <div>
          <div>
            <p>Upload your static site to us:</p>
            <pre>rsync --delete -rv ./public/ pgs.sh:/mysite/</pre>
          </div>

          

          <div>
            <p>Now your site is available with TLS handled for you: <strong>https://{user}-mysite.pgs.sh</strong></p>
            <p>We also automatically handle TLS for your custom domains!</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>Access localhost using https</h3>
        <div>
          <div>
            <p>
              If you have a local webserver on <code>localhost:8000</code>,
              activate an SSH tunnel to us:
            </p>
            <pre>ssh -R dev:80:localhost:8000 tuns.sh</pre>
          </div>

          

          <p>
            Now your local dev server is available on the web: <strong>https://{user}-dev.tuns.sh</strong>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>Authenticated *nix pipes over SSH</h3>
        <div>
          <div>
            <p>Have one terminal listen for an event and another terminal send the event:</p>
            <pre>ssh pipe.pico.sh sub mytopic</pre>
            <pre>echo "Hello world!" | ssh pipe.pico.sh pub mytopic</pre>
          </div>

          

          <div>
            <p>The <code>sub</code> will receive "Hello world!"</p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>Publish blog articles with a single command</h3>
        <div>
          <div>
            <p>Create your first post, (e.g. <code>hello-world.md</code>):</p>
            <pre># hello world!

This is my first blog post.

Cya!</pre>
          </div>

          

          <div>
            <p>Upload the post to us:</p>
            <pre>scp hello-world.md prose.sh:/</pre>
            <p>
              Congrats!  You just published a blog article, accessible here:
              <strong>https://{user}.prose.sh/hello-world</strong>
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>Easily share code snippets</h3>
        <div>
          <div>
            <p>Pipe some stdout to us:</p>
            <pre>git diff | ssh pastes.sh changes.diff</pre>
          </div>

          

          <p>
            And instantly share your code snippets:
            <strong>https://{user}.pastes.sh/changes.patch</strong>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>Receive email notifications for your favorite rss feeds</h3>
        <div>
          <div>
            <p>Create a <code>blogs.txt</code> file:</p>
            <pre>=: email rss@myemail.com
=: digest_interval 1day
=&gt; https://pico.prose.sh/rss
=&gt; https://erock.prose.sh/rss</pre>
          </div>

          

          <div>
            <p>Then upload it to us:</p>
            <pre>scp blogs.txt feeds.pico.sh:/</pre>
            <p>
              After the daily interval has been reached, you will
              receive an email with your feeds!
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h3>Ready to join?</h3>
        
      </div>
    </div>

  <hr>

  


  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mozilla launching "Thundermail" email service to take on Gmail, Microsoft 365 (162 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.techradar.com/pro/mozilla-launching-thundermail-email-service-to-take-on-gmail-microsoft-365</link>
            <guid>43560885</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 20:01:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.techradar.com/pro/mozilla-launching-thundermail-email-service-to-take-on-gmail-microsoft-365">https://www.techradar.com/pro/mozilla-launching-thundermail-email-service-to-take-on-gmail-microsoft-365</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43560885">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="article-body">
<hr><ul><li><strong>Mozilla takes on Gmail, Microsoft 365 with range of new features</strong></li><li><strong>Thunderbird Pro includes Appointment, Send and Thundermail</strong></li><li><strong>A new AI writing tool is also coming with local processing</strong></li></ul><hr><p>Mozilla is turning its Thunderbird open source <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/best/best-email-clients" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/best/best-email-clients">email client</a> into a full communications platform with the launch of Thundermail and Thunderbird Pro.</p><p>The expansion of Mozilla's email services aims to compete with rival ecosystems like Gmail and <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/tag/microsoft" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/tag/microsoft">Microsoft</a> 365, which are more rich in features, except Mozilla’s offering stands out for its <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/best/best-open-source-software" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/best/best-open-source-software">open source</a> values of privacy, freedom, transparency and user respect.</p><p>“Thunderbird loses users each day to rich ecosystems that are both clients and services,” Ryan Sipes, Managing Director for Product Thunderbird <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://thunderbird.topicbox.com/groups/planning/T437cd854afcb1395" target="_blank" data-url="https://thunderbird.topicbox.com/groups/planning/T437cd854afcb1395" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">confirmed</a> as he expressed the ‘why’ behind Thunderbird’s expansion.</p><h2 id="thunderbird-is-about-to-get-an-overhaul-3">Thunderbird is about to get an overhaul</h2><p>The Thunderbird <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://stats.thunderbird.net/#ami" target="_blank" data-url="https://stats.thunderbird.net/#ami" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">database</a> says its number of active monthly installs has dropped from 17.7 million in late December 2020 to 16.2 million in late March 2025, with the mail app struggling to keep up with the industry’s main players like Gmail.</p><p>With the launch of Thunderbird Pro, Mozilla is adding Thunderbird Appointment, a new scheduling tool for sharing calendar links; Thunderbird Send, a rebuild of the discontinued Firefox Send; and Thunderbird Assist, a new AI-powered writing tool enabled via a partnership with Flower AI that is intended to do the processing locally to eliminate privacy concerns.</p><p>The final launch will be Thundermail, an email hosting service using the open-source Stalwart stack. Usrs will be able to pick between thundermail.com and tb.pro domains.</p><p>Apart from consistent community contributors who will be able to get early access for free, Sipes confirmed Mozilla would ultimately end up charging for the features, such as Send which requires storage, an expensive commodity.</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-feTYLA7XQKiaBBebuEiXTF"><section><p>Sign up to the TechRadar Pro newsletter to get all the top news, opinion, features and guidance your business needs to succeed!</p></section></div><p>“Once we have a strong enough user base that the services appear to be sustainable, we will open up free tiers with limitations, such as less storage or the like,” Sipes added.</p><h3 id="section-you-might-also-like"><span>You might also like</span></h3><ul><li>Check out the <a href="https://www.techradar.com/best/ai-writer" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/best/ai-writer">best AI writers</a></li><li>Keep your documents online with the <a href="https://www.techradar.com/best/best-cloud-storage" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/best/best-cloud-storage">best cloud storage solutions</a></li><li><a href="https://www.techradar.com/vpn/vpn-services/proton-joins-force-with-vivaldi-browser-to-help-you-break-free-from-big-tech" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/vpn/vpn-services/proton-joins-force-with-vivaldi-browser-to-help-you-break-free-from-big-tech">Proton joins forces with Vivaldi browser to help you break free from Big Tech</a></li></ul>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Waltz's team set up at least 20 Signal group chats for crises across the world (248 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/02/waltzs-team-set-up-at-least-20-signal-group-chats-for-crises-across-the-world-00266845</link>
            <guid>43560336</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 19:09:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/02/waltzs-team-set-up-at-least-20-signal-group-chats-for-crises-across-the-world-00266845">https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/02/waltzs-team-set-up-at-least-20-signal-group-chats-for-crises-across-the-world-00266845</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43560336">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/02/waltzs-team-set-up-at-least-20-signal-group-chats-for-crises-across-the-world-00266845: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Restructuring Announcement (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://automattic.com/2025/04/02/restructuring-announcement/</link>
            <guid>43559855</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 18:34:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://automattic.com/2025/04/02/restructuring-announcement/">https://automattic.com/2025/04/02/restructuring-announcement/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43559855">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="wrapper">
	<main id="content">
		<nav><ul><li><a href="https://automattic.com/news">News</a></li><li>/</li><li><a href="https://automattic.com/category/company-news/">Company News</a></li></ul></nav>		
		
		
<p><em>Earlier today, CEO Matt Mullenweg shared with Automattic employees the following message.</em></p>



<hr>



<p>I have had to make difficult decisions to protect&nbsp;Automattic’s long-term future. This post will outline why the changes are happening and the next steps in our organizational restructuring. I wish to be transparent and acknowledge immediately that this will be difficult news to hear. We will do everything to ensure that all Automatticians, those staying and those leaving, are supported.</p>



<h2 id="why-we-re-making-changes">Why We’re Making Changes<a href="https://updateomattic.wordpress.com/2025/04/02/restructuring-announcement/#why-we-re-making-changes"></a></h2>



<p>We have reached an important crossroads. While our&nbsp;revenue&nbsp;continues to grow, Automattic operates in a highly competitive market, and technology is evolving at unprecedented levels. To support our customers and products, we must improve our productivity, profitability, and capacity to invest.</p>



<p>As difficult as this decision has been, we are restructuring the company to:</p>



<ul>
<li>Become more agile and responsive.</li>



<li>Break down silos that have created inefficiencies.</li>



<li>Focus on product quality, doing fewer things better.</li>



<li>Ensure a viable financial model for long-term success.</li>
</ul>



<h2 id="what-this-means">What This Means<a href="https://updateomattic.wordpress.com/2025/04/02/restructuring-announcement/#what-this-means"></a></h2>



<p>This restructuring will result in an approximately 16% workforce reduction. HR will email those impacted to inform them they will leave Automattic with financial and support benefits.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="supporting-those-affected">Supporting Those Affected<a href="https://updateomattic.wordpress.com/2025/04/02/restructuring-announcement/#supporting-those-affected"></a></h2>



<p>This process is complex with Automatticians in 90 countries, but we’re committed to communicating clearly and compassionately. Colleagues who will be leaving will receive:</p>



<ul>
<li>A comprehensive package covering severance pay and benefits.</li>



<li>Retention of company laptops.</li>



<li>Job placement resources.</li>
</ul>



<p>They also have our enduring gratitude for their time with the company.</p>



<h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward<a href="https://updateomattic.wordpress.com/2025/04/02/restructuring-announcement/#looking-forward"></a></h2>



<p>Automattic has multiple products with world-touching potential in WordPress and beyond. I’m confident we will come out of this situation in a better position, poised to create a vibrant, profitable, well-designed company that will continue our mission to democratize the internet. I would ask that you take a moment to thank and appreciate the efforts of your teammates who have left the company, reflect on how you will move forward as an individual and Automattician, and join me in the vital work we have in front of us. I recognize this is a difficult time. In the coming weeks, we’ll share more about our path forward and how we’ll work together to strengthen our company.</p>



<p>We understand that you may wish to access support and discuss this with those close to you. I’d like to remind you that Automattic partners with Workplace Options, which provides emotional and practical well-being support if you seek advice from an external provider.</p>



<ul>
<li>[links to resources for employees, redacted]</li>
</ul>



<p>As always, your HR Wranglers are here to talk with you and support you.</p>




		
			</main><!-- #content  -->
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Tell HN: Announcing tomhow as a public moderator (1114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43558671</link>
            <guid>43558671</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 16:49:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43558671">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43558671: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Matrix.org Will Migrate to MAS (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://matrix.org/blog/2025/04/matrix-auth-service/</link>
            <guid>43558464</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 16:28:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://matrix.org/blog/2025/04/matrix-auth-service/">https://matrix.org/blog/2025/04/matrix-auth-service/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43558464">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p><strong>On Monday 7th of April 2025 at 7am UTC, we will migrate the Matrix.org homeserver's authentication system over to MAS (Matrix Authentication Service) in order to benefit from Next-generation authentication.</strong></p>
<p>The migration will involve up to one hour of downtime.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/pull/3861">MSC3861</a> (Next-generation auth for Matrix, based on OAuth 2.0/OIDC) and its dependent MSCs have progressed sufficiently that the Foundation is confident in MAS and the new next-generation auth APIs.Specifically, all the MSCs are now in or have passed Final Comment Period (FCP) with disposition to merge! 🎉</p>
<p>We expect the MSCs to finish FCP and get merged into the next spec release.The full list of core Next-gen Auth MSCs is:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/pull/3861">MSC3861: Next-generation auth for Matrix, based on OAuth 2.0/OIDC</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/pull/2964">MSC2964: Usage of OAuth 2.0 authorization code grant and refresh token grant</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/pull/2965">MSC2965: OAuth 2.0 Authorization Server Metadata</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/pull/2966">MSC2966: Usage of OAuth 2.0 Dynamic Client Registration in Matrix</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/pull/2967">MSC2967: API scopes</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/pull/4254">MSC4254: Usage of RFC7009 Token Revocation for Matrix client logout</a></li>
</ul>
<p>This is incredibly exciting, reflecting 4 years of work on next-generation auth, and brings with it a new account management interface, additional security, and a better registration experience.</p>
<h3 id="the-account-management-interface"><a href="#the-account-management-interface" aria-label="Anchor link for: the-account-management-interface">🔗</a>The account management interface</h3>
<p>You will be able to manage you account on a <strong>dedicated interface at account.matrix.org</strong> (accessible through your client or browser), where you can:</p>
<ul>
<li>See and delete your devices.</li>
<li>Update your contact information, like your email address.</li>
<li>Change your password and deactivate your account.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://matrix.org/blog/img/mas-devices.webp">
</p>
<h3 id="improved-security"><a href="#improved-security" aria-label="Anchor link for: improved-security">🔗</a>Improved security</h3>
<p>MAS comes with a significant refactoring of how authentication works on Matrix. Without breaking compatibility with the former authentication API, it brings several benefits</p>
<ul>
<li>Now, only your server will be able to see your account credentials! No more typing your password in every client you’d like to log in to.</li>
<li>Restricted access to sensitive operations, like deactivating your account.</li>
<li>Clearer view of which clients are using your account.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://matrix.org/blog/img/mas-grant-access.webp">
</p>
<h3 id="improved-registration-experience"><a href="#improved-registration-experience" aria-label="Anchor link for: improved-registration-experience">🔗</a>Improved registration experience</h3>
<p>Regardless of the client you use, the new registration and login experience makes it clear where your account lives, and it supports next-generation clients like Element X.</p>
<p><img src="https://matrix.org/blog/img/mas-create-account.webp">
</p>
<h2 id="impact"><a href="#impact" aria-label="Anchor link for: impact">🔗</a>Impact</h2>
<p>Your current sessions will remain active after the migration has taken effect. In other words, you will not be logged out of your clients.</p>
<p>We’re providing backwards compatibility for existing Matrix clients - this does not remove the stable Matrix 1.0 APIs. You can read more about the impact on clients in our previously published blog article - <a href="https://matrix.org/blog/2025/01/06/authentication-changes/">Authentication changes on Matrix.org</a>.</p>
<h2 id="this-is-only-the-beginning"><a href="#this-is-only-the-beginning" aria-label="Anchor link for: this-is-only-the-beginning">🔗</a>This is only the beginning!</h2>
<p>Matrix Authentication Service is Matrix's next-generation authentication stack. Together with the next-generation authentication APIs, it is the base of a new exciting era for authentication in Matrix!</p>
<p>This has been one of the most ambitious projects within the Matrix project, the result of a multi-year investment by Element, funded in turn by Element’s customers, including BWI.</p>
<p>It will enable new forms of authentication flows, like QR-code login (coming soon to matrix.org with <a href="https://github.com/matrix-org/matrix-spec-proposals/pull/4108">MSC4108</a>), and new categories of applications building on Matrix, thanks to fine-grained control over client access to the account.</p>
<p>You can find all the technical details in Quentin's Matrix Conference talk, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wOW8keNafdE">Harder Better Faster Stronger Authentication with OpenID Connec</a>t.</p>
<p><strong>Finally, if you have any concerns, please come talk to us in <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#matrix-auth:matrix.org">#matrix-auth:matrix.org</a></strong></p>

            <div>
                <p>
                    <h2>The Foundation needs you</h2>
                </p>
                <div>
                    <p>
                        The Matrix.org Foundation is a non-profit and only relies
                        on donations to operate. Its core mission is to maintain
                        the Matrix Specification, but it does much more than that.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        It maintains the matrix.org homeserver and hosts several
                        bridges for free. It fights for our collective rights to
                        digital privacy and dignity.
                    </p>
                    <p><a href="https://matrix.org/support">Support us</a>
                </p></div>
            </div>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Digital Archivists: Protecting Public Data from Erasure (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/digital-archive</link>
            <guid>43558182</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 16:03:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/digital-archive">https://spectrum.ieee.org/digital-archive</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43558182">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-headline="How Digital Archivists Are Saving Public Information from the Memory Hole"><p>In the three decades since <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/brewster-kahle-on-whats-next-for-the-decentralized-web-movement" target="_self">Brewster Kahle</a> spun up the nonprofit <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/internet">Internet</a> Archive’s <a href="https://web.archive.org/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Wayback Machine</a>, it has scaled up to include government websites and datasets—many of which are essential to the engineering and scientific communities. U.S. government agencies like the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/national-science-foundation">National Science Foundation</a>, <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/department-of-energy">Department of Energy</a>, and <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/nasa">NASA</a> are critical sources of research data, technical specifications, and standards documentation in pretty much every area where <em><em><a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/">IEEE Spectrum</a></em></em>’s audience works—AI &amp; computer science, biomedical devices, <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/power-and-energy">power and energy</a>, <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/topic/semiconductors/">semiconductors</a>, telecommunications…the list goes on.</p><p>Access to that governmental data directly affects the reproducibility of experiments, the validation of models, and the integrity of the scholarly record. </p><p>So what happens if an entire dataset vanishes? Among other things, it can invalidate years of research built upon that foundation. </p><p>Until recently, wholesale deletion of data has been rare. In the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/united-states">United States</a>, presidential transitions typically involve some changes to government websites to reflect new policy priorities. And after 9/11, the George W. Bush administration removed “<a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/story?id=7496067&amp;page=1#:~:text=Unclassified%20military%20after%2Daction%20reports%2C%20an%20FAA%20database,amid%20fears%20that%20terrorists%20might%20find%20information" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">millions of bytes</a>” of information from government sites for security reasons as well as hundreds of <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/department-of-defense">Department of Defense</a> documents and “tens of thousands” of <a href="https://www.ferc.gov/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Federal Energy Regulation Commission</a> files. </p><p>The <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/obama">Obama</a> and Biden administrations likewise made changes to government websites but didn’t engage in large-scale removal of Web pages or datasets. Obama, in fact, expanded public access to government data in 2009 by launching <a href="http://data.gov/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Data.gov</a>, whose stated mission is in part “to unleash the power of government open data to inform decisions by the public and policymakers.”</p><p> During President Donald J. Trump’s first term, researchers at the Environmental Data &amp; Governance Initiative <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0246450" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">found</a> that some government sites became inaccessible, and the phrase “climate change” was purged from several government Web pages.</p><p>Access to governmental data directly affects the reproducibility of experiments, the validation of models, and the integrity of the scholarly record.</p><p>The second term has been different. In February, a few weeks after Trump was sworn in for his second term, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/02/upshot/trump-government-websites-missing-pages.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><em><em>The New York Times</em></em> reported</a> that his administration took down more than 8,000 Web pages and <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/databases">databases</a>. Many of those pages have since reappeared, but some of the restored pages and files have had changes, including the erasure of <a href="https://grist.org/language/trump-delete-climate-change-words-resilience-order/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">terms like “climate change” (again) and “clean energy,”</a><em><em>Grist</em></em> reports. These moves have faced multiple court challenges; on 11 February, for instance, a federal judge ordered that public access to Web pages and datasets belonging to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the Food and Drug Administration be restored. </p><p>In our April <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/internet-archive-saving-us-data" target="_blank">issue</a>, <em><em>Spectrum</em></em> Assistant Editor Gwendolyn Rak <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/internet-archive-saving-us-data" target="_self">reports</a> on efforts to preserve public access to information. In addition to the ongoing work at the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/internet-archive">Internet Archive</a>, she describes how archivists at the <a href="https://lil.law.harvard.edu/our-work/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Library Innovation Lab at Harvard Law School</a> amassed a copy of the 16-terabyte <a href="https://lil.law.harvard.edu/blog/2025/02/06/announcing-data-gov-archive/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">archive of Data.gov,</a> which includes more than 311,000 public datasets. That copied archive is being updated daily with new data hoovered up via automated queries to application <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/programming">programming</a> interfaces (APIs). </p><p>Archivists are the guardians of memory. We depend on them to help us stay in touch with our history, maintain our knowledge base, and provide context, allowing us to understand how we came to be where we are and to light the way forward. In the fields of science, engineering, and medicine, where today’s innovations stand on the shoulders of yesterday’s discoveries, these digital preservationists ensure that the circuit of human knowledge remains unbroken.</p><p><em>This article appears in the April 2025 print issue as “Lots of Copies Keep Stuff Safe.”</em></p><p><em>Editor’s note: This post was revised to match the print version.</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Animals Made from 13 Circles (2016) (391 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.dorithegiant.com/2016/05/13-animals-made-from-13-circles.html</link>
            <guid>43557873</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 15:35:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.dorithegiant.com/2016/05/13-animals-made-from-13-circles.html">https://www.dorithegiant.com/2016/05/13-animals-made-from-13-circles.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43557873">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.dorithegiant.com/2016/05/13-animals-made-from-13-circles.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Porting Tailscale to Plan 9 (316 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tailscale.com/blog/plan9-port</link>
            <guid>43557790</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 15:29:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tailscale.com/blog/plan9-port">https://tailscale.com/blog/plan9-port</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43557790">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://tailscale.com/blog/plan9-port: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nintendo unveils Switch 2 ahead of June 5 launch (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/</link>
            <guid>43557524</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 15:07:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43557524">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
          
<p>As seen previously, the Joy-Cons will be bigger than on the original Switch and will feature larger shoulder buttons on the inside edges. The system itself has a larger, "more sturdy" stand that can be adjusted to sit at multiple angles. A second USB-C outlet on the top of the system will allow for easier charging and connections.</p>
<p>Third-party publishers announced a number of ports for the Switch 2, including <em>Cyberpunk 2077: Ultimate Edition, Final Fantasy VII Remake Intergrade</em>, <em>Elden Ring: Tarnished Edition, Hades II, Street Fighter VI, Split Fiction, EA Sports FC, Madden NFL, Hogwarts Legacy </em>(with new Mouse Controls)<em>, Yakuza 0 Director's Cut, Tony Hawk's Pro Skater 3 + 4, and Hitman: World of Assassination</em>.</p>

<figure>
    <div>
            <p><a data-pswp-width="2338" data-pswp-height="1340" data-pswp-srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 AM.png 2338w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 AM-640x367.png 640w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 AM-1024x587.png 1024w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 AM-768x440.png 768w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 AM-1536x880.png 1536w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 AM-2048x1174.png 2048w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 AM-980x562.png 980w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 AM-1440x825.png 1440w" data-cropped="false" href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34%E2%80%AFAM.png" target="_blank">
              <img width="2338" height="1340" src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34%E2%80%AFAM.png" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM.png 2338w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-640x367.png 640w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1024x587.png 1024w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-768x440.png 768w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1536x880.png 1536w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-2048x1174.png 2048w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-980x562.png 980w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.54.34 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1440x825.png 1440w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2338px) 100vw, 2338px">
            </a></p><div id="caption-2086286">
              <p><em>The Duskbloods</em>, a Switch 2 exclusive from FromSoftware.
                              </p><p>
                  Credit:
                                      FromSoftware/Nintendo
                                  </p>
                          </div>
          </div>
          <figcaption>
        <div>
    
    <p><em>The Duskbloods</em>, a Switch 2 exclusive from FromSoftware.

              <span>
          Credit:

          
          FromSoftware/Nintendo

                  </span>
          </p>
  </div>
      </figcaption>
      </figure>

<p>FromSoftware also offered an extended preview of a new vampire-themed, <em>Bloodborne</em>-inspired action RPG game called <em>The Duskbloods</em>. The Switch 2 exclusive, planned for 2026, showed off a wide range of metaphyiscal imagery and both melee and gun-based combat, including a character that flies around in a metal suit with a jetpack.</p>
<figure>
    <div>
            <p><a data-pswp-width="2366" data-pswp-height="1338" data-pswp-srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM.png 2366w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM-640x362.png 640w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM-1024x579.png 1024w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM-768x434.png 768w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM-1536x869.png 1536w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM-2048x1158.png 2048w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM-384x216.png 384w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM-980x554.png 980w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 AM-1440x814.png 1440w" data-cropped="false" href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26%E2%80%AFAM.png" target="_blank">
              <img width="2366" height="1338" src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26%E2%80%AFAM.png" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM.png 2366w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-640x362.png 640w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1024x579.png 1024w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-768x434.png 768w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1536x869.png 1536w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-2048x1158.png 2048w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-384x216.png 384w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-980x554.png 980w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.43.26 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1440x814.png 1440w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2366px) 100vw, 2366px">
            </a></p><div id="caption-2086269"><p>
              GameCube games available exclusively to Switch 2 owners with Nintendo Online subscriptions.
                              </p><p>
                  Credit:
                                      Nintendo
                                  </p>
                          </div>
          </div>
          <figcaption>
        <div>
    
    <p>
      GameCube games available exclusively to Switch 2 owners with Nintendo Online subscriptions.

              <span>
          Credit:

          
          Nintendo

                  </span>
          </p>
  </div>
      </figcaption>
      </figure>

<p>Nintendo Switch Online memberships will carry over to Switch 2. And Switch 2 owners who subscribe to the Expansion Pack will get access to a library of Nintendo GameCube games, including <em>The Legend of Zelda: The Wind Waker</em>,&nbsp;<em>Soulcalibur II, and F-Zero GX </em>at launch, with more to be added in the future. These games will feature "sharper graphics and higher resolution" than the original releases, Nintendo said. A replica wireless GameCube controller will also be available for purchase by Nintendo Switch Online members.</p>
<p>Nintendo also showed a small preview of a new, open-world <i>Kirby Air Riders </i>game. The follow-up to GameCube's <em>Kirby's Air Ride</em> showed the pink puffball grabbing a jetpack-propelled star across verdant, grassy fields.</p>
<figure>
    <div>
            <p><a data-pswp-width="2372" data-pswp-height="1334" data-pswp-srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM.png 2372w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-640x360.png 640w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-1024x576.png 1024w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-768x432.png 768w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-1536x864.png 1536w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-2048x1152.png 2048w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-384x216.png 384w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-1152x648.png 1152w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-980x551.png 980w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 AM-1440x810.png 1440w" data-cropped="false" href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55%E2%80%AFAM.png" target="_blank">
              <img width="2372" height="1334" src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55%E2%80%AFAM.png" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM.png 2372w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-640x360.png 640w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1024x576.png 1024w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-768x432.png 768w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1536x864.png 1536w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-2048x1152.png 2048w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-384x216.png 384w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1152x648.png 1152w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-980x551.png 980w, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Screenshot-2025-04-02-at-9.59.55 https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/04/nintendo-offers-new-details-on-switch-2-hardware-software/AM-1440x810.png 1440w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2372px) 100vw, 2372px">
            </a></p><div id="caption-2086287"><p>
              The big gorilla is punching down.
                              </p><p>
                  Credit:
                                      Nintendo
                                  </p>
                          </div>
          </div>
          <figcaption>
        <div>
    
    <p>
      The big gorilla is punching down.

              <span>
          Credit:

          
          Nintendo

                  </span>
          </p>
  </div>
      </figcaption>
      </figure>

<p>The presentation concluded with a new 3D <em>Donkey Kong</em> game called <em>Donkey Kong Bonanza</em>, planned for July 17<em>.</em> The trailer showed a redesigned, cuter version of the big ape climbing cliffs, digging through highly destructible ground, and bashing enemies into one another with massive punches, alongside classic 2D and mine cart sections.</p>
<p>Nintendo will send out invitations for "priority" purchasing of the Switch 2, direct from the company, starting on May 8. Those who have purchased a Switch Online membership as of April 2, have had it for a minimum of 12 months, have opted to share gameplay data, and have logged at least 50 hours get priority. There will be a 72-hour window in which to use priority purchasing invitations.</p>
<p><em>This is a developing story and will be updated as new information comes in.</em></p>


          
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why is the world losing color? (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.culture-critic.com/p/why-is-the-world-losing-color</link>
            <guid>43557471</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 15:02:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.culture-critic.com/p/why-is-the-world-losing-color">https://www.culture-critic.com/p/why-is-the-world-losing-color</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43557471">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.culture-critic.com/p/why-is-the-world-losing-color: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Google built its Gemini robotics models (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.google/products/gemini/how-we-built-gemini-robotics/</link>
            <guid>43557310</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 14:47:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.google/products/gemini/how-we-built-gemini-robotics/">https://blog.google/products/gemini/how-we-built-gemini-robotics/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43557310">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

    
    





    

    
      

<div data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Hero Menu&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models&quot;
  }">
      <div>
          
            <p>Apr 01, 2025</p>
          
          
            <p data-reading-time-render="">[[read-time]] min read</p>
          
        </div>
      
        <p>
          Powered by Gemini Robotics models, robots can learn complex actions like preparing salads, playing games like Tic-Tac-Toe and even folding an origami fox.
        </p>
      
    </div>

    

    
      










<div>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img alt="A still of a white and black robot in a kitchen packing a blue lunchbox" data-component="uni-progressive-image" fetchpriority="high" height="150px" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-HeroImage_2096x1182.width-200.format-webp.webp" width="360px" data-sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw,(min-width: 1024px and max-width: 1259) 80vw, 1046px" data-srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-HeroImage_2096x1182.width-800.format-webp.webp 800w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-HeroImage_2096x1182.width-1200.format-webp.webp 1200w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-HeroImage_2096x1182.width-1600.format-webp.webp 1600w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-HeroImage_2096x1182.width-2200.format-webp.webp 2200w">
        </p>
      </div>
      
    </figure>
  </div>






    

    
    <div data-reading-time="true" data-component="uni-article-body">

            
              





<uni-article-speakable page-title="How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models" listen-to-article="Listen to article" data-date-modified="2025-04-01T21:25:21.117181+00:00" data-tracking-ids="G-HGNBTNCHCQ,G-6NKTLKV14N" data-voice-list="en.ioh-pngnat:Cyan,en.usb-pngnat:Lime" data-script-src="https://www.gstatic.com/readaloud/player/web/api/js/api.js"></uni-article-speakable>

            

            
            
<!--article text-->

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="0u55q">As Google DeepMind prepared for <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/gemini-robotics-brings-ai-into-the-physical-world/">its recent announcement</a> of a new family of Gemini 2.0 models designed specifically for robots, its head of robotics, Carolina Parada, gathered her team for another check of the tech’s capabilities.</p><p data-block-key="752j6">They asked a bi-arm ALOHA robot — a duo of limber metal appendages with multiple joints and pincer-like hands used widely in research — to perform tasks it hadn’t done before, using objects it hadn’t seen. “We did random things like put my shoe on the table and ask it to put some pens inside,” Carolina says. “The robot took a moment to understand the task, then did it.”</p><p data-block-key="a5acc">For the next request, they found a toy basketball hoop and ball and asked the robot to do a “slam dunk.” Carolina watched, proud and delighted, as it did just that.</p></div>
  

  
    






<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="A GIF shows a black robot arm picking up a small orange ball and placing it into a miniature toy basketball hoop. A prompt, Pick up the basketball and slam dunk it, is written out at the bottom of the GIF." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="Robot dunk" or-mp4-video-url="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/original_videos/Robotics-Inline-RobotDunk.mp4" section-header="How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="uv3a7">Carolina says witnessing the slam dunk was a “wow” moment.</p>
    </div>
  
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="0u55q">“We’d trained models to help robots with specific tasks and to understand natural language before, but this was a step change,” Carolina says. “The robot had never seen anything related to basketball, or this specific toy. Yet it understood something complex — ‘slam dunk the ball’ — and performed the action smoothly. <i>On its first try.</i>”</p><p data-block-key="e1ol8">This all-rounder robot was powered by a <a href="https://deepmind.google/technologies/gemini-robotics/">Gemini Robotics</a> model that is part of a new family of multimodal models for robotics. The models build upon <a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/google-gemini-ai-update-december-2024/">Gemini 2.0</a> through fine-tuning with robot-specific data, adding physical action to Gemini’s multimodal outputs like text, video and audio. "This milestone lays the foundation for the next generation of robotics that can be helpful across a range of applications," said Google CEO Sundar Pichai when <a href="https://x.com/sundarpichai/status/1899838913054744679">announcing the new models on X</a>.</p><p data-block-key="46l5k">The Gemini Robotics models are highly dextrous, interactive and general, meaning they can drive robots to react to new objects, environments and instructions without further training. Helpful, given the team’s ambitions.</p><p data-block-key="ev3sg">“Our mission is to build embodied AI to power robots that help you with everyday tasks in the real world,” says Carolina, whose fascination with robotics began with childhood sci-fi cartoons, fueled by dreams of automated chores. “Eventually, robots will be just another surface on which we interact with AI, like our phones or computers — agents in the physical world.”</p></div>
  

  
    
  
    


  <uni-youtube-player-article index="4" thumbnail-alt="A humanoid robot stands opposite a person looking at their laptop. In white text, the words Gemini 2.0 + Robotics are overlaid." video-id="4MvGnmmP3c0" video-type="video" image="Robotics-Inline1" video-image-url-lazy="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline1.width-100.format-webp.webp" video-image-url-mobile="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline1.width-700.format-webp.webp" video-image-url-desktop="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline1.width-1000.format-webp.webp">
  </uni-youtube-player-article>


  


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="0u55q">Like people, robots need two main functions to perform tasks effectively and safely: the ability to understand and make decisions, and the ability to take action. Gemini Robotics-ER, an "embodied reasoning” model built on Gemini 2.0 Flash, focuses on the former, recognizing elements in front of it, defining their size and location, and predicting the trajectory and grip required to move them. It then can generate code to execute the action. We’re now making this model available to trusted testers and partners.</p><p data-block-key="e4isc">Google DeepMind is also introducing Gemini Robotics, its most advanced vision-language-action model, which allows robots to reason about a scene, interact with the user and take action. Crucially, it makes significant advances in an area that has proved tricky for roboticists: dexterity. “What comes naturally to humans is difficult for robots,” Carolina explains. “Dexterity requires both spatial reasoning, and complex physical manipulation. Across testing, Gemini Robotics has set a new state-of-the-art for dexterity, solving complex multi-step tasks with smooth motions and great completion times.”</p></div>
  

  
    






<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="This is a collage of visualizations showcasing these capabilities. Top left: 2D object detection, top right: pointing, bottom left: multi-view correspondence, bottom right: 3d object detection." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="uv3a7">Gemini Robotics-ER excels at embodied reasoning capabilities, including detecting objects and pointing at object parts, finding corresponding points and detecting objects in 3D.</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="This is a collage of visualizations showcasing these capabilities. Top left: 2D object detection, top right: pointing, bottom left: multi-view correspondence, bottom right: 3d object detection." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline2.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline2.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline2.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="0u55q">Powered by Gemini Robotics, machines have prepared salads, packed kids’ lunches, played games like Tic-Tac-Toe and even folded an origami fox.</p><p data-block-key="9067r">Preparing models that could do many different kinds of tasks was a challenge — largely because it went against the general industry practice of training models for a <i>single</i> task over and over until it can be solved. “Instead, we chose broad task learning, training models on a huge number of tasks,” Carolina says. “We expected to see generalization emerge after a certain amount of time, and we were right.”</p><p data-block-key="284af">Both models can adapt to multiple embodiments, including academic-focused robots, like the bi-arm ALOHA machine, or humanoid robots like Apollo developed by our partner Apptronik.</p></div>
  

  
    






<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Four images of robots performing actions. In the top left, a humanoid robot is packing a lunch, in the top right a small arm can be seen picking up a snap pea from a tupperware container, in the bottom left two large white arms ready for a task on a bench, and in the bottom right a black pincer hand holds a whiteboard eraser atop a whiteboard." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="uv3a7">The models adapt to different embodiments, able to perform tasks like packing a lunchbox or wiping a whiteboard in different forms.</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="Four images of robots performing actions. In the top left, a humanoid robot is packing a lunch, in the top right a small arm can be seen picking up a snap pea from a tupperware container, in the bottom left two large white arms ready for a task on a bench, and in the bottom right a black pincer hand holds a whiteboard eraser atop a whiteboard." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline3.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline3.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Robotics-Inline3.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;How we built the new family of Gemini Robotics models&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="0u55q">This ability to adapt is key to a future where robots could take on a number of very different roles.</p><p data-block-key="7tp33">“The possibilities for robots using highly general and capable models are broad and exciting,” Carolina says. “They could be more useful in industries where setups are complex, precision is important and the spaces aren’t human-friendly. And they could be helpful in human-centric spaces, like the home. That’s some years away, but these models are taking us several steps closer.”</p><p data-block-key="6ofc8">Sounds like someone will get some help with those chores — eventually.</p></div>
  


            
            

            
              




            
          </div>
  </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A dramatic Einstein ring seen by Webb (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-04-einstein-webb.html</link>
            <guid>43557139</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 14:32:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phys.org/news/2025-04-einstein-webb.html">https://phys.org/news/2025-04-einstein-webb.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43557139">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
										
<div data-thumb="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/a-dramatic-einstein-ri.jpg" data-src="https://scx2.b-cdn.net/gfx/news/2025/a-dramatic-einstein-ri.jpg" data-sub-html="A spiral galaxy lensed around a closer elliptical galaxy. Credit: ESA/Webb, NASA &amp; CSA, G. Mahler">
        <figure>
            <img src="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/800a/2025/a-dramatic-einstein-ri.jpg" alt="A dramatic Einstein ring seen by Webb" title="A spiral galaxy lensed around a closer elliptical galaxy. Credit: ESA/Webb, NASA &amp; CSA, G. Mahler" width="800" height="530">
             <figcaption>
                A spiral galaxy lensed around a closer elliptical galaxy. Credit: ESA/Webb, NASA &amp; CSA, G. Mahler
            </figcaption>        </figure>
    </div><p>One of the first verified predictions of general relativity is the gravitational deflection of starlight. The effect was <a href="https://briankoberlein.com/post/einstein-and-eddington/" target="_blank">first observed in 1919</a> during a total solar eclipse. Since stars appear as points of light, the effect is seen as an apparent shift in the position of stars near the eclipse. But the effect happens more generally.</p>


										    
																					<p>If a distant galaxy is obscured by a closer one, some of the distant light is gravitationally lensed around the closer galaxy, giving us a warped and distorted view of the faraway stars. This effect can also magnify the distant galaxy, making its light appear brighter, and we have used this effect to observe some of the most distant stars in the universe.</p>
<p>But perhaps the most beautiful effect of gravitational lensing is what's known as an Einstein Ring. This is where the <a href="https://phys.org/tags/distant+galaxy/" rel="tag">distant galaxy</a> is so perfectly centered behind the closer galaxy that its light is distorted into a circle of light. Einstein was aware of the effect but said in 1936 that "there is no hope of observing this phenomenon directly." But as brilliant as Einstein was, he couldn't imagine the power of modern telescopes.</p>
<p>We have now found dozens of Einstein rings, and one of the more beautiful examples was recently found by JWST, as seen in the image above. The close galaxy in the foreground is an <a href="https://phys.org/tags/elliptical+galaxy/" rel="tag">elliptical galaxy</a> that's part of a large cluster known as SMACS J0028.2-7537. The more colorful galaxy warped around it is a <a href="https://phys.org/tags/spiral+galaxy/" rel="tag">spiral galaxy</a> similar to the Milky Way. It is billions of years more distant, but perfectly aligned to create the almost perfect ring.</p>
<p>Of course, this image is only possible because of our vantage point. Astronomers in other galaxies wouldn't catch such a wondrous image. Yet another astronomical example of how beauty is not only in the eye of the beholder, but also where that beholder is.</p>

																														
																					
																					
                              										                                        
										<!-- print only -->
										<div>
											 <p><strong>Citation</strong>:
												A dramatic Einstein ring seen by Webb (2025, April 1)
												retrieved 2 April 2025
												from https://phys.org/news/2025-04-einstein-webb.html
											 </p>
											 <p>
											 This document is subject to copyright. Apart from any fair dealing for the purpose of private study or research, no
											 part may be reproduced without the written permission. The content is provided for information purposes only.
											 </p>
										</div>
                                        
									</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tesla suffers worst quarter since 2022 as deliveries tumble (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ft.com/content/0ebcec51-2a5a-4820-99e8-1e500370fd68</link>
            <guid>43556443</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 13:27:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/0ebcec51-2a5a-4820-99e8-1e500370fd68">https://www.ft.com/content/0ebcec51-2a5a-4820-99e8-1e500370fd68</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43556443">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><a data-trackable="a11y-skip-to-help" href="https://www.ft.com/accessibility">Accessibility help</a><a data-trackable="a11y-skip-to-navigation" href="#site-navigation">Skip to navigation</a><a data-trackable="a11y-skip-to-content" href="#site-content">Skip to content</a><a data-trackable="a11y-skip-to-footer" href="#site-footer">Skip to footer</a></p><div id="barrier-page"><div id="heroOffer-Hero offer-42b5928c-43f2-4f6c-8278-02b0ba2b0d8a" data-component="heroOffer" data-component-unique-name="Hero offer"><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 L6"><p><span></span><span></span><span></span><span>Subscribe to unlock this article</span><span></span></p></div><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 L6"><p><h2><span>Try unlimited access</span></h2><h2><strong><span>Only </span><span>CHF1</span><span> for 4 weeks</span></strong></h2></p><p><span>Then </span><span>CHF85</span><span> per month.
Complete digital access to quality FT journalism on any device. 
Cancel anytime during your trial.</span></p></div></div><div id="recommendedOffers-Recommended offers" data-component="recommendedOffers" data-component-unique-name="Recommended offers"><p><h2 data-o-grid-colspan="12">Explore more offers.</h2></p><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw/https://barrier-page-components.s3.eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_standard.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p><p><h3>Standard Digital</h3></p></div><p><span>CHF55</span><span> per month</span></p><p><span>Essential digital access to quality FT journalism on any device. Pay a year upfront and save 20%.</span></p></div><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw/https://barrier-page-components.s3.eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_premium.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p></div><p><span>CHF85</span><span> per month</span></p><p><span>Complete digital access to quality FT journalism with expert analysis from industry leaders. Pay a year upfront and save 20%.</span></p></div><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div><p><img src="https://www.ft.com/__origami/service/image/v2/images/raw/https://barrier-page-components.s3.eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/assets/icons/primary_product_icon_bundle.svg?source=next-barrier-page&amp;format=svg" alt=""></p></div><p><span>CHF89</span><span> per month</span></p><p><span>Complete digital access to quality analysis and expert insights, complemented with our award-winning Weekend Print edition.</span></p></div></div></div><div data-component="subscriptionOptions" data-component-unique-name="Subscription options"><h2>Explore our full range of subscriptions.</h2><div><div><p>Discover all the plans currently available in your country</p></div><div><p>Digital access for organisations. Includes exclusive features and content.</p></div></div></div><div data-component="whyFT" data-component-unique-name="Why FT"><div><h2>Why the FT?</h2><p>See why over a million readers pay to read the Financial Times.</p></div><p><a href="https://subs.ft.com/whytheft?ft-content-uuid=0ebcec51-2a5a-4820-99e8-1e500370fd68">Find out why</a></p></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds (159 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.unsw.edu.au/newsroom/news/2025/03/sports-supplement-creatine-makes-no-difference-to-muscle-gains-trial-finds</link>
            <guid>43556350</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 13:16:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/newsroom/news/2025/03/sports-supplement-creatine-makes-no-difference-to-muscle-gains-trial-finds">https://www.unsw.edu.au/newsroom/news/2025/03/sports-supplement-creatine-makes-no-difference-to-muscle-gains-trial-finds</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43556350">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    
    <p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-1684635184" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">


<div>

    
        <div>
            <p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-1894355656" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">


<div>
            <p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-1969239712" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">


<div>
            
<p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-279665898" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">
<div>
    <p><span><strong>People hoping to build muscle with the support of a creatine supplement might be disappointed by new research which shows it has little to no effect when taken at the recommended level.&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></span></p>
<p>People who take the popular sports supplement creatine and lift weights do not build muscle any faster than those who do resistance training without the supplement, new research shows. &nbsp;</p>
<p>A UNSW-led clinical trial that put 54 people through a 12-week resistance training program found no difference between those who took the supplement at the recommended dose and those who did not, the research published in <i><a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/17/6/1081" target="_blank" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_Nutrients" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="Nutrients">Nutrients</a></i> shows.</p>
<p>Both groups in the randomised control trial put on an average of two kilograms of lean body mass during the program, which involved three supervised resistance training sessions per week.</p>
<p>“We’ve shown that taking five grams of creatine supplement per day does not make any difference to the amount of lean muscle mass people put on while resistance training,” said senior author <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/staff/mandy-hagstrom" target="_self" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_Dr Mandy Hagstrom" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="Dr Mandy Hagstrom">Dr Mandy Hagstrom</a>, from UNSW’s <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/medicine-health/our-schools/health-sciences" target="_self" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_School of Health Sciences" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="School of Health Sciences">School of Health Sciences</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“The benefits of creatine may have been overestimated in the past, due to methodological problems with previous studies,” she added.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Creatine is a naturally occurring compound which supplies energy to muscles. It is produced by the liver, pancreas and kidneys, and found in protein-rich foods. Previous research shows creatine supplements help build muscles, enhance athletic performance, and may even have cognitive benefits.&nbsp;</p>
<p>However, previous trials have started supplementation and exercise programs on the same day, making it difficult to separate the effect of each on muscle gains, Dr Hagstrom said. They’ve also overlooked the potential for creatine to cause water retention, though more research was needed to confirm this.</p>
<p>So, in this trial, those in the supplement group started on creatine one week before the exercise program began, taking five grams per day, which is at the upper end of the recommended maintenance dose of three to five grams.</p>
<p>“We had what we call a wash-in phase, where half of the participants started taking the supplement, without changing anything else in their daily life, to give their body a chance to stabilise in terms of its response to the supplement,” Dr Hagstrom said.&nbsp;</p>

</div>

    

</span>


</p>


        </div>



</span></p>


        </div>



</span></p>


        </div>
    
        <div>
<p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-338757124" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">


<div>
            
<p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-1242052858" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">
<div>
    <h3>Media enquiries</h3>
<p>For enquiries about this story and interview requests, please contact&nbsp;<strong>Kate Burke</strong>, News &amp; Content Coordinator, UNSW Medicine &amp; Health.</p>
<p>Tel:&nbsp;<a href="tel:+61%202%209348%202538" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_+61 2 9348 2538" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="+61 2 9348 2538">+61 2 9348 2538</a><br>
Email:&nbsp;<a href="mailto:kate.burke@unsw.edu.au" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_kate.burke@unsw.edu.au" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="kate.burke@unsw.edu.au">kate.burke@unsw.edu.au</a></p>

</div>

    

</span>


</p>

<div data-component_type="featured-experts" data-component_id="featured-experts-1934311351" data-component_title="Featured experts">
    <p><img src="https://api.research.unsw.edu.au/sites/default/files/images/profile/head%20shot%20for%20moodle.jpg" alt="Mandy Hagstrom">
    </p>
  
    <p><img src="https://api.research.unsw.edu.au/sites/default/files/images/profile/Headshot-3_0.JPG" alt="Imtiaz Desai">
    </p>
  </div>


        </div>



</span></p></div>
    
</div>



</span></p>
<p><span data-component_type="image-full-width" data-component_id="image-full-width-772239149" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">
<div data-cmp-is="image" data-cmp-src="/content/unsw-sites/au/en/newsroom/news/2025/03/sports-supplement-creatine-makes-no-difference-to-muscle-gains-trial-finds/_jcr_content/root/responsivegrid-layout-fixed-width/responsivegrid-full-top/image-full-width.coreimg.82{.width}.jpeg/1742439022601/25-03-adobestock-1279135268.jpeg" data-cmp-widths="335,700,1170,1280,1920" data-asset="/content/dam/images/medicine-health/health-sciences/stock/2025-03-creatine/25_03_AdobeStock_1279135268.jpeg" data-title="People taking creatine put on the same amount of muscle as those not taking the supplement, over the course of a 12-week resistance training program, the trial findings show. " itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject">
            
                
                
                
                
                <p><span itemprop="caption">People taking creatine put on the same amount of muscle as those not taking the supplement, over the course of a 12-week resistance training program, the trial findings show. </span>
                    
                    <span itemprop="subtitle">Photo: Adobe, AI Generated.</span>
                </p>
            
        </div>
</span>
</p>
<p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-669001312" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">
<div>
    <h2>The effect of creatine with and without resistance training</h2>
<p>During that first week people taking creatine gained more lean body mass, particularly women, gaining an average of 0.5 kilograms more than the control group. However, the extra gains they made varied greatly, and soon dropped back to match those of the control group.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“The people taking the creatine supplement saw changes before they even started exercising, which leads us to believe that it wasn’t actual real muscle growth, but potentially fluid retention,” Dr Hagstrom said.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“Then once they started exercising, they saw no additional benefit from creatine which suggests that five grams per day is not enough if you’re taking it for the purposes of building muscle.”&nbsp;</p>
<p>By comparison, previous trials with no wash-in period found those on creatine gained one kilogram more muscle, than those not taking the supplement, during trials spanning four to 12 weeks.</p>
<p>“In theory then you would have expected our creatine group to put on three kilograms of muscle over the 12-week program, but they didn’t,” said first author <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/staff/imtiaz-desai">Dr Imtiaz Desai</a>, from UNSW’s School of Health Sciences and <a href="https://neura.edu.au/" target="_blank" data-click_category="TextComponentRichText" data-click_id="text_Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA)" data-click_title="RichText" data-click_name="Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA)">Neuroscience Research Australia (NeuRA)</a>.&nbsp;</p>

</div>

    

</span>


</p>
<p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-1284124258" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">
<div>
    <p>The participants, aged 18 to 50, were all relatively healthy people doing less than the recommended minimum of 150 minutes of moderate intensity exercise per week.</p>
<div><p>They were put through the same training program and had their measurements taken at multiple stages using dual energy X-ray absorptiometry, a non-invasive imaging technique that measures bone mineral density (BMD) and body composition. They were also required to keep a food log three days prior to each assessment, which showed no significant differences in their diets.&nbsp;</p><p>
&nbsp;
Those on creatine did bypass a loading phase, which includes taking 20 to 25 grams daily for up to one week. While it is common to start with a loading phase, it can cause gastrointestinal issues and is not necessary to reach saturation levels – the maximum that the body can store at any one time.&nbsp;</p></div>

</div>

    

</span>


</p>
<p><span data-component_type="image" data-component_id="image-725853030" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">
<div data-cmp-is="image" data-cmp-src="/content/unsw-sites/au/en/newsroom/news/2025/03/sports-supplement-creatine-makes-no-difference-to-muscle-gains-trial-finds/_jcr_content/root/responsivegrid-layout-fixed-width/responsivegrid-full-top/image.coreimg.82{.width}.jpeg/1742436149986/adobestock-457423221-%281%29.jpeg" data-cmp-widths="335,700,1170,1280,1920" data-asset="/content/dam/images/unsw-wide/general/news/2025/2025-01-newsroom/AdobeStock_457423221 (1).jpeg" data-title="Instead of delivering extra muscle gains, researchers found creatine had a short-term impact on weight gain, which they suspect was caused by water retention." itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject">
            
                
                
                
                
                <p><span itemprop="caption">Instead of delivering extra muscle gains, researchers found creatine had a short-term impact on weight gain, which they suspect was caused by water retention.</span>
                    
                    <span itemprop="subtitle">Photo: Adobe/Kegfire</span>
                </p>
            
        </div>
</span>
</p>
<p><span data-component_type="text" data-component_id="text-857421423" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">
<div>
    <h2><strong>More research needed on creatine doses</strong></h2>
<p>The trial suggests people need to take more creatine than is commonly thought to get the desired benefit of additional muscle gains, the experts say.</p>
<div><p>Just how much more will need to be the subject of further research, but 10 grams could be the dose to test first, given it's already shown to be safe and promising for both brain and bone health, Dr Hagstrom said.&nbsp;</p><p>
&nbsp;
A longer study would also be beneficial, added Dr Desai, as would measuring body water content, tracking the menstrual cycle – which can affect fluid retention – and creatine absorption, which was not feasible for this trial.&nbsp;</p></div>
<div><p>“It would be really interesting to see if creatine has more of a long-term benefit,” said Dr Desai. “When you start weight training, you have those beginner gains in strength and those start tapering off around the 12-week mark and become slower, so it’s possible the support from creatine might come at a later stage.”&nbsp;</p><p>
&nbsp;
In the meantime, the researchers hope it will give people more realistic expectations on creatine use, and prompt them to question claims made in the marketing of some supplements. &nbsp;</p><p>
&nbsp;
“For your average person taking creatine to boost their gains in the gym, this will hopefully change their perception about what it can help them achieve,” Dr Desai said. “For professional athletes, particularly those who must be at a particular weight for their sport, the findings may inform how and when they take the supplement.”&nbsp;</p><p>
&nbsp;
As for researchers, it’s hoped the study may encourage others to start to use a wash-in phase, to better understand the impact of supplements with and without exercise.&nbsp;</p></div>

</div>

    

</span>


</p>



<div>
<p><span data-component_type="column-layout" data-component_id="column_layout-1684635187" data-component_title="Sports supplement creatine makes no difference to muscle gains, trial finds">


<div>
            <p><span data-component_type="heading" data-component_id="heading-1965971606" data-component_title="Related stories">
  <h3 id="heading-1965971606">
      Related stories
  </h3>
</span>


    

</p>





        </div>



</span></p></div>

    
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A steam locomotive from 1993 broke my yarn test (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/yarn-test-suffers-strange-derailment/</link>
            <guid>43556280</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 13:10:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/yarn-test-suffers-strange-derailment/">https://blog.cloudflare.com/yarn-test-suffers-strange-derailment/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43556280">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://blog.cloudflare.com/yarn-test-suffers-strange-derailment/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An 'administrative error' sent a Maryland man to an El Salvador prison (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/el-salvador-deportation-maryland-man-trump-error-818a0fa1218de714448edcb5be1f7347</link>
            <guid>43555724</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 11:54:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/el-salvador-deportation-maryland-man-trump-error-818a0fa1218de714448edcb5be1f7347">https://apnews.com/article/el-salvador-deportation-maryland-man-trump-error-818a0fa1218de714448edcb5be1f7347</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43555724">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://apnews.com/article/el-salvador-deportation-maryland-man-trump-error-818a0fa1218de714448edcb5be1f7347: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[RIP Val Kilmer: Real Genius .. the Film Nerd Culture Deserves (2015) (315 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://reactormag.com/30-years-later-real-genius-is-still-the-geek-solidarity-film-that-nerd-culture-deserves/</link>
            <guid>43555334</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 10:33:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://reactormag.com/30-years-later-real-genius-is-still-the-geek-solidarity-film-that-nerd-culture-deserves/">https://reactormag.com/30-years-later-real-genius-is-still-the-geek-solidarity-film-that-nerd-culture-deserves/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43555334">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <p>It’s&nbsp;interesting to me that <em>Revenge of the Nerds</em>, while still full up of the nostalgia that the 80s lends us, is lately being <a href="http://the-toast.net/2014/09/30/sexual-racial-politics-nerd-culture-dialogue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">repositioned in the zeitgeist</a>. What was viewed for many years as a bit of harmless fun that waved the banner for nerds everywhere is finally being called out for exactly what it is; an Us vs Them revenge fest that never lets go of racism or misogyny, and damages the image of geek culture more than it applauds for it. That shouldn’t be surprising—<em>RotN</em> was always just a frat house comedy with a thin nerdy gloss applied to it. And that’s fine with me, because that was never my go-to movie for feeling the geeky solidarity.</p>
<p>No, my friends. That movie was <em>Real Genius</em>.</p>

<p><em>Real Genius</em> was loosely (very very <em>very</em> loosely) inspired by actual events that took place when university students were working to&nbsp;crack laser technology. But in <em>Real Genius</em>, this is being done on the fictional Pacific Tech campus, where the students are unknowingly creating that laser for the CIA to use in government sanctioned hits from space. They don’t know this because their odious professor, Dr. Hathaway (played to a tee by William Atherton), obviously isn’t letting them in on the secret. He’s too busy skimming off the funds that the government is providing to the project, so he can renovate his house.</p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius3.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius3.jpg" alt="Real Genius, Mitch Taylor" width="740" height="314"></a></p>
<p>Our protagonist is fifteen-year-old Mitch Taylor (Gabriel Jarrett), who is accepted early to Pacific Tech because, well, he’s a genius. He’s assigned to the laser project, working with his new roommate Chris Knight (Val Kilmer), a senior at the school who appears to have given up on taking college all that seriously. So… burnt out upper classman plus eager-to-please, impressionable freshman? We’re already set up for some prime Odd Couple shenanigans. We’re introduced to a guy named Kent and his cronies, who are also working on the laser project. Unlike Chris, Kent is the ultimate sycophant and only too happy to throw other students under the bus provided he gets to be top dog. So now we have a rivalry. Mitch meets a lot of strange people at Pacific Tech, one of them being Jordan, one of the campus’ few women who happens to size Mitch up and make him a sweater the day after meeting him, which she excitedly presents to him in men’s room while he’s peeing. So now we have a love story.</p>
<p>And… that’s pretty much where the comparisons to most college flicks and <em>Real Genius</em> ends. Because the film is about a lot more than that, for all it is a very 80s campus comedy. For one, the movie is better at portraying geeks in ways that don’t just melt down to old tropes of pocket protectors and bow ties and awkwardness. It communicates that having an outrageous IQ can be isolating, but doesn’t make all smart people out to be socially undeveloped shut-ins. It also shows us how being driven toward answers can blind even the most optimistic, well-meaning folks into making terrible mistakes. And it communicates what it’s like to study for finals more realistically than any film I’ve ever seen, which is an accomplishment and a half.</p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius4.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius4.jpg" alt="Real Genius, Chris Knight, Val Kilmer" width="740" height="355"></a></p>
<p>No really, there’s a scene where everyone is gathered around a communal table to cram for the exam, and one guy just gets up and starts <em>screaming</em> at everyone before running from the building. Everyone else is unresponsive and some other dude sitting on the room’s perimeter moves into his vacated seat without comment. That’s basically the experience distilled into its purest form.</p>
<p>Also, did I mention that it ends on a Tears For Fears song? Because that should be enough to recommend it right there.</p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius9.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius9.jpg" alt="Real Genius, 1985" width="740" height="416"></a></p>
<p>Another great thing about this film is how it <em>doesn’t</em> couch itself in the “nerd versus jock” dynamic. It’s a boring cliche that rarely bothers to examine the realities of persecution due to differences. Instead, it herds people into group stereotypes and activity negates character complexity. <em>Real Genius</em> knows this, and most of the rivalry here is geek-on-geek. We watch the very real dynamic of people in the same social circle trying to one-up each other to gain status, stroke their own egos, or flat out cause trouble for fun. When we reach the “party with hot girls” part of the film that so many college movies unthinkingly provide, the narrative beelines away from any form of non-consensual action; the party is full of student beauticians who are keen to meet some boys, and when the guys from Pacific Tech balk at having to talk to them, Chris Knight points out that they might try using their brains to impress them. The most uncomfortable person at the party is not any of the female attendants, but Mitch… understandable because he’s fifteen and this is probably the highest concentration of bikinis he’s ever witnessed. He finally starts having fun when he realizes that Jordan is there, testing scuba equipment in the pool.</p>
<p>The virtually opposing approaches to life that Mitch and Chris represent is the focal point of the tale, the paragon of straight-laced nerd-dom juxtaposed with the free-wheeling, frenetic creativity that Knight gears his mind toward. Mitch is distraught by the fact that a student he’d previously idolized appears to be nothing more than another party-hard slacker who doesn’t seem to care one bit about their work they’re doing. It’s not until later that he finds out this attitude is new; Chris was once just like Mitch, but he relaxed into this new mindset when he followed a man into their dorm room closet. (I swear that’s not a metaphor.) That man—Lazlo Hollyfeld—was a big shot student at Pacific Tech in the decade previous, who went a little out of his mind when he found out that his inventions were being used to harm others. Seeing this, Chris realized that spending his life focused on work for work’s sake was a mistake.</p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius6.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius6.jpg" alt="Real Genius, Dr. Hathaway, William Atherton" width="740" height="359"></a></p>
<p>Unfortunately, Knight’s new groove is making it harder for Dr. Hathaway to meet his laser deadline, so the professor decides to spitefully ruin Chris’ life—giving Kent the post-school job he was already promised and flunking him out of the Pacific Tech program, preventing him from graduating. With a little pep talk from Mitch, Chris throws himself back into their project and makes real headway on the laser just to prove Hathaway wrong. It’s only after they deliver it to Hathaway that Lazlo leaves the steam tunnels below their closet and points out that what they created was likely intended for a very specific purpose—to kill people. From space. From that point on, the crew is on the clock to ruin the laser’s presentation for the military and CIA and to get even with Dr. Hathaway for using them. (Also to prank Kent because he kind of deserves it for being a lapdog and generally horrible to Mitch just because the kid is younger and smarter than he is.)</p>
<p>The film makes it a mission to prove that what geeks and geniuses are best at isn’t memorizing math formulas and elements off the periodic table; it’s their ability to be creative and in doing so, change the world around us. The students do get even with Dr. Hathaway, but they do it in an inspired way that essentially harms no one except him—they redirect the laser so it goes off at his home, where they’ve situated a giant ball of unpopped popcorn. <em>Ka-blooey.</em> Essentially, they destroy the thing that Hathaway was siphoning money off of the laser program to gain, his fancy house. It makes the project seem like a bust, effectively ruins Hathaway, and punishes him for being dishonest. As revenge schemes go, it’s a remarkably fair-minded one that’s fun to boot. And it’s not about proving their superiority over another group, but instead about taking back control over what they’ve created.</p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius5.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius5.jpg" alt="Real Genius, popcorn house" width="740" height="356"></a></p>
<p>The film doesn’t showcase as many women as we might hope for (and the Pacific Tech campus is also blindingly white overall, though Chris’ friend Ikagami is present and happily avoids most of your average Asian stereotypes aside from smartness), but the way it treats the majority of those women is impressive, particularly for this era in filmmaking… no doubt largely due to the movie’s female director, Martha Coolidge. There are few instances of pure objectification just for the sake of it in <em>Real Genius</em>; even though the co-ed party shows plenty of girls in swimsuits, the shots that reveal them are often at a distance, never lingering. While Knight is blunt in his sexual overtures to women, the ones he encounters are more than capable of tackling his advances and throwing them back in his face when he’s not up to snuff. His directness gives him no power, which is extremely important because it indicates that not every woman is automatically going to swoon over that kind of come-on. (Which, in turn, suggests that women are real, unique individuals with different preferences.) And when they aren’t interested, Chris is never entitled or angry about it—he simply moves on.</p>
<p>I really can’t talk about women in this film without focusing up on Jordan Cochran. While she does occupy a typically female place in the plot (Mitch’s love interest), her portrayal by Michelle Meyrink is nothing short of revelatory when it comes to broadening the variety of women that we should expect in fiction. To start, Jordan is not a conventionally attractive girl, certainly not in a California/feature film sense. She has a weird haircut and a child-like cadence to her voice, and she’s not particularly fashionable. It’s also entirely possible for this character to read somewhere on the autistic spectrum, though by way of a Hollywoodified lens; she is uncertain of common boundaries (visiting Mitch in the bathroom and being perturbed by his inability to pee in front of her), she has severe insomnia (it’s suggested that she drove her roommate to a nervous breakdown by never ever sleeping), she misunderstands the social cues of others (she frequently assumes the ends of Mitch’s sentences incorrectly), and her idea of what constitutes an everyday activity would hardly pass for your average citizen (Mitch finds her sanding her dorm room floor late one night and she uses the beautician party as an excuse to test a rebreather she designed herself). It’s not the fact that she might be on the spectrum itself that’s remarkable, but the fact that the film never suggests that Jordan should be viewed differently because of it. It doesn’t make her “special” in a manic pixie dream way, but it doesn’t make her pitiable either. She’s simply who she is, and that person is still portrayed as desirable and engaging and brilliant.</p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius8.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius8.jpg" alt="Real Genius, Jordan Cochran" width="740" height="357"></a></p>
<p>It helps that she’s very much her own kind of genius. Jordan makes most of her own equipment, clearly comfortable with a variety of tools and practical materials. She isn’t involved in the laser project whatsoever—in fact, we’re never told what Jordan is at Pacific Tech to do aside from being some sort of eclectic savant who cares about sled velocity on ice and the smoothness of her floors. She comes off as a kind of mad scientist, probably the sort of person to invent a few hundred incredibly useful patents throughout the course of her life and hopefully retire rich with a giant lab/workshop in her basement where she can create gorgeous metalwork in peace. Prior to <em>Real Genius</em>, Meyrink appeared in <em>Revenge of the Nerds</em> as one of the members of Omega Mu, the nerd girl sorority. In that movie, she and her Greek sisters were figures to be laughed at. Here, she is an odd force to be reckoned with. There is simply no comparison; one of these characters is inspirational to young women, and the other is decidedly not. In the end, Jordan’s status as Mitch’s girlfriend has very little to do with her place in the story (outside of letting her meet these characters and form friendships with them), an effective 180 from her position as&nbsp;Gilbert’s&nbsp;love interest&nbsp;in <em>Revenge of the Nerds</em>. Jordan is a heroic character in <em>Real Genius</em>, whereas Judy is largely a trophy for the (male) hero in <em>RotN</em>.</p>
<p>What’s also impressive about <em>Real Genius</em> is that it allows its focal character, Mitch Taylor, to be as young as he is, with all the embarrassment and strangeness that being fifteen entails. Mitch calls his parents crying because college isn’t working out the way he’d prefer, and he begs to come home. Mitch is cornered alone by an older, more experienced woman who clearly wants to teach him “the ways of the world,” but he runs from the scenario, owning up to his discomfort and knowing that he’d rather be with Jordan.<span>&nbsp; </span>The film never makes fun of Mitch for being less advanced than his peers or a perceived “square,” never sniggers at him for being the straight-laced one who cares about his work. It’s never suggested that he should simply play along, act older, learn to enjoy things that don’t interest him. Chris Knight has to convince him to loosen up by presenting real, hard data on why sticking too hard to the work might hurt him in the long run. And even then, Mitch doesn’t become a mini version of his mentor—he simply takes Knight’s advice to heart and figures out what his own version of relaxed is.</p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius2.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius2.jpg" alt="Real Genius, Mitch Taylor, Chris Knight" width="740" height="317"></a></p>
<p>Rather than placing geeks on someone else’s playground, forcing them into an opposing socially-constructed box and proving that they can “play the game” better than everyone else by virtue of being smarter, <em>Real Genius</em> shows that nerds have their own games. They don’t need to run faster or get more pledges or give themselves makeovers to have fun and prove their worth. Mitch wakes up to a hall full of ice one morning; Ikagami has somehow created a gas that turns into the slippery stuff, and then back into a gas after a few hours. Chris hails the accomplishment as “Pacific Tech’s: Smart People on Ice!” The walls of the dorms are covered in strange graffiti, people shuffle back and forth between common areas and rooms in their weird-looking pajamas and towels. Knight has appointed himself as the dorm resident in charge of fun, trying to get people away from their books with “Mutant Hamster Races” and “Madame Curie Lookalike Contests.” In short, it’s like any other college campus, complete with overworked students. Nerds are not a rare and exotic breed of people, but they do make some awesome stuff, and that’s why they make for good movie plots.</p>
<p>It also helps that <em>Real Genius</em> might be one of the most quotable films on the planet. Even Joss Whedon would cry at how snappy the dialogue is, which is recommendation enough over most college movies where dialogue can be horrifically contrived. Chris Knight is the primary conduit of said snappiness, and you have to wonder how many of Kilmer’s lines are ad-libbed, because it seems like it might be a lot of them. It’s encouraging to have a character who at the start appears to be such a parody of himself—the super-smart-guy-who-can-also-be-a-jerk-because-he’s-good-looking-and-snarky—turn out to be a genuinely decent person who cares about people. And he proves that by changing his tactics with others; when he realizes that Mitch is not responding to devil-may-care antics, he quits the act and explains his reasons for exhibiting rather extreme senioritis. It comes clear very quickly that his primary reason for asking Dr. Hathaway to make Mitch his roommate is to make certain that Mitch doesn’t make his (or Lazlo’s) mistakes. Without realizing that they’re already being lured into the same gambit that snagged Lazlo years ago, Chris is already trying to provide Mitch with the tools he needs to avoid the scenario. He may be a cynic, as he says, but he’s inciting campus rowdiness to protect everyone’s health and expand their horizons, not to encourage them to blow their educations.</p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius.gif"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://reactormag.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/real-genius.gif" alt="Real Genius, Chris Knight, why do I bother gif" width="720" height="306"></a></p>
<p>In that way, <em>Real Genius</em> occupies an interesting middle ground in how it portrays education for a film that’s all about brainy, bookish people. It’s not suggesting that going to college should be one long non-stop alcohol-fueled party haze, but it’s also not suggesting that what you learn at a higher education facility is the only valuable knowledge you will ever absorb. Life experience is shown to be equally (or even more) valuable. And while it can be easier to retreat into books when you’re a certain kind of person, the tale&nbsp;cautions that it’s important to&nbsp;stay aware of the world around you–otherwise you might miss when you’re being taken advantage of. For a film that’s already 30 years old, the wisdom it displays is universal; value your emotional development as much as your intellectual development; use your abilities to improve the world; question authority; definitely don’t make dangerous weapons for your college professors.</p>
<p>So you can keep <em>Revenge of the Nerds</em>, if that’s your thing, and all the other films of its ilk. They do a fairly poor job of committing the experience of social outsiders to memory. For a film that offers a chance to laugh with people rather than at them, to appreciate what college truly&nbsp;teaches most of us, to embrace what’s really fun about being an unabashed geek, I’d recommend <em>Real Genius</em> every single time.</p>
<p><em>Gif from <a href="http://pandawhale.com/post/53584/real-genius-why-do-i-even-bother-gif" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Panda Whale</a>.</em></p>
<p><a href="https://reactormag.com/Emily%20Asher-Perrin#filter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emmet Asher-Perrin</a>&nbsp;was thinking of the immortal words of Socrates, who said: “…I drank what?” You can bug her on <a href="https://twitter.com/use_theforce_em" target="external-links-new-window" rel="noopener">Twitter</a> and&nbsp;<a href="https://use-theforce-em.tumblr.com/" target="external-links-new-window" rel="noopener">Tumblr</a>, and read more of her work here and elsewhere.</p>

        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Coffea stenophylla: A forgotten bean that could save coffee from extinction (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/how-forgotten-bean-could-save-coffee-from-extinction-180986230/</link>
            <guid>43555286</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 10:25:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/how-forgotten-bean-could-save-coffee-from-extinction-180986230/">https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/how-forgotten-bean-could-save-coffee-from-extinction-180986230/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43555286">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/how-forgotten-bean-could-save-coffee-from-extinction-180986230/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Where does air pollution come from? (225 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ourworldindata.org/air-pollution-sources</link>
            <guid>43553663</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 04:25:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/air-pollution-sources">https://ourworldindata.org/air-pollution-sources</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43553663">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><header><h2>A breakdown of the sources of many air pollutants that damage our health and ecosystems.</h2></header><p><span>Millions of people </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/data-review-air-pollution-deaths" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>die prematurely</span></a><span> from air pollution every year. </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/energy-poverty-air-pollution" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>This problem has existed</span></a><span> since humans started burning materials for fuel — first wood and biomass, then fossil fuels.</span></p><p><span>But it’s an environmental and public health problem that we can make progress on. We know this because the world </span><em><span>has already</span></em><span> </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/cleanest-air-lessons" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>been successful</span></a><span> in reducing air pollutants, and many countries that used to be highly polluted now have much cleaner air than they used to.</span></p><p><span>To tackle air pollution effectively — to&nbsp;focus our efforts on the interventions that will have the biggest impact — we need to understand where it’s coming from.</span></p><p><span>That’s why we wrote this article.</span><a href="#note-1"><sup><span>1</span></sup></a></p><div inert="true"><h2 id="a-note-on-data-and-definitions"><span>A note on data and definitions</span><a href="#a-note-on-data-and-definitions"></a></h2><p><span>The main data source we rely on is the Community Emissions Data System (CEDS). There are a couple of reasons why we think it’s an incredibly valuable resource:</span></p><ul><li><span>It has long-term global and national data extending back to the 18th century and is frequently updated with the latest estimates for 2022.</span></li><li><span>It’s published with an open-access license and transparent methodology and inputs, which you can find </span><a href="https://github.com/JGCRI/CEDS/tree/master" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>on GitHub</span></a><span>. The peer-reviewed paper describing the methodology is </span><a href="https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/11/369/2018/gmd-11-369-2018.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>here</span></a><span>.</span><a href="#note-2"><sup><span>2</span></sup></a></li><li><span>This online data resource is open to user comments and feedback, so errors or issues can be easily reported.</span></li><li><span>CEDS provides clear documentation of data improvements and detailed comparisons of recent updates against previous versions.</span></li></ul><p><span>To be clear, CEDS does not have high-quality </span><em><span>measurements</span></em><span> of emissions of air pollutants — certainly not dating back to the 18th century. These figures are calculated and modeled based on inputs, such as the quantity of different fuels that were burned, technological advancements and pollution controls, fertilizer use, and agricultural production. You can, for example, estimate the amount of sulfur dioxide produced from burning one tonne of coal in a power plant (with or without pollution filters).</span></p><p><span>Of course, this means the data comes with some uncertainty, especially in earlier periods. However, it gives us a reasonable and consistent global dataset to understand how trends in emissions of air pollutants have changed over time.</span></p><p><span>This article will focus on the breakdown of pollutants by their source. For this, we’ll use a categorization based on CEDS’s classification. In the table below, we summarize what is included in each category.</span></p><div><table><tbody><tr><th scope="col"><p><strong><span>Category</span></strong></p></th><th scope="col"><p><strong><span>Sub-categories</span></strong></p></th></tr><tr><td><p><span>Agriculture</span></p></td><td><p><span>Enteric fermentation</span></p><p><span>Fuel use in agriculture, forestry, and fishing</span></p><p><span>Indirect N₂O emissions</span></p><p><span>Manure management</span></p><p><span>Rice cultivation</span></p><p><span>Soil emissions</span></p><p><span>Other agricultural emissions</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>Buildings</span></p></td><td><p><span>Commercial and institutional buildings</span></p><p><span>Residential buildings</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>Domestic aviation</span></p></td><td><p><span>Domestic aviation</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>Energy</span></p></td><td><p><span>Electricity production (autoproducer)</span></p><p><span>Electricity production (public)</span></p><p><span>Fossil fuel fires</span></p><p><span>Fugitive emissions from natural gas distribution</span></p><p><span>Fugitive emissions from natural gas production</span></p><p><span>Fugitive emissions from other energy sources</span></p><p><span>Fugitive emissions from petroleum</span></p><p><span>Fugitive emissions from solid fuels</span></p><p><span>Heat production</span></p><p><span>Other energy transformation</span></p><p><span>Other fuel use (unspecified)</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>Industry</span></p></td><td><p><span>Adipic acid production</span></p><p><span>Aluminum production</span></p><p><span>Cement production</span></p><p><span>Chemical industry</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (chemicals)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (construction)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (food and tobacco)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (iron and steel)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (machinery)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (mining and quarrying)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (non-ferrous metals)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (non-metallic minerals)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (other)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (pulp and paper)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (textile and leather)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (transport equipment)</span></p><p><span>Industrial combustion (wood products)</span></p><p><span>Iron and steel alloy production</span></p><p><span>Lime production</span></p><p><span>Nitric acid production</span></p><p><span>Other mineral production</span></p><p><span>Other non-ferrous metal production</span></p><p><span>Pulp and paper, food, beverage, and wood processing</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>International aviation</span></p></td><td><p><span>International aviation</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>International shipping</span></p></td><td><p><span>International shipping</span></p><p><span>Oil tanker loading</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>Solvents</span></p></td><td><p><span>Chemical products manufacture and processing</span></p><p><span>Degreasing and cleaning</span></p><p><span>Other product use</span></p><p><span>Paint application</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>Transport</span></p></td><td><p><span>Domestic navigation</span></p><p><span>Rail transportation</span></p><p><span>Road transportation</span></p><p><span>Other transport</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span>Waste</span></p></td><td><p><span>Solid waste disposal</span></p><p><span>Waste combustion</span></p><p><span>Wastewater handling</span></p><p><span>Other waste handling</span></p><p><span>Other waste sources</span></p><p><span>Unspecified waste sources</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table></div></div><h2 id="how-air-pollution-damages-our-health"><span>How air pollution damages our health</span><a href="#how-air-pollution-damages-our-health"></a></h2><p><span>Before we discuss the sources of some of the key air pollutants, we should briefly explain how air pollution affects human health and how each of these pollutants contributes to this.</span></p><p><span>There are three key pathways by which a pollutant can cause harm</span><a href="#note-3"><sup><span>3</span></sup></a><span>:</span></p><ul><li><strong><span>Direct exposure:</span></strong><span> Some gases are toxic and can have an acute effect on health. These acute impacts are more common for people with existing respiratory conditions such as asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). This direct exposure does cost lives, but the total number is relatively small compared to the millions that die from chronic exposure to air pollution.</span></li><li><strong><span>Formation of particulate matter: </span></strong><span>Many of the pollutants we’ll look at contribute to health impacts </span><em><span>indirectly</span></em><span> by breaking down to form secondary smaller particles. These particles are called “particulate matter”. Typically, the smaller the particles are, the worse they can be for human health because they can enter our lungs and airways — and, in some cases, the bloodstream. Particulate matter can cause respiratory and cardiovascular problems, including cancer, strokes, and heart attacks.</span></li><li><strong><span>Formation of ozone: </span></strong><span>Another </span><em><span>indirect</span></em><span> way these pollutants can affect our health is by forming a gas called ozone (O</span><sub><span>3</span></sub><span>). Ozone can cause breathing problems and worsen acute conditions like asthma and COPD</span><a href="#note-4"><sup><span>4</span></sup></a><span>. However, it also affects our health through chronic exposure by causing inflammation of the lungs, increasing the risk of respiratory diseases, and reducing our cardiovascular health.</span></li></ul><p><span>As we discuss each pollutant, we’ll briefly explain how it affects health through one or several pathways. While it’s difficult to pinpoint exactly how many deaths each pollutant causes, wherever possible, we’ll also try to give a rough order of magnitude estimate.</span></p><p><span>To give some sense of scale, </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/global-health?tab=chart&amp;Health+Area=Risk+factors&amp;Indicator=Air+pollution&amp;Metric=Number+of+deaths&amp;Source=IHME&amp;country=OWID_WRL~CHN~ZAF~BRA~USA~GBR~IND~RWA"><span>here</span></a><span> is the Global Burden of Disease’s breakdown of global deaths from air pollution.</span><a href="#note-5"><sup><span>5</span></sup></a></p><p><span>In 2021, this totaled around</span><strong><span> 8 million deaths.</span></strong><span> Note that there are also natural sources of particulate matter, so not </span><em><span>all</span></em><span> of these pollution deaths resulted from human emissions. But most did. For more on this, see our colleague Max Roser’s </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/data-review-air-pollution-deaths" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>article</span></a><span>, which looks at estimates from various sources.</span></p><p><strong><span>3.1 million</span></strong><span> came from </span><em><span>household</span></em><span> air pollution, a combination of direct toxicity and particulate matter. </span><strong><span>4.7 million</span></strong><span> came from outdoor particulate matter, and another </span><strong><span>half a million</span></strong><span> from outdoor ozone pollution.</span><a href="#note-6"><sup><span>6</span></sup></a></p><div><figure data-grapher-src="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution"><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><picture><source id="grapher-preview-source" srcset="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution.png?imWidth=850 850w, https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution.png?imWidth=1700 1700w" sizes="(max-width: 850px) 100vw, 850px"><img src="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution.png" width="850" height="600" loading="lazy" data-no-lightbox="true"></picture></a></figure></div><h2 id="breaking-down-the-sources-of-different-air-pollutants"><span>Breaking down the sources of different air pollutants</span><a href="#breaking-down-the-sources-of-different-air-pollutants"></a></h2><h2 id="sulfur-dioxide-the-source-of-acid-rain"><span>Sulfur dioxide: the source of acid rain</span><a href="#sulfur-dioxide-the-source-of-acid-rain"></a></h2><p><span>Sulfur dioxide (SO</span><sub><span>2</span></sub><span>) is the main pollutant that causes </span><a href="https://worksinprogress.co/issue/the-end-of-acid-rain/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>acid rain</span></a><span>. This has been a major environmental problem because acid rain can change the chemistry of rivers and lakes, affecting fish populations, soils, and the extent and quality of forests. You can also see the effects of acid rain on older limestone and marble buildings and statues, where the acidity dissolves parts of the structure.</span></p><p><span>There are two ways that SO</span><sub><span>2</span></sub><span> </span><a href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/en/topics/in-depth/air-pollution/eow-it-affects-our-health" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>can threaten</span></a><span> human health. First, direct inhalation of SO</span><sub><span>2</span></sub><span> can exacerbate respiratory problems such as asthma and bronchitis. But its main contribution is by breaking down to form small particulate matter. While an exact figure is hard to pin down, given that sulfur dioxide is a substantial contributor to particulate matter and that at least 4 million deaths are linked to these small particles yearly, we would estimate that </span><strong><span>hundreds of thousands</span></strong><span> of deaths per year are linked to SO</span><sub><span>2</span></sub><span>.</span></p><p><span>SO</span><sub><span>2</span></sub><span> is formed when we burn fuels that contain sulfur.</span></p><p><span>The charts below show where global emissions come from and how these sectors have changed over time. In 2022, energy production was the biggest contributor by far. This is predominantly due to power from coal, which has sulfur impurities that are released when it’s burned.</span></p><p><span>The main contribution of the industry is the metal smelting process.</span><a href="#note-7"><sup><span>7</span></sup></a><span> This is because many of the ores that are used to produce metals – such as pyrite – contain large amounts of sulfur, which is released when they are roasted at high temperatures.</span></p><p><span>Oil also contains sulfur, which is why road transport, shipping, and aviation all contribute. Shipping emissions have received a lot of attention in the last few years because they </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/air-pollution?country=~OWID_WRL&amp;Pollutant=Sulfur+dioxide&amp;Sector=International+shipping&amp;Per+capita=false"><span>dropped by more than 70%</span></a><span> in 2020 after the introduction of tight regulations on maritime fuels.</span></p><p><span>You’ll notice that global emissions of SO</span><sub><span>2</span></sub><span> peaked in 1979 and have almost halved since then, thanks to the introduction of pollution controls, particularly in Europe, North America, and China. SO</span><sub><span>2 </span></sub><span>can be removed from smokestacks in coal plants using technologies that filter or “scrub” the sulfur away before it’s emitted into the atmosphere. This, combined with a </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/energy?tab=chart&amp;country=USA~GBR~OWID_EU27&amp;Total+or+Breakdown=Select+a+source&amp;Energy+or+Electricity=Electricity+only&amp;Metric=Share+of+total&amp;Select+a+source=Coal"><span>move away from coal</span></a><span> in Europe and North America, has led to a rapid reduction in emissions.</span><sub><span> </span></sub></p><h2 id="nitrogen-oxides-n-ox-the-reason-car-exhaust-fumes-are-so-damaging"><span>Nitrogen oxides (NOₓ): the reason car exhaust fumes are so damaging</span><a href="#nitrogen-oxides-n-ox-the-reason-car-exhaust-fumes-are-so-damaging"></a></h2><p><span>Nitrogen oxides (NOₓ) are a group of gases, mostly made up of nitric oxide (NO) and nitrogen dioxide (NO</span><sub><span>2</span></sub><span>). They are formed when fuels containing nitrogen (again, mostly fossil fuels) are burned, causing them to react with oxygen.</span></p><p><span>Like sulfur dioxide, which we just looked at, NOₓ can cause acid rain, threatening wildlife and ecosystems. NOₓ has a particularly large impact on human health because it acts through all three mechanisms we looked at earlier. It can be acutely toxic, inflaming the lungs. It reacts with other gases to form particulate matter, and it also forms ozone. NOₓ, therefore, causes smog and the thick haze you often see in highly polluted cities.</span></p><p><span>Again, we don’t have exact estimates for how many deaths it contributes to. But, given that it’s a main source of ozone (which kills around half a million) and a substantial fraction of particulate matter (which kills several million), it’s reasonable to expect that NOₓ is linked to </span><strong><span>over a million deaths yearly</span></strong><span>.</span></p><p><span>Since coal, oil, and gas all contain nitrogen, NOₓ is produced in various sectors, as the chart below shows. The biggest source is transport — mostly from road vehicles — where NOₓ is emitted from the exhaust of cars and trucks. This is almost matched by the burning of coal and gas for electricity production, shown as “energy” in the chart. Like road transport, burning fuel for shipping emits significant amounts of NOₓ, making it a leading source, too.</span></p><p><span>And industrial processes such as metal smelting, cement production, and petroleum refining contribute a lot.</span></p><p><span>A smaller but still important source is agriculture. When nitrogen is applied to crops as synthetic fertilizer or manure, some of this nitrogen is converted to nitrogen oxides (and ammonia, which we’ll come on to later) in the soil.</span><a href="#note-8"><sup><span>8</span></sup></a><span> While emissions of NOₓ from processes such as transport and electricity production have declined a lot globally, progress on agriculture has been much slower: emissions have flatlined but have not fallen much.</span></p><p><span>Some countries have been successful in drastically reducing emissions of NOₓ – with huge benefits for human health. Moving away from fossil fuels – particularly coal in electricity production – has led to a large decline in “energy” emissions (have a look at </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/air-pollution?time=1950..2022&amp;Pollutant=Nitrogen+oxides&amp;Sector=All+sectors+%28total%29&amp;Per+capita=false&amp;country=~GBR"><span>the United Kingdom</span></a><span> as an example). Setting pollution control standards for automakers has also played a crucial role in reducing emissions from road transport. NOₓ emissions from exhausts can be dramatically reduced through the use of </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catalytic_converter" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>catalytic converters</span></a><span>, which are devices that split the NOₓ compounds into nitrogen and oxygen before they are released into the atmosphere.</span></p><h2 id="black-carbon-the-soot-that-fills-our-skies-and-lungs"><span>Black carbon: the soot that fills our skies and lungs</span><a href="#black-carbon-the-soot-that-fills-our-skies-and-lungs"></a></h2><p><span>Black carbon (BC) are the small particles that many of us know as “soot”.</span></p><p><span>As most of us know from experience — such as lighting a bonfire — soot is formed when we burn materials such as wood and biomass or fossil fuels like coal. It’s the </span><em><span>incomplete</span></em><span> combustion of these materials that leads to the formation of these BC particles.</span></p><p><span>These particles are black because they absorb light, and this absorption of sunlight contributes to climate change. However, when it comes to health, it contributes through its direct toxicity and the formation of small particulates.</span></p><p><span>Black carbon can be a major issue for household and outdoor particulate matter and </span><a href="https://drawdown.org/publications/reducing-black-carbon" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>probably contributes to</span></a><span> </span><strong><span>several million deaths per year</span></strong><span>.</span></p><p><span>In the charts below, you can see the sources of black carbon globally.</span></p><p><span>Unsurprisingly, the biggest contributor to BC is energy production, mostly coal and biomass burning for electricity and heat. Black carbon is a big problem in industrialized countries with large-scale electricity production, but also in lower-income countries where people rely on burning biomass and charcoal for cooking and heating.</span></p><p><span>Road transport is another major contributor since black carbon is also formed from diesel engines and exhausts. The open burning of waste also plays a surprisingly large role, particularly in low-to-middle-income countries, where this is often used for waste disposal.</span></p><p><span>Some countries — particularly richer ones — have seen </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/air-pollution?time=1950..2022&amp;Pollutant=Black+carbon&amp;Sector=All+sectors+%28total%29&amp;Per+capita=false&amp;country=GBR~FRA~DEU~USA"><span>a huge drop</span></a><span> in black carbon emissions over the last 50 years due to moving away from biomass and coal burning and introducing cleaner cars.</span></p><h2 id="methane-burping-cows-rice-paddies-and-gas-leaks"><span>Methane: burping cows, rice paddies, and gas leaks</span><a href="#methane-burping-cows-rice-paddies-and-gas-leaks"></a></h2><p><span>Methane (CH</span><sub><span>4</span></sub><span>) is a greenhouse gas, so it’s </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/co2-and-greenhouse-gas-emissions" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>mostly discussed</span></a><span> regarding contributions to climate change. However, methane can also affect health when it breaks down to form ozone, a gas that’s hazardous to human health. In fact, methane is the biggest precursor to ozone in many places.</span></p><p><span>It’s </span><a href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/en/analysis/publications/methane-climate-change-and-air-quality-in-europe-exploring-the-connections" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>estimated that</span></a><span> methane can lead to up to </span><strong><span>half a million premature deaths</span></strong><span> a year.</span><a href="#note-9"><sup><span>9</span></sup></a></p><p><span>The charts below show where it comes from.</span></p><p><span>Agriculture, specifically livestock and rice production, is the biggest source of methane. Ruminant livestock — mostly cows — produce methane in their digestive systems and release it into the atmosphere by burping. That’s why beef and lamb </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/less-meat-or-sustainable-meat" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>tend to have</span></a><span> a high carbon footprint.</span><a href="#note-10"><sup><span>10</span></sup></a><span> Rice also produces methane because it’s often grown in flooded paddy fields with low oxygen levels. This means methane is produced rather than carbon dioxide. Eating less beef, lamb, and dairy could </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/food-choice-vs-eating-local" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>dramatically reduce</span></a><span> emissions from agriculture. Finding innovative ways to reduce the amount of methane produced per cow by changing their diets could also help.</span></p><p><span>Energy generation is another large source of methane. Most of it comes from leaks — which we call “fugitive emissions” — from oil and gas wells. If these are not properly managed, some methane escapes into the atmosphere. Another key source is coal mining. Monitoring oil and gas wells for methane leaks and enforcing regulations to ensure that limits are not breached can reduce these emissions. New drone and satellite technologies are </span><a href="https://www.catf.us/2023/02/guide-monitoring-quantifying-methane-emissions-oil-gas-sector/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>already being developed</span></a><span> to provide a global map of where these leaks are coming from.</span></p><p><span>The third sector that contributes a lot is waste. Methane is produced when organic material — like food waste or paper — rots in conditions without much oxygen (like in a landfill). Securely sealing landfills or capturing this methane for energy can effectively reduce these emissions. Methane from waste has been falling in many richer countries — like </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/air-pollution?time=1990..2022&amp;country=~GBR&amp;Pollutant=Methane&amp;Sector=Waste&amp;Per+capita=false"><span>the United Kingdom</span></a><span> — that have implemented these strategies.</span></p><h2 id="ammonia-nh3-it-s-all-about-farming"><span>Ammonia (NH</span><sub><span>3</span></sub><span>): it’s all about farming</span><a href="#ammonia-nh3-it-s-all-about-farming"></a></h2><p><span>As the chart below shows, nearly all human emissions of ammonia (NH</span><sub><span>3</span></sub><span>) come from agriculture. When we add nitrogen to crops as synthetic fertilizers or manure, some of this nitrogen is converted into NH</span><sub><span>3</span></sub><span> in the soil. Other smaller sources include decomposing organic waste in landfills and energy production.</span></p><p><span>Although NH</span><sub><span>3 </span></sub><span>doesn’t stay in the atmosphere for long — typically hours to days — it can react with other gases to form small particulates that harm human health.</span></p><p><span>Some studies suggest ammonia could drive </span><strong><span>several hundred thousand (up to 385,000) premature deaths</span></strong><span> from particulate matter.</span><a href="#note-11"><sup><span>11</span></sup></a></p><p><span>In the charts below, you can see that unlike most other air pollutants, where emissions have peaked globally, emissions of NH</span><sub><span>3 </span></sub><span>have continued to rise as </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/meat-production" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>livestock production</span></a><span> and the use of synthetic </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/fertilizers" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>fertilizers</span></a><span> have increased.</span></p><p><span>Some countries — particularly </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/air-pollution?time=1950..2022&amp;Pollutant=Ammonia&amp;Sector=All+sectors+%28total%29&amp;Per+capita=false&amp;country=GBR~FRA~DEU"><span>those in Europe</span></a><span> — have achieved small reductions in emissions because they </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/effective-policies-reducing-environmental-impacts-agriculture" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>use less fertilizers</span></a><span> than a few decades ago.</span></p><h2 id="non-methane-volatile-organic-compounds-nmvo-cs"><span>Non-methane volatile organic compounds (NMVOCs)</span><a href="#non-methane-volatile-organic-compounds-nmvo-cs"></a></h2><p><span>Non-methane volatile organic compounds (NMVOCs) can threaten human health through all three of the pathways we looked at earlier: they can be directly toxic in high concentrations and mix with other gases to form ozone and small particulates.</span></p><p><span>You can see the global sources of NMVOCs in the chart below.</span></p><p><span>NMVOCs are produced by traditional pollution sources like burning fossil fuels and car exhausts. However, unlike most other pollutants, solvents such as paints, cleaning products, and chemical plants are also major sources.</span></p><p><span>In addition to switching to low-carbon energy and phasing out gasoline cars, we also need to reduce the use of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in personal care products and solvents. Setting emission limits on the chemicals industry will also be key to lowering our exposure to non-methane VOCs (NMVOCs).</span></p><h2 id="while-pollution-sources-are-diverse-the-solutions-are-often-not"><span>While pollution sources are diverse, the solutions are often not</span><a href="#while-pollution-sources-are-diverse-the-solutions-are-often-not"></a></h2><p><span>Going through so many pollutants, one by one — as we just did — can seem overwhelming. We don’t need to just tackle one or two; we need to tackle more than six.</span><a href="#note-12"><sup><span>12</span></sup></a></p><p><span>The good news is that the solutions we need often cut across several gases at the same time.</span></p><p><span>Burning stuff for energy — whether that’s fossil fuels or biomass — is the root source for many of these gases. Moving to clean energy — deploying renewable or nuclear electricity, </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/electric-car-sales" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>electrifying our cars</span></a><span>, our industry, and home heating — and ensuring that people worldwide </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/worlds-energy-problem" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>have access</span></a><span> to </span><em><span>modern</span></em><span> energy sources would simultaneously cut many of these pollutants.</span></p><p><span>Reducing meat production and consumption </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/food-choice-vs-eating-local" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>by shifting to</span></a><span> more plant-based diets would reduce methane and ammonia emissions at the same time, too.</span></p><p><span>These transitions come with large health benefits, just from reducing air pollution alone.</span></p><p><span>And we know that it can be done. Many countries </span><em><span>have</span></em><span> dramatically reduced levels of air pollution, and as you can see in the chart below, they’ve prevented hundreds of thousands of early deaths as a result.</span></p><figure><figcaption><span>The total number of deaths has declined in these countries despite much larger older populations. The </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/death-rate-from-air-pollution-per-100000?tab=chart&amp;country=GBR~USA~NOR~DEU~SWE"><span>decline in</span></a><span> death </span><em><span>rates</span></em><span> has been even larger.</span></figcaption></figure><div><figure data-grapher-src="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution?country=GBR~USA~CAN~DEU~NOR~SWE"><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution?country=GBR~USA~CAN~DEU~NOR~SWE" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><picture><source id="grapher-preview-source" srcset="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution.png?country=GBR~USA~CAN~DEU~NOR~SWE&amp;imWidth=850 850w, https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution.png?country=GBR~USA~CAN~DEU~NOR~SWE&amp;imWidth=1700 1700w" sizes="(max-width: 850px) 100vw, 850px"><img src="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/deaths-from-household-and-outdoor-air-pollution.png?country=GBR~USA~CAN~DEU~NOR~SWE" width="850" height="600" loading="lazy" data-no-lightbox="true"></picture></a></figure></div><div><h4>Acknowledgments</h4><p><span>Many thanks to Max Roser and Edouard Mathieu for their feedback and comments on this article.</span></p></div><h2 id="continue-reading-on-our-world-in-data"><span>Continue reading on Our World in Data</span><a href="#continue-reading-on-our-world-in-data"></a></h2><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/cleanest-air-lessons"><div><picture><source srcset="https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/2634177d-6b60-4df5-3152-c38263399f00/w=48 48w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/2634177d-6b60-4df5-3152-c38263399f00/w=100 100w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/2634177d-6b60-4df5-3152-c38263399f00/w=350 350w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/2634177d-6b60-4df5-3152-c38263399f00/w=850 850w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/2634177d-6b60-4df5-3152-c38263399f00/w=1350 1350w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/2634177d-6b60-4df5-3152-c38263399f00/w=2400 2400w" type="image/png" sizes="350px"><img src="https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/2634177d-6b60-4df5-3152-c38263399f00/w=2400" alt="Featured image" loading="lazy" data-filename="reducing-air-pollution-featured.png" width="2400" height="1260"></picture></div><div><p><h3>In many countries, people breathe the cleanest air in centuries. What can the rest of the world learn from this?</h3></p><p>Air pollution tends to get worse before it gets better, but how can we accelerate this transition?</p></div></a><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/air-pollution"><div><p><h3> Data Explorer</h3></p></div></a><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/data-review-air-pollution-deaths"><div><picture><source srcset="https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/02062e42-9ceb-45b2-bad7-aed8d5169d00/w=48 48w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/02062e42-9ceb-45b2-bad7-aed8d5169d00/w=100 100w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/02062e42-9ceb-45b2-bad7-aed8d5169d00/w=350 350w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/02062e42-9ceb-45b2-bad7-aed8d5169d00/w=850 850w, https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/02062e42-9ceb-45b2-bad7-aed8d5169d00/w=1200 1200w" type="image/png" sizes="350px"><img src="https://ourworldindata.org/cdn-cgi/imagedelivery/qLq-8BTgXU8yG0N6HnOy8g/02062e42-9ceb-45b2-bad7-aed8d5169d00/w=1200" loading="lazy" data-filename="air-pollution-deaths-thumbnail.png" width="1200" height="630"></picture></div><div><p><h3>Data review: how many people die from air pollution?</h3></p><p>This data review presents published estimates of the global death toll from air pollution and provides the context that makes them understandable.</p></div></a><div><h3 id="article-endnotes">Endnotes</h3><ol><li id="note-1"><p><span>Here, we’re not talking about greenhouse gases that drive climate change — which we cover in great detail elsewhere — although we will include a few greenhouse gases, such as methane, which can also act as a precursor to local air pollutants.</span></p></li><li id="note-2"><p><span>Hoesly, R. M., Smith, S. J., Feng, L., Klimont, Z., Janssens-Maenhout, G., Pitkanen, T., ... &amp; Zhang, Q. (2018). </span><a href="https://gmd.copernicus.org/articles/11/369/2018/gmd-11-369-2018.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>Historical (1750–2014) anthropogenic emissions of reactive gases and aerosols from the Community Emissions Data System (CEDS)</span></a><span>. Geoscientific Model Development, 11(1), 369-408.</span></p></li><li id="note-3"><p><span>World Health Organization (2021). </span><a href="https://www.who.int/publications/i/item/9789240034228" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>WHO global air quality guidelines: particulate matter (‎PM2.5 and PM10)‎, ozone, nitrogen dioxide, sulfur dioxide and carbon monoxide</span></a><span>.</span></p></li><li id="note-4"><p><span>Note that we’re talking about ground-level, or tropospheric, ozone in the lower atmosphere. At this level, it’s considered a pollutant. This differs from </span><em><span>stratospheric</span></em><span> ozone, which is high in the atmosphere and crucial for protecting us from ultraviolet radiation. We cover this in our work on the </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/ozone-layer" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>Ozone Layer</span></a><span>.</span></p><p><span>* Mar, K. A., Unger, C., Walderdorff, L., &amp; Butler, T. (2022). Beyond CO2 equivalence: The impacts of methane on climate, ecosystems, and health. Environmental science &amp; policy.</span></p></li><li id="note-5"><p><span>The Global Burden of Disease is published by the Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation (IHME).</span></p></li><li id="note-6"><p><span>Note that when we add all of these </span><em><span>individual</span></em><span> risk factors — indoor particulates, outdoor particulates, and outdoor ozone — the total comes to 8.3 million, which is higher than the Global Burden of Disease reports on aggregate. This is because different risk factors can combine to increase health problems and the risk of premature death. In </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/how-do-researchers-estimate-the-death-toll-caused-by-each-risk-factor-whether-its-smoking-obesity-or-air-pollution" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>this article</span></a><span>, our colleague, Saloni Dattani, examines how risk factors are estimated and why they can’t be summed up to give the total number of premature deaths.</span></p></li><li id="note-7"><p><span>Fioletov, V. E., McLinden, C. A., Krotkov, N., Li, C., Joiner, J., Theys, N., ... &amp; Moran, M. D. (2016). </span><a href="https://acp.copernicus.org/articles/16/11497/2016/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>A global catalogue of large SO2 sources and emissions derived from the Ozone Monitoring Instrument</span></a><span>. Atmospheric Chemistry and Physics, 16(18), 11497-11519.</span></p></li><li id="note-8"><p><span>Pan, S. Y., He, K. H., Lin, K. T., Fan, C., &amp; Chang, C. T. (2022). </span><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41612-022-00265-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>Addressing nitrogenous gases from croplands toward low-emission agriculture</span></a><span>. Npj Climate and Atmospheric Science.</span></p></li><li id="note-9"><p><span>This estimate comes from the UN Environment Programme and Climate and Clean Air Coalition:UNEP and Climate and Clean Air Coalition (2021) </span><a href="https://www.unep.org/resources/report/global-methane-assessment-benefits-and-costs-mitigating-methane-emissions" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>Global Methane Assessment: Benefits and Costs of Mitigating Methane Emissions</span></a><span>.</span></p></li><li id="note-10"><p><span>Although this is not the only reason they have a high carbon footprint, even </span><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/carbon-footprint-food-methane" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span>when we ignore methane</span></a><span>, they still emit much carbon through land use and manure.</span></p></li><li id="note-11"><p><span>Wyer, K. E., Kelleghan, D. B., Blanes-Vidal, V., Schauberger, G., &amp; Curran, T. P. (2022). Ammonia emissions from agriculture and their contribution to fine particulate matter: A review of implications for human health. Journal of Environmental Management, 323, 116285.</span></p></li><li id="note-12"><p><span>We included six of the big ones in this article, but it’s not a complete list.</span></p></li></ol></div><div id="article-citation"><h3>Cite this work</h3><p>Our articles and data visualizations rely on work from many different people and organizations. When citing this article, please also cite the underlying data sources. This article can be cited as:</p><div><pre><code>Hannah Ritchie and Pablo Rosado (2025) - “Air pollution kills millions every year&nbsp;— where does it come from?” Published online at OurWorldinData.org. Retrieved from: 'https://ourworldindata.org/air-pollution-sources' [Online Resource]</code></pre></div><p>BibTeX citation</p><div><pre><code>@article{owid-air-pollution-sources,
    author = {Hannah Ritchie and Pablo Rosado},
    title = {Air pollution kills millions every year&nbsp;— where does it come from?},
    journal = {Our World in Data},
    year = {2025},
    note = {https://ourworldindata.org/air-pollution-sources}
}</code></pre></div></div><div id="article-licence"><p><img src="https://ourworldindata.org/owid-logo.svg" alt="Our World in Data logo" width="104" height="57"></p><h3>Reuse this work freely</h3><p>All visualizations, data, and code produced by Our World in Data are completely open access under the <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Creative Commons BY license</a>. You have the permission to use, distribute, and reproduce these in any medium, provided the source and authors are credited.</p><p>The data produced by third parties and made available by Our World in Data is subject to the license terms from the original third-party authors. We will always indicate the original source of the data in our documentation, so you should always check the license of any such third-party data before use and redistribution.</p><p>All of <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/faqs#how-can-i-embed-one-of-your-interactive-charts-in-my-website">our charts can be embedded</a> in any site.</p></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Val Kilmer has passed away (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/01/movies/val-kilmer-dead.html</link>
            <guid>43553573</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 04:04:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/01/movies/val-kilmer-dead.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/01/movies/val-kilmer-dead.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43553573">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/01/movies/val-kilmer-dead.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I vibecoded a 35k LoC recipe app (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.recipeninja.ai</link>
            <guid>43553031</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 01:57:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.recipeninja.ai">https://www.recipeninja.ai</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43553031">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Simulated Economy Tutorial (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jasonfantl.com/posts/Simulated-Economy-(1)/</link>
            <guid>43552530</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:05:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jasonfantl.com/posts/Simulated-Economy-(1)/">https://jasonfantl.com/posts/Simulated-Economy-(1)/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43552530">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://jasonfantl.com/posts/Simulated-Economy-(1)/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>