<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 09:30:21 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I want to wash my car. The car wash is 50 meters away. Should I walk or drive? (401 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mastodon.world/@knowmadd/116072773118828295</link>
            <guid>47031580</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 06:31:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mastodon.world/@knowmadd/116072773118828295">https://mastodon.world/@knowmadd/116072773118828295</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47031580">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Peter Thiel: 2,436 emails with Epstein from 2014 to 2019 (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jmail.world/wiki/peter-thiel</link>
            <guid>47028369</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 22:29:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jmail.world/wiki/peter-thiel">https://jmail.world/wiki/peter-thiel</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47028369">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><!--$?--><template id="B:1"></template><!--/$--><title>Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia</title><meta name="description" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia. Sourced from 2,429 emails across 1,345 threads in the Jmail archive."><meta name="author" content="Luke Igel"><meta name="author" content="Riley Walz"><meta name="creator" content="Luke Igel &amp; Riley Walz"><meta name="publisher" content="Kino AI"><meta name="robots" content="index, follow"><meta name="googlebot" content="index, follow"><meta property="og:title" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia"><meta property="og:description" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia. Sourced from 2,429 emails across 1,345 threads in the Jmail archive."><meta property="og:url" content="https://jmail.world/wiki/peter-thiel"><meta property="og:site_name" content="Jmail"><meta property="og:image" content="https://jmail.world/api/og/jwiki/peter-thiel"><meta property="og:image:width" content="1200"><meta property="og:image:height" content="630"><meta property="og:image:alt" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia"><meta property="og:type" content="article"><meta name="twitter:card" content="summary_large_image"><meta name="twitter:site" content="@jmailarchive"><meta name="twitter:title" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia"><meta name="twitter:description" content="Peter Thiel — The Jmail Encyclopedia. Sourced from 2,429 emails across 1,345 threads in the Jmail archive."><meta name="twitter:image" content="https://jmail.world/api/og/jwiki/peter-thiel"></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Magnus Carlsen Wins the Freestyle (Chess960) World Championship (271 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fide.com/magnus-carlsen-wins-2026-fide-freestyle-world-championship/</link>
            <guid>47028227</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 22:17:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.fide.com/magnus-carlsen-wins-2026-fide-freestyle-world-championship/">https://www.fide.com/magnus-carlsen-wins-2026-fide-freestyle-world-championship/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47028227">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-id="377e8e4" data-element_type="widget" data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="43662" data-elementor-post-type="post" data-widget_type="theme-post-content.default">
				<div data-id="815ffae" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1000" height="605" src="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03.jpg 1000w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-300x182.jpg 300w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-768x465.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">															</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="13c5e19" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
									<p><strong>Magnus Carlsen</strong> (Norway) is the 2026 FIDE Freestyle Chess World Champion. A draw in the fourth and final game against <strong>Fabiano Caruana</strong> (USA) was enough to seal a 2.5–1.5 match victory in Weissenhaus, Germany.</p><p><span>&nbsp;</span><span>The decisive moment came in game three. Carlsen won from a dead lost position, turning the match in his favor. Entering the final game, he needed only a draw and achieved it in an equal endgame after Caruana missed late chances to mount a comeback. Both finalists qualified for the 2027 FIDE Freestyle Chess World Championship.</span></p>								</div>
				<div data-id="3d4b435" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<p><img decoding="async" width="1000" height="661" src="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Carlsen-Caruana.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Carlsen-Caruana.jpg 1000w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Carlsen-Caruana-300x198.jpg 300w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Carlsen-Caruana-768x508.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">															</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="cb9359c" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
									<p>The 2026 tournament marks the first official FIDE-recognized Freestyle Chess World Championship. World number one Carlsen had previously attempted to win the FIDE Fischer Random World Championship without success. In Weissenhaus, he secured the official FIDE Freestyle Chess title – his 21st world title across formats.</p><p><span>&nbsp;</span><span>In the match for third place, <strong>Nodirbek Abdusattorov</strong> (Uzbekistan) defeated <strong>Vincent Keymer</strong> (Germany). Abdusattorov secured the match by drawing a winning position in the final game, also ensuring qualification for the 2027 championship.</span></p>								</div>
				<div data-id="27aa71b" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<p><img decoding="async" width="1000" height="670" src="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Abdusattorov-Keymer.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Abdusattorov-Keymer.jpg 1000w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Abdusattorov-Keymer-300x201.jpg 300w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Abdusattorov-Keymer-768x515.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">															</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="55d317e" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
									<p><span><strong>Hans Niemann</strong> (USA) took fifth place with a 2–0 victory over <strong>Arjun Erigaisi</strong> (India), while <strong>Levon Aronian</strong> (USA) won his Armageddon against <strong>Javokhir Sindarov</strong> (Uzbekistan) to take seventh place.</span></p><p>In the women’s exhibition match, <strong>Bibisara Assaubayeva</strong> (Kazakhstan) prevailed over <strong>Alexandra Kosteniuk</strong> (Switzerland) after winning the third game and drawing the fourth.</p>								</div>
				<div data-id="b1752d4" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="image.default">
				<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="670" src="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Kosteniuk-Assaubayeva.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Kosteniuk-Assaubayeva.jpg 1000w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Kosteniuk-Assaubayeva-300x201.jpg 300w, https://www.fide.com/wp-content/uploads/FS-D03-Kosteniuk-Assaubayeva-768x515.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px">															</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="20a76b5" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
									<p><strong>Key facts</strong>:</p><ul><li><span>⁠</span><span>⁠<span>Location: Weissenhaus, Germany</span></span></li><li><span><span>⁠</span><span>Dates: February 13–15, 2026</span></span></li><li><span><span>⁠</span><span>Prize fund: $300,000</span></span></li><li><span><span>⁠</span><span>Winner’s prize: $100,000</span></span></li><li><span><span>⁠</span><span>Top three qualify for 2027</span></span></li></ul><p><span>&nbsp;</span><span>A full report is available <a href="https://www.freestyle-chess.com/news/magnus-carlsen-wins-fide-freestyle-chess-world-championship/"><strong>[HERE]</strong></a>.</span></p><p><strong>Written by Till Behrend</strong></p><p><strong>Photos: Lennart Ootes and Steve Bonhage / Freestyle Chess</strong></p><p>Official website:&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.freestyle-chess.com/">https://www.freestyle-chess.com/</a></strong></p>								</div>
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I’m joining OpenAI (991 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://steipete.me/posts/2026/openclaw</link>
            <guid>47028013</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 21:54:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://steipete.me/posts/2026/openclaw">https://steipete.me/posts/2026/openclaw</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47028013">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="article" data-astro-cid-vj4tpspi="">  <p><strong>tl;dr: I’m joining OpenAI to work on bringing agents to everyone. <a href="https://openclaw.ai/">OpenClaw</a> will move to a foundation and stay open and independent.</strong></p>
<p>The last month was a whirlwind, never would I have expected that my playground project would create such waves. The internet got weird again, and it’s been incredibly fun to see how my work inspired so many people around the world.</p>
<p>There’s an endless array of possibilities that opened up for me, countless people trying to push me into various directions, giving me advice, asking how they can invest or what I will do. Saying it’s overwhelming is an understatement.</p>
<p>When I started exploring AI, my goal was to have fun and inspire people. And here we are, the lobster is taking over the world. My next mission is to build an agent that even my mum can use. That’ll need a much broader change, a lot more thought on how to do it safely, and access to the very latest models and research.</p>
<p>Yes, I could totally see how OpenClaw could become a huge company. And no, it’s not really exciting for me. I’m a builder at heart. I did the whole creating-a-company game already, poured 13 years of my life into it and learned a lot. What I want is to change the world, not build a large company and teaming up with OpenAI is the fastest way to bring this to everyone.</p>
<p>I spent last week in San Francisco talking with the major labs, getting access to people and unreleased research, and it’s been inspiring on all fronts. I want to thank all the folks I talked to this week and am thankful for the opportunities.</p>
<p>It’s always been important to me that OpenClaw stays open source and given the freedom to flourish. Ultimately, I felt OpenAI was the best place to continue pushing on my vision and expand its reach. The more I talked with the people there, the clearer it became that we both share the same vision.</p>
<p>The community around OpenClaw is something magical and OpenAI has made strong commitments to enable me to dedicate my time to it and already sponsors the project. To get this into a proper structure I’m working on making it a foundation. It will stay a place for thinkers, hackers and people that want a way to own their data, with the goal of supporting even more models and companies.</p>
<p>Personally I’m super excited to join OpenAI, be part of the frontier of AI research and development, and continue building with all of you.</p>
<p>The claw is the law.</p>
<p><img src="https://steipete.me/assets/img/2026/openclaw/clawcon.jpg" alt="ClawCon" loading="lazy"></p> </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[State Attorneys General Want to Tie Online Access to ID (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://reclaimthenet.org/40-attorneys-general-back-ids-online-safety-act</link>
            <guid>47026848</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 19:49:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://reclaimthenet.org/40-attorneys-general-back-ids-online-safety-act">https://reclaimthenet.org/40-attorneys-general-back-ids-online-safety-act</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47026848">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-id="7eda0c13" data-element_type="widget" data-e-type="widget" data-widget_type="theme-post-content.default">
					<p>A bloc of 40 state and territorial attorneys general is urging Congress to adopt the Senate’s version of the controversial <a href="https://reclaimthenet.org/kids-online-safety-act-kosa-privacy-surveillance-concerns-2025">Kids Online Safety Act</a>, positioning it as the stronger regulatory instrument and rejecting the House companion as insufficient.</p>
<p>The Act would kill online anonymity and tie online activity and speech to a real-world identity.</p>
<p>Acting through the National Association of Attorneys General, the coalition sent a letter to congressional leadership endorsing S. 1748 and opposing H.R. 6484.</p>
<p><strong>We obtained a copy of the letter for you <a href="https://docs.reclaimthenet.org/ag-letter-supporting-senate-kosa-february-10-2026.pdf">here</a>.</strong></p><div data-id="eb333a5" data-element_type="container" data-e-type="container" data-settings="{&quot;background_background&quot;:&quot;classic&quot;}" data-elementor-type="section" data-elementor-id="235992" data-elementor-post-type="elementor_library">
				<div data-id="4678215" data-element_type="widget" data-e-type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<p>Reclaim Your Digital Freedom.</p>
				</div>
				<div data-id="fe169cc" data-element_type="widget" data-e-type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<p>Get unfiltered coverage of surveillance, censorship, and the technology threatening your civil liberties.</p>
				</div>
				
					</div>

<p>Their request centers on structural differences between the bills. The Senate proposal would create a federally enforceable “Duty of Care” requiring covered platforms to mitigate defined harms to minors.</p>
<p>Enforcement authority would rest with the Federal Trade Commission, which could investigate and sue companies that fail to prevent minors from encountering content deemed to cause “harm to minors.”</p>
<p>That framework would require regulators to evaluate internal content moderation systems, recommendation algorithms, and safety controls.</p>
<p>S. 1748 also directs the Secretary of Commerce, the FTC, and the Federal Communications Commission to study “the most technologically feasible methods and options for developing systems to verify age at the device or operating system level.”</p>
<p>This language moves beyond platform-level age gates and toward infrastructure embedded directly into hardware or operating systems.</p>
<p>Age verification at that layer would not function without some form of credentialing. Device-level verification would likely depend on digital identity checks tied to government-issued identification, third-party age verification vendors, or persistent account authentication systems.</p>
<p>That means users could be required to submit identifying information before accessing broad categories of lawful online speech.&nbsp;Anonymous browsing depends on the ability to access content without linking identity credentials to activity.</p>
<p>A device-level age verification architecture would establish identity checkpoints upstream of content access, creating records that age was verified and potentially associating that verification with a persistent device or account.</p>
<p>Even if content is not stored, the existence of a verified identity token tied to access creates a paper trail.</p>
<p>Constitutional questions follow. The Supreme Court has repeatedly recognized anonymous speech as protected under the First Amendment. Mandating identity verification before accessing lawful speech raises prior restraint and overbreadth concerns, particularly where the definition of “harm to minors” extends into categories that are legal for adults.</p>
<p>Courts have struck down earlier <a href="https://reclaimthenet.org/texas-app-store-accountability-act-blocked-federal-judge-first-amendment">efforts to impose age verification requirements</a> for online content on First Amendment grounds, citing the chilling effect on lawful expression and adult access.</p>
<p>Despite this history, state officials continue to advocate for broader age verification regimes. Several states have enacted or proposed laws requiring age checks for social media or adult content sites, often triggering litigation over compelled identification and privacy burdens.</p>
<p>The coalition’s letter suggests that state attorneys general are not retreating from that position and are instead seeking federal backing.</p>
<p>The attorneys general argue that social media companies deliberately design products that draw in underage users and monetize their personal data through targeted advertising. They contend that companies have not adequately disclosed addictive features or mental health risks and point to evidence suggesting firms are aware of adverse consequences for minors.</p>
<p>Multiple state offices have already filed lawsuits or opened investigations against Meta and TikTok, alleging “harm” to young users.</p>
<p>At the same time, the coalition objects to provisions in H.R. 6484 that would limit state authority. The House bill contains broader federal preemption language, which could restrict states from enforcing parallel or more stringent requirements. The attorneys general warn that this would curb their ability to pursue emerging online harms under state law. They also fault the House proposal for relying on company-maintained “reasonable policies, practices, and procedures” rather than imposing a statutory Duty of Care.</p>
<p>The Senate approach couples enforceable federal standards with preserved state enforcement power.</p>
<p>The coalition calls on the United States House of Representatives to align with the Senate framework, expand the list of enumerated harms to include even suicide, eating disorders, compulsive use, mental health harms, and financial harms, and ensure that states retain authority to act alongside federal regulators. The measure has bipartisan sponsorship in the United States Senate.</p>
<p>The policy direction is clear. Federal agencies would study device-level age verification systems, the FTC would police compliance with harm mitigation duties, and states would continue to pursue parallel litigation. Those mechanisms would reshape how platforms design their systems and how users access speech.</p>
<p>Whether framed as child protection or platform accountability, the architecture contemplated by S. 1748 would move identity verification closer to the heart of internet access.</p>
<p>Once age checks are embedded at the operating system level, the boundary between verifying age and verifying identity becomes difficult to maintain.</p>
<p>The internet would be changed forever.</p>
<!-- CONTENT END 1 -->
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Microgpt is a GPT you can visualize in the browser (177 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://microgpt.boratto.ca</link>
            <guid>47026186</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:40:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://microgpt.boratto.ca">https://microgpt.boratto.ca</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47026186">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Editor's Note: Retraction of article containing fabricated quotations (236 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/staff/2026/02/editors-note-retraction-of-article-containing-fabricated-quotations/</link>
            <guid>47026071</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:29:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/staff/2026/02/editors-note-retraction-of-article-containing-fabricated-quotations/">https://arstechnica.com/staff/2026/02/editors-note-retraction-of-article-containing-fabricated-quotations/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47026071">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                      
                      
          <p>On Friday afternoon, Ars Technica published <a href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/02/after-a-routine-code-rejection-an-ai-agent-published-a-hit-piece-on-someone-by-name/">an article</a> containing fabricated quotations generated by an AI tool and attributed to a source who did not say them. That is a serious failure of our standards. Direct quotations must always reflect what a source actually said.</p>
<p>That this happened at Ars is especially distressing. We have covered the risks of overreliance on AI tools for years, and our written policy reflects those concerns. In this case, fabricated quotations were published in a manner inconsistent with that policy. We have reviewed recent work and have not identified additional issues. At this time, this appears to be an isolated incident.</p>
<p>Ars Technica does not permit the publication of AI-generated material unless it is clearly labeled and presented for demonstration purposes. That rule is not optional, and it was not followed here.</p>
<p>We regret this failure and apologize to our readers. We have also apologized to Mr. Scott Shambaugh, who was falsely quoted.</p>


          
                      
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Radio host David Greene says Google's NotebookLM tool stole his voice (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2026/02/15/david-greene-google-ai-podcast/</link>
            <guid>47025864</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:05:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2026/02/15/david-greene-google-ai-podcast/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2026/02/15/david-greene-google-ai-podcast/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025864">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2026/02/15/david-greene-google-ai-podcast/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Modern CSS Code Snippets: Stop writing CSS like it's 2015 (450 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://modern-css.com</link>
            <guid>47025851</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:04:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://modern-css.com">https://modern-css.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025851">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="all-comparisons">
    
    <p><span>Browser compatibility:</span>
      
      
      
      
    </p>
    <div id="tipsGrid">
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/range-style-queries-without-multiple-blocks/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Range style queries without multiple blocks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>/* Multiple style() blocks */</span><br><span>@container</span> <span>style</span>(<span>--p: 51%</span>) {}<br><span>@container</span> <span>style</span>(<span>--p: 52%</span>) {}<br><span>/* ...for each value */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@container</span> <span>style</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>--progress &gt; 50%</span><br>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.bar</span> { ... }<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/sticky-snapped-styling-without-javascript/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Sticky &amp; snapped element styling without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>window</span>.<span>addEventListener</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>'scroll'</span>, () =&gt; {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>/* check position */</span><br>});</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@container</span> <span>scroll-state</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>stuck: top</span><br>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.header</span> { ... }<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/typed-attribute-values-without-javascript/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Typed attribute values without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS reading dataset</span><br><span>el</span>.<span>style</span>.<span>width</span> =<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>el</span>.<span>dataset</span>.<span>pct</span> + <span>'%'</span>;</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.bar</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>width</span>: <span>attr</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>data-pct</span> <span>type</span>(<span>&lt;percentage&gt;</span>)<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/inline-conditional-styles-without-javascript/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Inline conditional styles without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JavaScript toggling</span><br><span>el</span>.<span>classList</span>.<span>toggle</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>'primary'</span>, <span>isPrimary</span><br>);</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.btn</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>background</span>: <span>if</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>style(--variant: primary)</span>:<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>blue</span>; <span>else</span>: <span>gray</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/reusable-css-logic-without-sass-mixins/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Reusable CSS logic without Sass mixins</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Sass function</span><br><span>@function</span> <span>fluid</span>(<span>$min</span>, <span>$max</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>@return</span> <span>clamp</span>(...);<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@function</span> <span>--fluid</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>--min</span>, <span>--max</span><br>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>@return</span> <span>clamp</span>(...);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/corner-shapes-beyond-rounded-borders/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Corner shapes beyond rounded borders</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.card</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>clip-path</span>: <span>polygon</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>...</span> <span>/* 20+ points */</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>border-radius</span>: <span>2em</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>corner-shape</span>: <span>squircle</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/responsive-clip-paths-without-svg/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Responsive clip paths without SVG</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.shape</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>clip-path</span>: <span>path</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>'M0 200 L100 0...'</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.shape</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>clip-path</span>: <span>shape</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>from 0% 100%</span>, ...<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/scroll-spy-without-intersection-observer/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Scroll spy without IntersectionObserver</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>const</span> <span>observer</span> = <span>new</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>IntersectionObserver</span>(cb);<br><span>/* 15+ lines of JS */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>nav a</span>:<span>target-current</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color</span>: <span>var(--accent)</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/filling-available-space-without-calc-workarounds/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Filling available space without calc workarounds</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.full</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>width</span>: <span>calc</span>(<span>100%</span> - <span>40px</span>);<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>/* or width: 100% and overflow */</span><br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.full</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>width</span>: <span>stretch</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* fills container, keeps margins */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/staggered-animations-without-nth-child-hacks/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Staggered animations without nth-child hacks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>li:nth-child(1)</span> { <span>--i</span>: <span>0</span>; }<br><span>li:nth-child(2)</span> { <span>--i</span>: <span>1</span>; }<br><span>li:nth-child(3)</span> { <span>--i</span>: <span>2</span>; }<br><span>/* repeat for every item… */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>li</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>transition-delay</span>:<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>calc</span>(<span>0.1s</span> * (<span>sibling-index()</span> - <span>1</span>));<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/carousel-navigation-without-a-javascript-library/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Carousel navigation without a JavaScript library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Swiper.js or Slick carousel</span><br><span>new</span> <span>Swiper</span>(<span>'.carousel'</span>, {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>navigation</span>: { <span>/* … */</span> },<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>pagination</span>: { <span>/* … */</span> },<br>});</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.carousel</span><span>::scroll-button(right)</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>content</span>: <span>"➡"</span>;<br>}<br><span>.carousel li</span><span>::scroll-marker</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>content</span>: <span>''</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/vertical-text-centering-without-padding-hacks/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Vertical text centering without padding hacks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.btn</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>padding</span>: <span>10px 20px</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>/* looks off-center, tweak top/bottom */</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>padding-top</span>: <span>8px</span>; <span>/* hack */</span><br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>h1</span>, <span>button</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>text-box</span>: <span>trim-both cap alphabetic</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* true optical centering */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/hover-tooltips-without-javascript-events/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Hover tooltips without JavaScript events</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS: mouseenter + mouseleave</span><br><span>btn</span>.<span>addEventListener</span>(<span>'mouseenter'</span>,<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;() =&gt; <span>showTooltip</span>())<br><span>/* + focus, blur, positioning */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>&lt;button</span> <span>interestfor</span>=<span>"tip"</span><span>&gt;</span>Hover me<span>&lt;/button&gt;</span><br><span>&lt;div</span> <span>id</span>=<span>"tip"</span> <span>popover</span>=<span>hint</span><span>&gt;</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;Tooltip content<br><span>&lt;/div&gt;</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/modal-controls-without-onclick-handlers/" data-baseline="">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Modal controls without onclick handlers</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>&lt;button</span> <span>onclick</span>=<span>"</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>document</span>.<span>querySelector</span>(<span>'#dlg'</span>)<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;.<span>showModal</span>()<span>"</span><span>&gt;</span>Open<span>&lt;/button&gt;</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>&lt;button</span> <span>commandfor</span>=<span>"dlg"</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>command</span>=<span>"show-modal"</span><span>&gt;</span>Open<span>&lt;/button&gt;</span><br><span>&lt;dialog</span> <span>id</span>=<span>"dlg"</span><span>&gt;</span>...<span>&lt;/dialog&gt;</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/dialog-light-dismiss-without-click-outside-listeners/" data-baseline="">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Dialog light dismiss without click-outside listeners</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS: listen for click on ::backdrop</span><br><span>dialog</span>.<span>addEventListener</span>(<span>'click'</span>,<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;(e) =&gt; { <span>/* check bounds */</span> })</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>&lt;dialog</span> <span>closedby</span>=<span>"any"</span><span>&gt;</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;Click outside to close<br><span>&lt;/dialog&gt;</span><br><span>/* no JS listeners */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/customizable-selects-without-a-javascript-library/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Customizable selects without a JavaScript library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Select2 or Choices.js</span><br><span>new</span> <span>Choices</span>(<span>'#my-select'</span>);<br><span>/* rebuilds entire DOM */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>select</span>,<br><span>select</span> <span>::picker(select)</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>appearance</span>: <span>base-select</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/vivid-colors-beyond-srgb/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Vivid colors beyond sRGB</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.hero</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color</span>: <span>rgb</span>(200, 80, 50);<br>}<br><span>/* sRGB only, washed on P3 */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.hero</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color</span>: <span>oklch</span>(0.7 0.25 29);<br>}<br><span>/* or color(display-p3 1 0.2 0.1) */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/color-variants-without-sass-functions/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Color variants without Sass functions</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>/* Sass: lighten($brand, 20%), darken($brand, 10%) */</span><br><span>.btn</span> { <span>background</span>: <span>#e0e0e0</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.btn</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>background</span>: <span>oklch</span>(<span>from</span> <span>var</span>(--brand) <span>calc</span>(l + 0.2) c h);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/multiline-text-truncation-without-javascript/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Multiline text truncation without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>/* JS: slice text by chars/words, add "..." */</span><br><span>.card-title</span> { <span>overflow</span>: <span>hidden</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card-title</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>-webkit-box</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>-webkit-line-clamp</span>: <span>3</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>line-clamp</span>: <span>3</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/drop-caps-without-float-hacks/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Drop caps without float hacks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.drop-cap::first-letter</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>float</span>: <span>left</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-size</span>: <span>3em</span>; <span>line-height</span>: <span>1</span>;<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.drop-cap::first-letter</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>initial-letter</span>: <span>3</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/positioning-shorthand-without-four-properties/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Positioning shorthand without four properties</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.overlay</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>top</span>: <span>0</span>; <span>right</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>bottom</span>: <span>0</span>; <span>left</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.overlay</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>position</span>: <span>absolute</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>inset</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/lazy-rendering-without-intersection-observer/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Lazy rendering without IntersectionObserver</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS IntersectionObserver</span><br><span>new</span> <span>IntersectionObserver</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;(entries) =&gt; { <span>/* render */</span> }<br>).<span>observe</span>(el);</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.section</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>content-visibility</span>: <span>auto</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>contain-intrinsic-size</span>: <span>auto 500px</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/dropdown-menus-without-javascript-toggles/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Dropdown menus without JavaScript toggles</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.menu</span> { <span>display</span>: <span>none</span>; }<br><span>.menu.open</span> { <span>display</span>: <span>block</span>; }<br><span>/* + JS: click, clickOutside, ESC, aria */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>button</span>[<span>popovertarget</span>=<span>menu</span>] { }<br><span>#menu</span>[<span>popover</span>] {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>position</span>: <span>absolute</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/tooltip-positioning-without-javascript/" data-baseline="limited">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Tooltip positioning without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>/* Popper.js / Floating UI: compute rect,</span><br><span>   position: fixed, update on scroll */</span><br><span>.tooltip</span> { <span>position</span>: <span>fixed</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.trigger</span> { <span>anchor-name</span>: <span>--tip</span>; }<br><span>.tooltip</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>position-anchor</span>: <span>--tip</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>top</span>: <span>anchor(bottom)</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/scoped-styles-without-bem-naming/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Scoped styles without BEM naming</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// BEM: .card__title, .card__body</span><br><span>.card__title</span> { â€¦ }<br><span>.card__body</span> { â€¦ }<br><span>// or CSS Modules / styled-components */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@scope</span> (<span>.card</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.title</span> { <span>font-size</span>: <span>1.25rem</span>; }<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.body</span> { <span>color</span>: <span>#444</span>; }<br>}<br><span>/* .title only inside .card */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/typed-custom-properties-without-javascript/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Typed custom properties without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// --hue was a string, no animation</span><br><span>:root</span> { <span>--hue</span>: <span>0</span>; }<br><span>hsl</span>(<span>var</span>(<span>--hue</span>), â€¦) <span>/* no interpolation */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@property</span> <span>--hue</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>syntax</span>: <span>"&lt;angle&gt;"</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>inherits</span>: <span>false</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>initial-value</span>: <span>0deg</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* animatable, validated */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/independent-transforms-without-the-shorthand/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Independent transforms without the shorthand</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.icon</span> { <span>transform</span>: <span>translateX</span>(<span>10px</span>) <span>rotate</span>(<span>45deg</span>) <span>scale</span>(<span>1.2</span>); }<br><span>/* change one = rewrite all */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.icon</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>translate</span>: <span>10px 0</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>rotate</span>: <span>45deg</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>scale</span>: <span>1.2</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* animate any one without touching the rest */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/animating-display-none-without-workarounds/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Animating display none without workarounds</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// wait for transitionend then display:none</span><br><span>el</span>.<span>addEventListener</span>(<span>'transitionend'</span>, â€¦)<br><span>visibility</span> + <span>opacity</span> + <span>pointer-events</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.panel</span> { <span>transition</span>: <span>opacity .2s, overlay .2s</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>transition-behavior</span>: <span>allow-discrete</span>; }<br><span>.panel.hidden</span> { <span>opacity</span>: <span>0</span>; <span>display</span>: <span>none</span>; }<br><span>/* no JS wait or visibility hack */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/entry-animations-without-javascript-timing/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Entry animations without JavaScript timing</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// add class after paint</span><br><span>requestAnimationFrame</span>(() =&gt; {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>el</span>.<span>classList</span>.<span>add</span>(<span>'visible'</span>);<br>});</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card</span> { <span>transition</span>: <span>opacity .3s, transform .3s</span>; }<br><span>.card</span> { <span>@starting-style</span> { <span>opacity</span>: <span>0</span>; <span>transform</span>: <span>translateY</span>(<span>10px</span>); } }<br><span>/* no rAF/setTimeout */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/page-transitions-without-a-framework/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Page transitions without a framework</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Barba.js or React Transition Group</span><br><span>Barba</span>.<span>init</span>({ â€¦ })<br><span>transition</span> hooks + <span>duration</span> state</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>document</span>.<span>startViewTransition</span>(() =&gt; <span>updateDOM</span>());<br><span>.hero</span> { <span>view-transition-name</span>: <span>hero</span>; }<br><span>/* no Barba, no React TG */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/scroll-snapping-without-a-carousel-library/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Scroll snapping without a carousel library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Slick, Swiper, or scroll/touch JS</span><br><span>$</span>(<span>'.carousel'</span>).<span>slick</span>({ â€¦ })<br><span>touchstart</span> / <span>scroll</span> handlers</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.carousel</span> { <span>scroll-snap-type</span>: <span>x mandatory</span>; }<br><span>.carousel &gt; *</span> { <span>scroll-snap-align</span>: <span>start</span>; }<br><span>/* no lib, no touch handlers */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/balanced-headlines-without-manual-line-breaks/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Balanced headlines without manual line breaks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// manual &lt;br&gt; or Balance-Text.js</span><br><span>h1</span> { <span>text-align</span>: <span>center</span>; }<br><span>.balance-text</span> <span>/* JS lib */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>h1</span>, <span>h2</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>text-wrap</span>: <span>balance</span>;<br>}<br><span>/* no br or JS */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/font-loading-without-invisible-text/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Font loading without invisible text</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@font-face</span> { ... }<br><span>/* Default: invisible text until load */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@font-face</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-family</span>: <span>"MyFont"</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-display</span>: <span>swap</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/multiple-font-weights-without-multiple-files/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Multiple font weights without multiple files</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@font-face</span> { <span>font-weight</span>: <span>400</span>; }<br><span>@font-face</span> { <span>font-weight</span>: <span>700</span>; }<br><span>/* 4+ files */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@font-face</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-family</span>: <span>"MyVar"</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>src</span>: <span>url("MyVar.woff2")</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-weight</span>: <span>100 900</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/dark-mode-defaults-without-extra-css/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Dark mode defaults without extra CSS</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@media</span> (<span>prefers-color-scheme</span>: <span>dark</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>input, select, textarea</span> { ... }<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>:root</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color-scheme</span>: <span>light dark</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/dark-mode-colors-without-duplicating-values/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Dark mode colors without duplicating values</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@media</span> (<span>prefers-color-scheme</span>: <span>dark</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>color</span>: <span>#eee</span>;<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>color</span>: <span>light-dark</span>(<span>#111</span>, <span>#eee</span>);<br><span>color-scheme</span>: <span>light dark</span>;          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/low-specificity-resets-without-complicated-selectors/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Low-specificity resets without complicated selectors</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.reset ul, .reset ol</span> { ... }<br><span>/* or (0,0,1) specificity, still wins */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>:where</span>(<span>ul, ol</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>margin</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>padding-inline-start</span>: <span>1.5rem</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/direction-aware-layouts-without-left-and-right/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Direction-aware layouts without left and right</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>margin-left</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br><span>padding-right</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br><span>[dir="rtl"</span>] <span>.box</span> { <span>margin-right</span>: ... }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>margin-inline-start</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br><span>padding-inline-end</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br><span>border-block-start</span>: <span>1px solid</span>;          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/naming-grid-areas-without-line-numbers/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Naming grid areas without line numbers</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>float</span>: <span>left</span>; <span>/* clearfix, margins */</span><br><span>grid-column</span>: <span>1 / 3</span>;<br><span>grid-row</span>: <span>2</span>;</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.layout</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>grid</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>grid-template-areas</span>: <span>"header header" "sidebar main" "footer footer"</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/aligning-nested-grids-without-duplicating-tracks/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Aligning nested grids without duplicating tracks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.child-grid</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>grid-template-columns</span>: <span>1fr 1fr 1fr</span>;<br><span>/* duplicate parent tracks */</span><br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.child-grid</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>grid</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>grid-template-columns</span>: <span>subgrid</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/modal-dialogs-without-a-javascript-library/" data-baseline="">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Modal dialogs without a JavaScript library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.overlay</span> { <span>position</span>: <span>fixed</span>; <span>z-index</span>: <span>999</span>; }<br><span>/* + JS: open/close, ESC, focus trap */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>dialog</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>padding</span>: <span>1rem</span>;<br>}<br><span>dialog::backdrop</span> { <span>background</span>: <span>rgb</span>(0 0 0 / .5); }          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/styling-form-controls-without-rebuilding-them/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Styling form controls without rebuilding them</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>appearance</span>: <span>none</span>;<br><span>// + 20+ lines of custom box/border/background</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>input</span>[<span>type</span>=<span>"checkbox"</span>],<br><span>input</span>[<span>type</span>=<span>"radio"</span>] {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>accent-color</span>: <span>#7c3aed</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/grouping-selectors-without-repetition/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Grouping selectors without repetition</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.card h1</span>, <span>.card h2</span>, <span>.card h3</span>, <span>.card h4</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>margin-bottom</span>: <span>0.5em</span>;<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card</span> <span>:is</span>(<span>h1</span>, <span>h2</span>, <span>h3</span>, <span>h4</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>margin-bottom</span>: <span>0.5em</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/focus-styles-without-annoying-mouse-users/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Focus styles without annoying mouse users</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>:focus</span> { <span>outline</span>: <span>2px solid blue</span>; }<br><span>// Shows on mouse click too, or people remove it (a11y fail)</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>:focus-visible</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>outline</span>: <span>2px solid</span> <span>var</span>(<span>--focus-color</span>);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/controlling-specificity-without-important/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Controlling specificity without !important</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.card .title</span> { ... }<br><span>.page .card .title</span> { ... }<br><span>.page .card .title.special</span> { <span>color</span>: <span>red</span> <span>!important</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@layer</span> <span>base</span>, <span>components</span>, <span>utilities</span>;<br><span>@layer</span> <span>utilities</span> { <span>.mt-4</span> { <span>margin-top</span>: <span>1rem</span>; } }          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/theme-variables-without-a-preprocessor/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Theme variables without a preprocessor</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Sass: $primary: #7c3aed;</span><br><span>// Compiles to static #7c3aed</span><br><span>.btn</span> { <span>background</span>: <span>$primary</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>:root</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>--primary</span>: <span>#7c3aed</span>;<br>}<br><span>.btn</span> { <span>background</span>: <span>var</span>(<span>--primary</span>); }          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/fluid-typography-without-media-queries/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Fluid typography without media queries</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>h1</span> { <span>font-size</span>: <span>1rem</span>; }<br><span>@media</span> (<span>min-width</span>: <span>600px</span>) { <span>h1</span> { <span>font-size</span>: <span>1.5rem</span>; } }<br><span>@media</span> (<span>min-width</span>: <span>900px</span>) { <span>h1</span> { <span>font-size</span>: <span>2rem</span>; } }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>h1</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>font-size</span>: <span>clamp</span>(<span>1rem</span>, <span>2.5vw</span>, <span>2rem</span>);<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/spacing-elements-without-margin-hacks/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Spacing elements without margin hacks</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.grid</span> <span>&gt; *</span> { <span>margin-right</span>: <span>16px</span>; }<br><span>.grid</span> <span>&gt; *:last-child</span> { <span>margin-right</span>: <span>0</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.grid</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>flex</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>gap</span>: <span>16px</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/aspect-ratios-without-the-padding-hack/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Aspect ratios without the padding hack</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>.wrapper</span> { <span>padding-top</span>: <span>56.25%</span>; <span>position</span>: <span>relative</span>; }<br><span>.inner</span> { <span>position</span>: <span>absolute</span>; <span>inset</span>: <span>0</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.video-wrapper</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>aspect-ratio</span>: <span>16 / 9</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/sticky-headers-without-javascript-scroll-listeners/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Sticky headers without JavaScript scroll listeners</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS: scroll listener + getBoundingClientRect</span><br><span>// then add/remove .fixed class</span><br><span>.header.fixed</span> { <span>position</span>: <span>fixed</span>; }</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.header</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>position</span>: <span>sticky</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>top</span>: <span>0</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/scroll-linked-animations-without-a-library/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Scroll-linked animations without a library</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JS + IntersectionObserver</span><br><span>observer</span>.<span>observe</span>(el)<br><span>el</span>.<span>style</span>.<span>opacity</span> = …</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>animation-timeline</span>: <span>view()</span>;<br><span>animation-range</span>: <span>entry</span>;<br><span>/* pure CSS, GPU-accelerated */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/nesting-selectors-without-sass-or-less/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Nesting selectors without Sass or Less</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// requires Sass compiler</span><br><span>.nav</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>&amp; a</span> { <span>color</span>: <span>#888</span>; }<br>}</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.nav</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>&amp; a</span> { <span>color</span>: <span>#888</span>; }<br>}<br><span>/* plain .css, no build */</span>          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/responsive-components-without-media-queries/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Responsive components without media queries</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>@media</span> (<span>max-width</span>: <span>768px</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.card</span> { … }<br>}<br><span>/* viewport, not container */</span></span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>@container</span> (<span>width</span> &lt; <span>400px</span>) {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>.card</span> { <span>flex-direction</span>: <span>column</span>; }<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/mixing-colors-without-a-preprocessor/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Mixing colors without a preprocessor</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// Sass required</span><br><span>$blend</span>: <span>mix</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>$blue</span>, <span>$pink</span>, <span>60%</span>);</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>background</span>: <span>color-mix</span>(<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>in oklch</span>, <span>#3b82f6</span>,<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>#ec4899</span>);          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/selecting-parent-elements-without-javascript/" data-baseline="newly">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Selecting parent elements without JavaScript</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>// JavaScript required</span><br><span>el</span>.<span>closest</span>(<span>'.parent'</span>)<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;.<span>classList</span>.<span>add</span>(…)</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.card:has(img)</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>grid-template</span>: <span>auto 1fr</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
            <a href="https://modern-css.com/centering-elements-without-the-transform-hack/" data-baseline="widely">
        <div>
          
          <h3>Centering elements without the transform hack</h3>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p><span>Old</span>
            <span><span>position</span>: <span>absolute</span>;<br><span>top</span>: <span>50%</span>; <span>left</span>: <span>50%</span>;<br><span>transform</span>: <span>translate(-50%,-50%)</span>;</span>
          </p>
          <p><span>Modern</span>
            <span>.parent</span> {<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>display</span>: <span>grid</span>;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>place-items</span>: <span>center</span>;<br>}          </p>
          <p><span>see modern →</span>
        </p></div>
        
      </a>
          </div>
  </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Palantir Gets Millions of Dollars from New York City's Public Hospitals (281 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theintercept.com/2026/02/15/palantir-contract-new-york-city-health-hospitals/</link>
            <guid>47025624</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:37:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theintercept.com/2026/02/15/palantir-contract-new-york-city-health-hospitals/">https://theintercept.com/2026/02/15/palantir-contract-new-york-city-health-hospitals/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025624">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    
    <p><span>New York City’s</span> public hospital system is paying millions to Palantir, the controversial ICE and military contractor, according to documents obtained by The Intercept.</p>
<p>Since 2023, the New York City Health and Hospitals Corporation has paid Palantir nearly $4 million to improve its ability to track down payment for the services provided at its hospitals and medical clinics. Palantir, a data analysis firm that’s now a Wall Street giant thanks to its lucrative work with the Pentagon and U.S. intelligence community, deploys its software to make more efficient the billing of Medicaid and other public benefits. That includes automated scanning of patient health notes to “Increase charges captured from missed opportunities,” contract materials reviewed by The Intercept show.</p>
<p>Palantir’s administrative involvement in the business of healing people stands in contrast to its longtime role helping facilitate warfare, <a href="https://theintercept.com/2017/03/02/palantir-provides-the-engine-for-donald-trumps-deportation-machine/">mass deportations</a>, and dragnet surveillance.</p>
<p>In 2016, <a href="https://theintercept.com/2017/02/22/how-peter-thiels-palantir-helped-the-nsa-spy-on-the-whole-world/">The Intercept revealed</a> Palantir’s role behind XKEYSCORE, a secret NSA bulk surveillance program revealed by the whistleblower Edward Snowden that allowed the U.S. and its allies to search the unfathomably large volumes of data they collect. The company has also attracted global scrutiny and criticism for its “<a href="https://www.palantir.com/assets/xrfr7uokpv1b/3MuEeA8MLbLDAyxixTsiIe/9e4a11a7fb058554a8a1e3cd83e31c09/C134184_finaleprint.pdf">strategic partnership</a>” with the Israeli military while it was leveling Gaza.</p>

<p>But it’s Palantir’s work with U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement that is drawing the most protest today. The company provides a variety of services to help the federal government find and deport immigrants. ICE’s Palantir-furnished case management software, for example, “plays a critical role in supporting the daily operations of ICE, ensuring critical mission success,” according to federal contracting documents.</p>
<p>“It’s unacceptable that the same company that is targeting our neighbors for deportation and providing tools to the Israeli military is also providing software for our hospitals,” said Kenny Morris, an organizer with the American Friend Service Committee, which shared the contract documents with The Intercept.</p>
<!-- BLOCK(cta)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22CTA%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%7D) --><!-- END-BLOCK(cta)[0] -->
<p>Established by the state legislature, New York City Health and Hospitals is the nation’s biggest municipal health care system, administering over 70 facilities throughout New York City, including Bellevue Hospital, and providing care for over 1 million New Yorkers annually.</p>
<p>New York City Health and Hospitals spokesperson Adam Shrier did not respond to multiple requests to discuss the contract’s details. Palantir spokesperson Drew Messing said the company does not use or share hospital data outside the bounds of its contract.</p>
<p>Palantir’s contract with New York’s public health care system allows the company to work with patients’ protected health information, or PHI. With permission from New York City Health and Hospitals, Palantir can “de-identify PHI and utilize de-identified PHI for purposes other than research,” the contract states. De-identification generally involves the stripping of certain revealing information, such as names, Social Security numbers, and birthdays. Such provisions are common in contracts involving health data.</p>
<p>Activists who oppose Palantir’s involvement in New York point to a large body of research that indicates re-identifying personal data, including in medial contexts, is <a href="https://georgetownlawtechreview.org/re-identification-of-anonymized-data/GLTR-04-2017/">often</a> <a href="https://techscience.org/a/2017082801/">trivial</a>.</p>
<p>“Any contract that shares any of New Yorkers’ highly personal data from NYC Health &amp; Hospital’s with Palantir, a key player in the Trump administration’s mass deportation effort, is reckless and puts countless lives at risk,” said Beth Haroules of the New York Civil Liberties Union. “Every New Yorker, without exception, has a right to quality healthcare and city services. New Yorkers must be able to seek healthcare without fear that their intimate medical information, or immigration status, will be delivered to the federal government on a silver platter.”</p>
<!-- BLOCK(newsletter)[0](%7B%22componentName%22%3A%22NEWSLETTER%22%2C%22entityType%22%3A%22SHORTCODE%22%2C%22optional%22%3Atrue%7D)(%7B%7D) --><!-- END-BLOCK(newsletter)[0] -->
<p>Palantir has long provided similar services to the U.K. National Health Service, a business relationship that today has an increasing number of detractors. Palantir “has absolutely no place in the NHS, looking after patients’ personal data,” Green Party leader Zack Polanski recently stated in a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2026/feb/05/calls-to-halt-uk-palantir-contracts-grow-amid-lack-of-transparency-over-deals">letter to the U.K. health secretary</a>.</p>
<figure>
<blockquote>
<p>“Palantir is targeting the exact patients that NYCHH is looking to serve.” </p>
</blockquote>
</figure>
<p>Some New York-based groups feel similarly out of distrust for what the firm could do with troves of sensitive personal data.</p>
<p>“Palantir is targeting the exact patients that NYCHH is looking to serve,” said Jonathan Westin of the Brooklyn-based organization Climate Organizing Hub. “They should immediately sever their contract with Palantir and stand with the millions of immigrant New Yorkers that are being targeted by ICE in this moment.”</p>
<p>“The chaos Palantir is inflicting through its technology is not just limited to the kidnapping of our immigrant neighbors and the murder of heroes like our fellow nurse, Alex Pretti,” said Hannah Drummond, an Asheville, North Carolina-based nurse and organizer with National Nurses United, a nursing union. “As a nurse and patient advocate, I don’t want anything having to do with Palantir in my hospital — and neither should any elected leader who claims to represent nurses.”</p>
<p>Palantir’s vocally right-wing CEO Alex Karp&nbsp;has been a <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/11/08/alex-karp-palantir-democrats-mamdani">frequent</a> critic <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/video/6384521232112">of New York City’s</a> newly inaugurated democratic socialist Mayor Zohran Mamdani. Health and Hospitals operates as a public benefit corporation, but the mayor can exert considerable influence over the network, for instance through the appointment of its board of directors. Its president, Dr. Mitchell Katz, was <a href="https://www.nyc.gov/site/ocme/news/cm1025/mayor-elect-mamdani-renominates-nyc-health-hospitals-president-ceo-dr-mitchell-katz-and">renominated</a> by Mamdani, then the mayor-elect, late last year.</p>
<p>The mayor’s office did not respond in time for publication when asked about its stance on the contract.<a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LT6502: A 6502-based homebrew laptop (351 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502</link>
            <guid>47025399</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:12:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502">https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025399">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">LT6502</h2><a id="user-content-lt6502" aria-label="Permalink: LT6502" href="#lt6502"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A 6502 based laptop design</p>
<p dir="auto">Yes, I know I'm crazy, but I figured why not. I'm enjoying working the <a href="https://github.com/TechPaula/PC6502/">PC6502</a> project but having a little tower of PCBs on the sofa isn't the best.
It's very simple, these are the specs</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>65C02 running at 8MHz</li>
<li>46K RAM</li>
<li>BASIC in ROM</li>
<li>65C22 VIA (for timers and some IO)</li>
<li>9" DIsplay (with built in font/simple graphics)</li>
<li>Built in keyboard</li>
<li>Compact Flash for storage</li>
<li>10000mAh battery built in</li>
<li>USBC powered/charged</li>
<li>Serial Console</li>
<li>1 internal expansion slot</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pictures</h2><a id="user-content-pictures" aria-label="Permalink: Pictures" href="#pictures"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Assembled front view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_Front_Open.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_Front_Open.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the front"></a>
Assembled rear view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_Rear_Open.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_Rear_Open.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the rear"></a>
Assembled LHS view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_LHS_Open.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_LHS_Open.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the left hand side"></a>
Assembled RHS view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_RHS_Open.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_RHS_Open.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the right hand side"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Assembled closed front view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_Front_Closed.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_Front_Closed.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the front when closed"></a>
Assembled closed rear view
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/Assembled_Rear_Closed.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/Assembled_Rear_Closed.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the assembled 6502 laptop in it's 3D printed case from the rear when closed"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Lower parts (main board, battery, keyboard) in it's case
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/blob/main/Images/LT6502_BaseCase.jpeg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/TechPaula/LT6502/raw/main/Images/LT6502_BaseCase.jpeg?raw=true" alt="Picture of the 6502 laptop base in it's 3D printed case"></a>
Screen with BASIC code
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TechPaula/LT6502/refs/heads/main/Images/LT6502_SCREEN_BASIC.jpeg"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TechPaula/LT6502/refs/heads/main/Images/LT6502_SCREEN_BASIC.jpeg" alt="Picture of the 6502 laptop with screen and basic Jan 2026"></a>
First bring up
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TechPaula/LT6502/refs/heads/main/Images/Keyboard_hello_basic_Test.jpeg"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/TechPaula/LT6502/refs/heads/main/Images/Keyboard_hello_basic_Test.jpeg" alt="Picture of the 6502 laptop as of 5th Jan 2026"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Status</h2><a id="user-content-status" aria-label="Permalink: Status" href="#status"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>2025-11-12 - Initial commit with work in progress PCB, Schematics complete.</li>
<li>2025-12-30 - PCBs arrived!</li>
<li>2026-01-01 - Initial power up of PCBs gives all the correct voltages</li>
<li>2026-01-03 - Bring up of board with simple ROM/RAM/Console working.</li>
<li>2026-01-04 - VIA working, ACIA working, comms to/from the keyboard in basic working. Begun integrating keyboard into firmware</li>
<li>2026-01-05 - Keyboard now integrated into firmware, so you can type on the keyboard and don't need the console for input</li>
<li>2026-01-09 - Compact flash working, Beeper also now working. Also runs from battery just fine.</li>
<li>2026-01-16 - Connected a 4.3" 800x480 RA8875 based display and got that working. I failed to get the LT7683 based display working.</li>
<li>2026-01-17 - work on a number of case related things that did not quite work in actual life.</li>
<li>2026-01-18 - Tweaked CPLD to slow down FTDI read/writes. Also begun work on bios, added start beep and begun work on load/save functions</li>
<li>2026-02-08 - Added more commands, notably SAVE,LOAD and DIR for compact flash</li>
<li>2026-02-13 - Added more graphics commands :)</li>
<li>2026-02-14 - Assembled the case</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">In Progress</h2><a id="user-content-in-progress" aria-label="Permalink: In Progress" href="#in-progress"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Expansion board</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">To do (probably in order)</h2><a id="user-content-to-do-probably-in-order" aria-label="Permalink: To do (probably in order)" href="#to-do-probably-in-order"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>add in larger display (going to try a 10.1" RA8889 based 1024x600, fall back is a 9" RA8875 based 800x480)</li>
<li>Fix buggy keyscan code on MEGA644P</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Memory Map</h2><a id="user-content-memory-map" aria-label="Permalink: Memory Map" href="#memory-map"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The memory map is fairly stable at the moment, everything seems to be working fine.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">High Level</h4><a id="user-content-high-level" aria-label="Permalink: High Level" href="#high-level"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Start</th>
<th>End</th>
<th>Size (Dec)</th>
<th>Size (Hex)</th>
<th>What is it</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0x0000</td>
<td>0xBEAF</td>
<td>48816</td>
<td>0xBEB0</td>
<td>RAM</td>
<td>This includes Zeropage and other bits BASIC may need (more below)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBE00</td>
<td>0xBFFF</td>
<td>512</td>
<td>0x200</td>
<td>peripherals</td>
<td>This is where the peripherals are mapped (see below)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xC000</td>
<td>0xFFFF</td>
<td>12288</td>
<td>0x3000</td>
<td>ROM</td>
<td>holding EhBASIC, eWoz monitor, bootstrap and vectors</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">ROM breakdown</h5><a id="user-content-rom-breakdown" aria-label="Permalink: ROM breakdown" href="#rom-breakdown"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Start</th>
<th>End</th>
<th>Size (Dec)</th>
<th>Size (Hex)</th>
<th>What is it</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0xC000</td>
<td>0xFAFF</td>
<td>15104</td>
<td>0x3B0</td>
<td>EhBASIC</td>
<td>EhBASIC 2.22p5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xF000</td>
<td>0xF2FF</td>
<td>768</td>
<td>0x300</td>
<td>eWozMon</td>
<td><a href="https://gist.github.com/BigEd/2760560">Enhanced Wozmon</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xF300</td>
<td>0xFFF9</td>
<td>3322</td>
<td>0xCFA</td>
<td>Bootstrap</td>
<td>startup messages and also input/output/load/save functions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xFFFA</td>
<td>0xFFFF</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>0x0A</td>
<td>6502 Vectors</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">RAM breakdown</h5><a id="user-content-ram-breakdown" aria-label="Permalink: RAM breakdown" href="#ram-breakdown"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Start</th>
<th>End</th>
<th>Size (Dec)</th>
<th>Size (Hex)</th>
<th>What is it</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0x0000</td>
<td>0x02FF</td>
<td>768</td>
<td>0x300</td>
<td>RAM</td>
<td>This includes Zeropage and other bits BASIC may need</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x0300</td>
<td>0x07FF</td>
<td>1280</td>
<td>0x500</td>
<td>RAM</td>
<td>This is going to be for the compact flash reading/writing</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x0800</td>
<td>0xBDFF</td>
<td>46592</td>
<td>0xB6B0</td>
<td>ROM</td>
<td>BASIC RAM available</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">peripherals</h5><a id="user-content-peripherals" aria-label="Permalink: peripherals" href="#peripherals"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Address</th>
<th>subAddr range</th>
<th>RW</th>
<th>What is it</th>
<th>Notes</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0xBE0O</td>
<td>00-FF</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>Expansion slot</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBF00</td>
<td>00-9F</td>
<td></td>
<td>Unused Currently</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFAO</td>
<td>0-0</td>
<td>W</td>
<td>Beeper</td>
<td>just write 0xFF and 0x00 to turn on/off the speaker</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFBO</td>
<td>0-7</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>Compact Flash</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFCO</td>
<td>0-F</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>65C22</td>
<td>on board VIA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFDO</td>
<td>0-F</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>Display</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFEO</td>
<td>0-F</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>65C21</td>
<td>internal keyboard</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xBFF0</td>
<td>0-1</td>
<td>RW</td>
<td>Console</td>
<td>FTDI USB console port</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">EhBASIC Extra commands</h2><a id="user-content-ehbasic-extra-commands" aria-label="Permalink: EhBASIC Extra commands" href="#ehbasic-extra-commands"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I've Added a some extra commands to EhBASIC and they are as follows;</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>BEEP P,L - Pitch (P) is 0-255, length (L) = 0 to 255</li>
<li>CIRCLE X,Y,R,C,F - Draws a Circle, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479, R(radius) is 1 - 65535, C is 8bit RGB Value (RRRGGGBB), F is fill (0 = no fill, 1 = fill)</li>
<li>CLS - Clear screen (both graphic and text mode)</li>
<li>COLOUR &lt;0-255&gt; - Sets the colour (text) to 8bit RGB value, in the form RRRGGGBB</li>
<li>DIR - Scans the Compact Flash card and shows slot number and name for any files present</li>
<li>ELIPSE - X,Y,RX,RY,C,F - Draws an elipse, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479, RX is X radius, RY is Y radius, C is colour and F is fill</li>
<li>LINE X,Y,EX,EY,C - Draws a line, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479, EX is X end point (0-799), EY is Y end point (0-479), C is colour</li>
<li>LOAD &lt;0-2047&gt; - LOAD a file from CF</li>
<li>MODE &lt;0,1&gt; - Sets the display mode, MODE 0 is text, MODE 1 is graphics</li>
<li>OUTK - Outputs Text to the 8 character display on the keybed, can be a string or value, anything more than 8 characters will result in text shifting. a String will clear the display and then output the characters</li>
<li>PLOT X,Y,C - Plots a dot, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479 and C is 8bit RGB Value (RRRGGGBB)</li>
<li>SAVE &lt;0-2047&gt;,"" - SAVE current BASIC program into a SLOT and give it a name, upto 16 characters</li>
<li>SQUARE - X,Y,EX,EY,C,F - Draws a square, X is 0-799, Y is 0-479, EX is X end point (0-799), EY is Y end point (0-479), C is colour and F is fill</li>
<li>WOZMON - Jumps to wozmon, Q will exit WOZMON and return to basic (Handy for check chunks of memory)</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU bans the destruction of unsold apparel, clothing, accessories and footwear (962 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-eu-rules-stop-destruction-unsold-clothes-and-shoes-2026-02-09_en</link>
            <guid>47025378</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:10:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-eu-rules-stop-destruction-unsold-clothes-and-shoes-2026-02-09_en">https://environment.ec.europa.eu/news/new-eu-rules-stop-destruction-unsold-clothes-and-shoes-2026-02-09_en</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025378">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>The European Commission today (Feb 9) adopted new measures under the Ecodesign for Sustainable Products Regulation (ESPR) to prevent the destruction of unsold apparel, clothing, accessories and footwear.</p><p>The rules will help cut waste, reduce environmental damage and create a level playing field for companies embracing sustainable business models, allowing them to reap the benefits of a more circular economy.</p><p>Every year in Europe, an estimated<strong> 4-9% of unsold textiles</strong> are destroyed before ever being worn. This waste generates around <strong>5.6 million tons</strong> of CO2 emissions – almost equal to Sweden’s total net emissions in 2021.</p><p>To help reduce this wasteful practice, the ESPR requires companies to disclose information on the unsold consumer products they discard as waste. It also introduces a ban on the destruction of unsold apparel, clothing accessories and footwear.</p><p>The Delegated and Implementing Acts adopted today will support businesses in complying with these requirements by:</p><ul><li><strong>Clarifying derogations</strong>: The Delegated Act outlines specific and justified circumstances under which the destruction will be permitted, for instance, due to safety reasons or product damage. National authorities will oversee compliance.</li><li><strong>Facilitating disclosure:</strong> The Implementing Act introduces a standardised format for businesses to disclose the volumes of unsold consumer goods they discard. This applies from February 2027, giving businesses sufficient time to adapt.</li></ul><p>Instead of discarding stock, companies are encouraged to manage their stock more effectively, handle returns, and explore alternatives such as resale, remanufacturing, donations, or reuse.</p><p>The ban on destruction of unsold apparel, clothing accessories and footwear and the derogations will apply to large companies from <strong>19 July 2026.</strong> Medium-sized companies are expected to follow in 2030. The rules on disclosure under the ESPR <strong>already apply</strong> <strong>to large companies</strong> and will also apply to medium-sized companies in 2030.</p><blockquote><p>"The textile sector is leading the way in the transition to sustainability, but there are still challenges. The numbers on waste show the need to act. With these new measures, the textile sector will be empowered to move towards sustainable and circular practices, and we can boost our competitiveness and reduce our dependencies."</p><p><strong>Jessika Roswall, Commissioner for Environment, Water Resilience and a Competitive Circular Economy</strong></p></blockquote><h4><strong>Background</strong></h4><p>The destruction of unsold goods is a wasteful practice. In France alone, around €630 million worth of unsold products are destroyed each year. Online shopping also fuels the issue: in Germany, nearly 20 million returned items are discarded annually.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>Textiles are a major part of the problem, and a key focus for action. To cut waste and reduce the sector’s environmental footprint, the European Commission is promoting more sustainable production while helping European companies stay competitive.&nbsp;</p><p>The ESPR is central to this effort. It will make products on the EU market more durable, reusable and recyclable, while boosting efficiency and circularity.</p><h5><strong>More information</strong></h5><p><a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/publications/commission-delegated-regulation-setting-out-derogations-prohibition-destruction-unsold-consumer_en">Delegated Regulation setting out derogations from the prohibition of destruction of unsold consumer products | European Commission</a></p><p><a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/publications/commission-implementing-regulation-details-and-format-disclosure-information-discarded-unsold_en">Implementing Regulation on the details and format for the disclosure of information on discarded unsold consumer products | European Commission</a></p><p><a href="https://commission.europa.eu/energy-climate-change-environment/standards-tools-and-labels/products-labelling-rules-and-requirements/ecodesign-sustainable-products-regulation_en">Ecodesign for Sustainable Products Regulation | European Commission</a></p><p><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX%3A32024R1781&amp;qid=1719580391746">Ecodesign for Sustainable Products Regulation | EUR-Lex</a></p><p><a href="https://environment.ec.europa.eu/strategy/textiles-strategy_en">Textiles strategy | European Commission</a></p><p><a href="https://www.eea.europa.eu/en/analysis/publications/the-destruction-of-returned-and-unsold-textiles-in-europes-circular-economy">The destruction of returned and unsold textiles in Europe’s circular economy | European Environment Agency (EEA)</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Knock-Knock.net – Visualizing the bots knocking on my server's door (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://knock-knock.net</link>
            <guid>47025338</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:06:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://knock-knock.net">https://knock-knock.net</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025338">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p>KNOCK-KNOCK.NET</p>
	    <p>Set up an unprotected server on the net, and the bots start swarming!</p><p> This site shows bots attempting (unsuccessfully) to break into an ordinary internet server.</p>
            <p>This constant chatter of bots knocking on the doors of machines on the net has been referred to as <em>"the background radiation of the Internet".</em></p>
	    <p>Knock-knock.net is a visualization of this bot traffic.
	    It shows the bot activity in real-time, and provides historic stats of the bot attacks over time: where they are coming from, the most common usernames and passwords attempted, the worst offending ISPs, and in some cases, why the password or username was chosen.</p>
            <p>Have fun! Send questions or comments to:<br><a href="#"></a></p>
            <p><a href="https://www.abuseipdb.com/user/270949" title="AbuseIPDB is an IP address blacklist for webmasters and sysadmins to report IP addresses engaging in abusive behavior on their networks" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
                <img src="https://www.abuseipdb.com/contributor/270949.svg" alt="AbuseIPDB Contributor Badge">
              </a>
            </p>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Palantir vs. the "Republik": US analytics firm takes magazine to court (226 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.heise.de/en/news/Palantir-vs-the-Republik-US-analytics-firm-takes-magazine-to-court-11176508.html</link>
            <guid>47025188</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:51:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.heise.de/en/news/Palantir-vs-the-Republik-US-analytics-firm-takes-magazine-to-court-11176508.html">https://www.heise.de/en/news/Palantir-vs-the-Republik-US-analytics-firm-takes-magazine-to-court-11176508.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47025188">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
          





<a-collapse has-indicator="">
  
  <div data-collapse-target="">
      
  <nav>
    <ol>
        
        <li>

          
            <span aria-current="page">
              Palantir vs. the "Republik": US analytics firm takes magazine to court
            </span>

            
              <ul>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_streisand_effect_0" title="Streisand Effect" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Streisand Effect
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_swiss__1" title="Swiss Counterstatements" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Swiss Counterstatements
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_difficult__2" title="Difficult Terrain Europe" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Difficult Terrain Europe
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav__borderline__3" title="&quot;Borderline Conspiracy Theories&quot;" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    "Borderline Conspiracy Theories"
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
                <li>
                
                  <a href="#nav_palantir__4" title="Palantir Rejects Accusation of Intimidation" data-google-interstitial="false">
                    Palantir Rejects Accusation of Intimidation
                  </a>
                
                </li>
              
              </ul>
            

          

        </li>
    </ol>

    

    

  </nav>

    </div>
  
</a-collapse>


          <!-- RSPEAK_START -->

        

        <p>Palantir Technologies, the US provider of analytics software, finds itself directly affected by two reports from the Swiss online magazine "Republik". After the company unsuccessfully demanded a counterstatement from the magazine, it now wants to enforce one through legal action. It's about a factual comparison, says the software provider. The "Republik" creators appear surprised.</p>
<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->




  


<!-- RSPEAK_START -->

<h3 id="nav_streisand_effect_0">Streisand Effect</h3>
<p>With the step to court, Palantir has generated more attention for the "Republik" reporting than the objected articles themselves could have caused – 23 years after Barbra Streisand <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Barbra-Streisand-klagt-gegen-Homepage-Betreiber-79921.html?from-en=1">triggered the effect named after her</a>. And yet, there are reasons why Palantir is acting this way.</p>
<p>While in Germany the provider of data linking and data analysis software for authorities with surveillance powers is successful with at least some state customers. The company has so far had – as far as is known – little state clientele in Switzerland.</p>
<p>In December, "Republik" <a href="https://www.republik.ch/2025/12/08/wie-hartnaeckig-palantir-die-schweiz-umwarb">extensively quoted from Swiss administration files</a>. According to this, Palantir repeatedly sought contact with Swiss authorities – and found it. In some cases, it originated from Palantir, in others, likely from public bodies. The matters concerned the military, police, and health authorities. However, no business deal was apparently concluded.</p>
<p>Palantir feels unfairly treated by the reporting on this. "We can confirm that an application for a counterstatement has been filed with the Commercial Court in this matter," the communications officer of the Cantonal High Court told heise online on Friday upon request.</p>
<h3 id="nav_swiss__1">Swiss Counterstatements</h3>
<p>Swiss law provides for counterstatements, meaning that as soon as a request for a counterstatement has been rejected by a medium, a civil court can examine the matter and hear both sides. The Commercial Court of Zurich is responsible here. The Commercial Court of Zurich is responsible here.</p>
<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->


  



  




<!-- RSPEAK_START -->

<p>Palantir says it had to sue to uphold its legal claim. "Palantir fully respects press freedom and the essential role of independent media in public debate," said a company spokeswoman. The right to a counterstatement is a "correction instrument intended to provide the public with balanced information."</p>
<p>For Palantir, the "Republik" reporting came at an inopportune time. This is because important procurement decisions are currently being made in several business areas in many European countries: the modernization and expansion of military, intelligence, and secret services, as well as police authorities, would be a promising business for Palantir and its software, which is also helpful for official surveillance.</p>
<p>In its home market, the USA, the company does business with US federal authorities for about a quarter of a billion US dollars, according to transparency data <a href="https://www.usaspending.gov/recipient/1ea8a9a4-3726-3491-9040-66950bb67606-C/latest">approximately a quarter of a billion US dollars</a>. Customers include the US Department of Defense, the Army, and the FBI. The company reports nearly 4.5 billion US dollars in revenue for 2025, about a tenth of SAP's annual revenue. And yet, Palantir is valued on the stock market at around 300 billion euros, while SAP comes in at around 200 billion.</p>
<h3 id="nav_difficult__2">Difficult Terrain Europe</h3>
<p>The European market remains difficult terrain for Palantir. The connection to the Immigration and Customs Enforcement agency (ICE), <a href="https://www.heise.de/hintergrund/USA-Die-Architektur-der-Abschiebung-und-Palantirs-Rolle-im-neuen-ICE-System-11152960.html?from-en=1">which is supposed to track down illegal migrants with brutal methods and a lot of high-tech</a>, causes consternation in Europe. As a US company, Palantir is subject to US law, which increasingly questions international cooperation in security matters – this is unlikely to be conducive to sales for Palantir.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the uproar had just subsided elsewhere: Palantir was criticized for its involvement in Israel. Founders Peter Thiel and Alex Karp had agreed to a strategic partnership with the Israeli Ministry of Defense in January 2024, Bloomberg reported at the time. The report on this is <a href="https://www.palantir.com/assets/xrfr7uokpv1b/3MuEeA8MLbLDAyxixTsiIe/9e4a11a7fb058554a8a1e3cd83e31c09/C134184_finaleprint.pdf">publicly available on the Palantir website</a>.</p>
<p>The small medium from Switzerland is hardly comparable to industry giants like Bloomberg. It has been published ad-free and exclusively online since 2018. It is primarily supported by a good 30,000 subscribers, a majority of whom are also cooperative members with voting rights. Not a media behemoth with a large publisher behind it.</p>
<h3 id="nav__borderline__3">"Borderline Conspiracy Theories"</h3>
<p>Shortly after the publication of the two articles now being heard in court, Courtney Bowman, head of Palantir's "Privacy and Civil Liberties" department, had already set the course on LinkedIn: The reports from "Republik" were "full of distortions, insinuations, and borderline conspiracy theories."</p>
<p>Bowman accuses the authors of having reproduced a report from the Swiss Army Staff too uncritically – whose authors, unfortunately, had "relied on a limited set of search engine hit sources." The Palantir representative, in turn, provided no evidence for his claims.</p>
<p>"I believe we have done excellent research and documented it very comprehensively," says Daniel Binswanger, co-editor-in-chief of "Republik," in an interview with heise online. Research based on Swiss government documents is one of the "best foundations for reporting." He is very confident about the outcome of the proceedings.</p>
<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->

  




<!-- RSPEAK_START -->

<h3 id="nav_palantir__4">Palantir Rejects Accusation of Intimidation</h3>
<p>Palantir strongly rejects the impression that a multi-billion dollar company is flexing its muscles against a small magazine: Any accusation that this is a strategic attempt to intimidate unfavorable reporting through legal action is unfounded, the company spokeswoman emphasizes: "Palantir merely seeks the publication of a concise and appropriate counterstatement to correct significant inaccuracies."</p>
<p>However, the company does not disclose what specific "significant inaccuracies" Palantir wants to see corrected. Palantir did not respond to a request to send the "corrections" specifically demanded by "Republik" by Friday afternoon.</p>
<p>Whether the company will achieve at least partial success with its approach in court is hardly predictable. The Swiss right to a counterstatement involves no examination by the court whether a statement was actually correct. This is why it is a frequently used form in the Swiss media world when companies feel they have been misrepresented.</p>
<p>"The right to a counterstatement is not about whether something is true or false," explains "Republik" co-editor-in-chief Daniel Binswanger. "It's about whether another version of the facts could also be possible." However, this only concerns factual representation. Opinions, on the other hand, are not challengeable in Switzerland either.</p>
<p>For the Swiss online magazine, however, the effect is noticeable and measurable. "We are overwhelmed," says Daniel Binswanger in an interview with heise online. "The offers of donations, expressions of solidarity – it's gigantic," he says. "We've never experienced a story triggering this." Ms. Streisand sends her regards.</p>


<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->

<!-- RSPEAK_START -->
<p>

<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
<span>(<a href="mailto:vbr@heise.de" title="Volker Briegleb">vbr</a>)</span>
<!-- RSPEAK_START -->
</p>
<div>
    <p>
      Don't miss any news – follow us on
      <a href="https://www.facebook.com/heiseonlineEnglish">Facebook</a>,
      <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/104691972">LinkedIn</a> or
      <a href="https://social.heise.de/@heiseonlineenglish">Mastodon</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <em>This article was originally published in
      
        <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Palantir-gegen-die-Republik-US-Analysefirma-geht-gegen-Magazin-vor-Gericht-11176503.html">German</a>.
      
      It was translated with technical assistance and editorially reviewed before publication.</em>
    </p>
  </div>



        

        
        <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
        

<a-gift has-access="">
    
</a-gift>


        
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hideki Sato, designer of all Sega's consoles, has died (397 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.videogameschronicle.com/news/hideki-sato-designer-of-segas-consoles-dies-age-75/</link>
            <guid>47024907</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 16:19:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.videogameschronicle.com/news/hideki-sato-designer-of-segas-consoles-dies-age-75/">https://www.videogameschronicle.com/news/hideki-sato-designer-of-segas-consoles-dies-age-75/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47024907">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content_body"><p><span>Hideki Sato, the designer behind virtually every Sega console, and the company’s former president, has died age 77.</span></p><p><span>Japanese games outlet <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://x.com/beep2021/status/2022662105904877996?s=46">Beep21 </a>reports that Sato passed away this weekend.</span></p><p><span>Sato and his R&amp;D team were responsible for the creation of <a title="Companies > Sega [1,106 articles]" href="https://www.videogameschronicle.com/companies/sega/">Sega</a>’s arcade and home console hardware, including the Master System, Genesis / Mega Drive, Saturn, and Dreamcast.</span></p><p><span>The engineer joined Sega in 1971 and was the company’s acting president between 2001 and 2003. He left the company in 2008.</span></p><p><span>“From the beginning, Sega’s home console development has always been influenced by our arcade development,” Sato previously told <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://shmuplations.com/segahistory/">Famitsu</a> in an interview covering Sega’s history.</span></p><p><span>“Our first 8-bit machine was the </span><span>SC-3000</span><span>. This was a <a title="Platforms > PC [11,949 articles]" href="https://www.videogameschronicle.com/platforms/pc/">PC</a> for beginner-level users. At that time, Sega only did arcade games, so this was our first challenge. We had no idea how many units we’d sell.”</span></p><p><span>Sato said of Mega Drive, Sega’s most successful console: “At that point, we decided to start developing a new home console. By then, arcade games were using 16-bit CPUs. </span></p><p><span>“Arcade development was something we were very invested in, so we were always using the most cutting-edge technology there. Naturally, it started us thinking: what if we used that technology in a home console? </span></p><p><span>“Two years after we started development, it was done: a 16-bit CPU home console, the Megadrive. The 68000 chip had also recently come down in price, so the timing was right.”</span></p><p><span>On Dreamcast, the release that ultimately ended Sega’s run in hardware, Sato said the keyword for the development was “play and communication.”</span></p><p><span>“The ultimate form of communication is a direct connection with another, and we included the modem and the linkable VMUs for that purpose,” he said. </span></p><p><span>“We had also planned to have some sort of linking function with cell phones, but we weren’t able to realize it. Consumers were now used to the raging ‘bit wars’, so even though we knew it was a lot of nonsense, we needed to appeal to them in those terms with the Dreamcast. </span></p><p><span>“And so we marketed it as having a ‘128 bit graphics engine RISC CPU’, even the SH-4 was only 64-bit. (laughs) On the other hand, we extensively customized the original SH-4 for the Dreamcast, to the point where I think you could almost call it something new.”</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gwtar: A static efficient single-file HTML format (226 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gwern.net/gwtar</link>
            <guid>47024506</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 15:37:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gwern.net/gwtar">https://gwern.net/gwtar</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47024506">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI is going to kill app subscriptions (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nichehunt.app/blog/ai-going-to-kill-app-subscriptions</link>
            <guid>47024387</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 15:21:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nichehunt.app/blog/ai-going-to-kill-app-subscriptions">https://nichehunt.app/blog/ai-going-to-kill-app-subscriptions</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47024387">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p>The math is simple: if it costs almost nothing to build an app, it costs almost nothing to clone an app. And if cloning is free, subscription pricing dies.</p>
<p>We're already seeing this play out in the numbers. Apple's App Store got 557K new submissions in 2025, up 24% from 2024 (source: Appfigures). That's not because people suddenly got more creative. It's because building an app went from a $50K project to a weekend with Claude.</p>
<h2>What happens to pricing</h2>
<p>For apps that run locally—no servers, no cloud costs—subscriptions make no sense anymore. The only real cost is development, and that's becoming negligible. If someone charges $10/month for a local PDF editor, someone else will build a clone for $5 one-time. Then someone will make it free.</p>
<p>Apps that need servers (sync, AI features, storage) will still have subscriptions, but the price will drop to barely above cost. Same logic applies: easy to copy means no pricing power.</p>
<h2>Apple isn't fighting this</h2>
<p>I thought Apple to tighten App Store review to slow down the flood of apps. Instead they put Claude in Xcode. They're not just okay with AI-generated apps—they're actively supporting it.</p>
<p>The revenue numbers back this up. App Store grew 11% in 2025, Google Play 5%. There's still tons of unmet demand, especially for niche use cases that were never worth building before. Lower development costs mean these niches finally get served.</p>
<h2>Developer perspective</h2>
<p>This sucks for developers trying to make a living from apps. The competitive pressure is going to be brutal. But for users? It's great. People have been complaining about app subscription costs for years. There's that old complaint: "Why do I have to keep paying for software after I already paid $1000 for my iPhone?"</p>
<p>That might actually become reality now.</p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon, Google Unwittingly Reveal the Severity of the U.S. Surveillance State (823 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://greenwald.substack.com/p/amazons-ring-and-googles-nest-unwittingly</link>
            <guid>47023238</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 12:42:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://greenwald.substack.com/p/amazons-ring-and-googles-nest-unwittingly">https://greenwald.substack.com/p/amazons-ring-and-googles-nest-unwittingly</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47023238">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic" width="1456" height="971" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:971,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1996048,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/heic&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://greenwald.substack.com/i/187789911?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!MwWG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e3e6373-e7bb-4397-8e93-a5ad524ee4cf_4000x2667.heic 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em>One of Google’s Nest surveillance cameras, whose recordings can be accessed          by Google even if users don’t subscribe to the security firm’s services.                   </em><span>CC Photo Lab / Shutterstock</span></figcaption></figure></div><p><strong>That the U.S. Surveillance State is</strong><span> rapidly growing to the point of ubiquity has been demonstrated over the past week by seemingly benign events. While the picture that emerges is grim, to put it mildly, at least Americans are again confronted with crystal clarity over how severe this has become.</span></p><p><span>The latest round of valid panic over privacy began during the Super Bowl held on Sunday. During the game, Amazon ran </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OheUzrXsKrY" rel="">a commercial</a><span> for its Ring camera security system. The ad manipulatively exploited people’s love of dogs to induce them to ignore the consequences of what Amazon was touting. It seems that trick did not work.</span></p><p>The ad highlighted what the company calls its “Search Party” feature, whereby one can upload a picture, for example, of a lost dog. Doing so will activate multiple other Amazon Ring cameras in the neighborhood, which will, in turn, use AI programs to scan all dogs, it seems, and identify the one that is lost. The 30-second commercial was full of heart-tugging scenes of young children and elderly people being reunited with their lost dogs.</p><p>But the graphic Amazon used seems to have unwittingly depicted how invasive this technology can be. That this capability now exists in a product that has long been pitched as nothing more than a simple tool for homeowners to monitor their own homes created, it seems, an unavoidable contrast between public understanding of Ring and what Amazon was now boasting it could do.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png" width="2424" height="1243" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1243,&quot;width&quot;:2424,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:5364048,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://greenwald.substack.com/i/187789911?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd64d01cc-601f-4649-bf9d-c537edb2bff8_2968x1522.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0JUB!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82e6327a-fa3c-4292-b929-8f1c12444f41_2424x1243.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em>Amazon’s Super Bowl ad for Ring and its “Search Party” feature.</em></figcaption></figure></div><p>Many people were not just surprised but quite shocked and alarmed to learn that what they thought was merely their own personal security system now has the ability to link with countless other Ring cameras to form a neighborhood-wide (or city-wide, or state-wide) surveillance dragnet. That Amazon emphasized that this feature is available (for now) only to those who “opt-in” did not assuage concerns.</p><p><span>Numerous media outlets sounded the alarm. The online privacy group Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF) </span><a href="https://abc7chicago.com/post/ring-flock-partnership-amazon-scraps-surveillance-company-safety-super-bowl-commercial-backlash/18596207/" rel="">condemned</a><span> Ring’s program as previewing “a world where biometric identification could be unleashed from consumer devices to identify, track, and locate anything — human, pet, and otherwise.”</span></p><p><span>Many private citizens who previously used Ring also reacted negatively. “Viral videos online show people removing or destroying their cameras over privacy concerns,” </span><a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2026/02/10/ring-super-bowl-ad-dog-camera-privacy/88606738007/" rel="">reported</a><span> USA Today. The backlash became so severe that, just days later, Amazon — seeking to assuage public anger — </span><a href="https://abc7chicago.com/post/ring-flock-partnership-amazon-scraps-surveillance-company-safety-super-bowl-commercial-backlash/18596207/" rel="">announced</a><span> the termination of a partnership between Ring and Flock Safety, a police surveillance tech company (while Flock is unrelated to Search Party, public backlash made it impossible, at least for now, for Amazon to send Ring’s user data to a police surveillance firm).</span></p><p>The Amazon ad seems to have triggered a long-overdue spotlight on how the combination of ubiquitous cameras, AI, and rapidly advancing facial recognition software will render the term “privacy” little more than a quaint concept from the past. As EFF put it, Ring’s program “could already run afoul of biometric privacy laws in some states, which require explicit, informed consent from individuals before a company can just run face recognition on someone.”</p><p>Those concerns escalated just a few days later in the context of the Tucson disappearance of Nancy Guthrie, mother of long-time TODAY Show host Savannah Guthrie. At the home where she lives, Nancy Guthrie used Google’s Nest camera for security, a product similar to Amazon’s Ring.</p><p><span>Guthrie, however, did not pay Google for a subscription for those cameras, instead solely using the cameras for real-time monitoring. As CBS News </span><a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/cybersecurity-experts-nancy-guthrie-surveillance-footage-recovery/" rel="">explained</a><span>, “with a free Google Nest plan, the video should have been deleted within 3 to 6 hours — long after Guthrie was reported missing.” Even professional privacy advocates have understood that customers who use Nest without a subscription will not have their cameras connected to Google’s data servers, meaning that no recordings will be stored or available for any period beyond a few hours.</span></p><p><span>For that reason, Pima County Sheriff Chris Nanos </span><a href="https://fortune.com/2026/02/11/privacy-concerns-nancy-guthrie-google-nest-camera-footage-kidnapping/" rel="">announced</a><span> early on “that there was no video available in part because Guthrie didn’t have an active subscription to the company.” Many people, for obvious reasons, prefer to avoid permanently storing comprehensive daily video reports with Google of when they leave and return to their own home, or who visits them at their home, when, and for how long.</span></p><p>Despite all this, FBI investigators on the case were somehow magically able to “recover” this video from Guthrie’s camera many days later. FBI Director Kash Patel was essentially forced to admit this when he released still images of what appears to be the masked perpetrator who broke into Guthrie’s home. (The Google user agreement, which few users read, does protect the company by stating that images may be stored even in the absence of a subscription.)</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png" width="920" height="642" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:642,&quot;width&quot;:920,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:689574,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://greenwald.substack.com/i/187789911?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!OWb9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F36f93214-f835-4323-841f-53de4ae5f0ce_920x642.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em>Image obtained through Nancy Guthrie’s unsubscribed Google Nest camera and released by the FBI.</em></figcaption></figure></div><p>While the “discovery” of footage from this home camera by Google engineers is obviously of great value to the Guthrie family and law enforcement agents searching for Guthrie, it raises obvious yet serious questions about why Google, contrary to common understanding, was storing the video footage of unsubscribed users. A former NSA data researcher and CEO of a cybersecurity firm, Patrick Johnson, told CBS: “There's kind of this old saying that data is never deleted, it's just renamed.”</p><p><strong>It is rather remarkable that</strong><span> Americans are being led, more or less willingly, into a state-corporate, Panopticon-like domestic surveillance state with relatively little resistance, though the widespread reaction to Amazon’s Ring ad is encouraging. Much of that muted reaction may be due to a lack of realization about the severity of the evolving privacy threat. Beyond that, privacy and other core rights can seem abstract and less of a priority than more material concerns, at least until they are gone.</span></p><p>It is always the case that there are benefits available from relinquishing core civil liberties: allowing infringements on free speech may reduce false claims and hateful ideas; allowing searches and seizures without warrants will likely help the police catch more criminals, and do so more quickly; giving up privacy may, in fact, enhance security.</p><p>But the core premise of the West generally, and the U.S. in particular, is that those trade-offs are never worthwhile. Americans still all learn and are taught to admire the iconic (if not apocryphal) 1775 words of Patrick Henry, which came to define the core ethos of the Revolutionary War and American Founding: “Give me liberty or give me death.” It is hard to express in more definitive terms on which side of that liberty-versus-security trade-off the U.S. was intended to fall.</p><p><span>These recent events emerge in a broader context of this new Silicon Valley-driven destruction of individual privacy. Palantir’s federal contracts for domestic surveillance and domestic data management continue to expand rapidly, with more and more intrusive data about Americans consolidated under the control of this </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JypG_o7HWT0" rel="">one sinister corporation</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Facial recognition technology — now fully in use for an array of purposes from Customs and Border Protection at airports to ICE’s patrolling of American streets — means that fully tracking one’s movements in public spaces is easier than ever, and is becoming easier by the day. It was only three years ago that we </span><a href="https://x.com/systemupdate_/status/1712828792320778590" rel="">interviewed</a><span> </span><em>New York Times</em><span> reporter Kashmir Hill about her new book, “Your Face Belongs to Us.” The warnings she issued about the dangers of this proliferating technology have not only come true with startling speed but also appear already beyond what even she envisioned.</span></p><p>On top of all this are advances in AI. Its effects on privacy cannot yet be quantified, but they will not be good. I have tried most AI programs simply to remain abreast of how they function.</p><p>After just a few weeks, I had to stop my use of Google’s Gemini because it was compiling not just segregated data about me, but also a wide array of information to form what could reasonably be described as a dossier on my life, including information I had not wittingly provided it. It would answer questions I asked it with creepy, unrelated references to the far-too-complete picture it had managed to create of many aspects of my life (at one point, it commented, somewhat judgmentally or out of feigned “concern,” about the late hours I was keeping while working, a topic I never raised).</p><p>Many of these unnerving developments have happened without much public notice because we are often distracted by what appear to be more immediate and proximate events in the news cycle. The lack of sufficient attention to these privacy dangers over the last couple of years, including at times from me, should not obscure how consequential they are.</p><p><span>All of this is particularly remarkable, and particularly disconcerting, since we are barely more than a decade removed from the disclosures about mass domestic surveillance enabled by the courageous whistleblower Edward Snowden. Although most of our reporting focused on state surveillance, one of </span><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jun/06/us-tech-giants-nsa-data" rel="">the first stories</a><span> featured the joint state-corporate spying framework built in conjunction with the U.S. security state and Silicon Valley giants.</span></p><p><span>The Snowden stories sparked years of anger, attempts at reform, changes in diplomatic relations, and even genuine (albeit forced) </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/19/technology/end-to-end-encryption.html" rel="">improvements</a><span> in Big Tech’s user privacy. But the calculation of the U.S. security state and Big Tech was that at some point, attention to privacy concerns would disperse and then virtually evaporate, enabling the state-corporate surveillance state to march on without much notice or resistance. At least as of now, the calculation seems to have been vindicated.</span></p></div></article></div><div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div><div><h3>Ready for more?</h3></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reversed engineered game Starflight (1986) (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/s-macke/starflight-reverse</link>
            <guid>47022943</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 11:37:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/s-macke/starflight-reverse">https://github.com/s-macke/starflight-reverse</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47022943">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Starflight-Reverse</h2><a id="user-content-starflight-reverse" aria-label="Permalink: Starflight-Reverse" href="#starflight-reverse"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What is Starflight?</h2><a id="user-content-what-is-starflight" aria-label="Permalink: What is Starflight?" href="#what-is-starflight"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/s-macke/starflight-reverse/blob/master/images/starflight-game.gif"><img src="https://github.com/s-macke/starflight-reverse/raw/master/images/starflight-game.gif" alt="Starflight 1 for the PC" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Back in the 80ths, an unknown company called Binary Systems published the game Starflight. The game puts the player in the role of a starship captain sent to explore the galaxy. There is no set path, allowing players to switch freely between mining, ship-to-ship combat, and alien diplomacy. The broader plot of the game emerges slowly, as the player discovers that an ancient race of beings is causing stars to flare and destroy all living creatures.
The game has been widely praised by both contemporary and modern critics, and is one of the earliest instances of a sandbox game.  The game influenced the design of numerous other games for decades after its release.</p>
<p dir="auto">To find out more about the game check the following links:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starflight" rel="nofollow">Wikipedia</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.filfre.net/2014/10/starflight/" rel="nofollow">The Digital Antiquarian</a></li>
<li><a href="http://starflt.com/" rel="nofollow">Starflight Resource Pages</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/s-macke/starflight-reverse/tree/master/webarchive">Technical Articles Saved from Oblivion</a></li>
<li><a href="http://crpgaddict.blogspot.de/search/label/Starflight" rel="nofollow">Review of Starflight 1</a></li>
<li><a href="http://crpgaddict.blogspot.de/search/label/Starflight%20II" rel="nofollow">Review of Starflight 2</a></li>
<li>Other fan sites or projects <a href="http://bravearmy.com/starflight/" rel="nofollow">1</a> <a href="http://otherelectricities.com/neckdeep/starflight.html" rel="nofollow">2</a> <a href="https://www.dosgameclub.com/starflight/" rel="nofollow">3</a> <a href="http://blakessanctum.x10.mx/Games/Starflight/" rel="nofollow">4</a> <a href="https://www.starflight3.com/" rel="nofollow">5</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">You can buy the game at <a href="https://www.gog.com/game/starflight_1_2" rel="nofollow">GoG</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What is this project about?</h2><a id="user-content-what-is-this-project-about" aria-label="Permalink: What is this project about?" href="#what-is-this-project-about"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The first time I heard about the game I wanted to play it. However, I was too young and could not speak English. 20 later I tried again and it was a very pleasant experience. The exploration is fun, the storyline is epic and ends with a surprise, that is one of the best I have experienced. Sure, the game hasn't aged well, but you can feel the devotion of the developers to the game. There’s an art aspect to this game as well as a craftman’s attention to detail.</p>
<p dir="auto">As much as playing this truly amazing game is fun, so is reverse engineering this game. You follow in the footsteps of the developers and experience their thought processes as if it were the year 1985 again.
For this game expect the unexpected. Normally when you reverse engineer such an old game you have to receive ten thousands of lines of pure assembler code, which you can analyze with the usual tools such as IDA Pro. But not this time. Actually for this game you can throw the usual tools away. They are useless. You are on your own. The reason is that Starflight was written in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forth_(programming_language)" rel="nofollow">Forth</a>, a language I barely knew about.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Forth</h2><a id="user-content-forth" aria-label="Permalink: Forth" href="#forth"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Forth is the language with the ultimate minimalism regarding syntax. There is no more syntax than the space between "words". You can write a Forth reader and interpreter basically in a few lines of code.</p>
<p dir="auto">In a modern language you write something like</p>

<p dir="auto">to print the result of 2+3. In Forth however it looks like this.</p>

<p dir="auto">Forth is a stack machine, with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reverse_Polish_notation" rel="nofollow">reverse Polish notation</a>. The interpretation is as follows</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>push 2 on top of the stack</li>
<li>push 3 on top of the stack</li>
<li>pop the last two stack entries and add them together. Push the result back on top of the stack.</li>
<li>pop the top value from the stack and print it</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">The syntax is simple and the interpreter is simple. "2", "3", "+" and "." are just called "words". There is no syntactic distinction between data and code. Certainly a language that lived up to the limitations of the early home computers.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Disassembly description</h2><a id="user-content-disassembly-description" aria-label="Permalink: Disassembly description" href="#disassembly-description"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">When you dissect the executable STARFLT.COM it reveals some fantastic internals</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>The compiled code retains the structure of the Forth source code. No optimization by the compiler. A word in the source code are two bytes in the compiled code.</li>
<li>The x86-assembly code consumes less than 5% of the size of the exectuable</li>
<li>More than 90% of the executable are actually 16-Bit pointers.</li>
<li>2000 of around 6000 word names, which you would call debugging symbols nowadays, are still in the code, but encrypted. This enables us to reverse engineer a high portion of the original source code.</li>
<li>The Forth interpreter (not compiler) is still part of the executable and can be enabled</li>
<li>The executable is slow. Besides of some assembler optimized routines, the code wastes at least 50% of the CPU cycles just by jumping around in the code.</li>
<li>The executable makes heavily use of code overlays, which makes the decoding much more complicated</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The main building block</h2><a id="user-content-the-main-building-block" aria-label="Permalink: The main building block" href="#the-main-building-block"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">As explained above Forth is a stack machine. As coding mechanic it uses <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Threaded_code#Indirect_threading" rel="nofollow">indirect threading</a>, a very space efficient method to store your compiled code. Threaded code has a form that essentially consists entirely of calls to subroutines. Indirect threading uses pointers to locations that in turn point to machine code.</p>
<p dir="auto">Let's say your instruction pointer points to the address 0x1000 and contains the 16-Bit value Read16(0x1000)=0x0f72.</p>

<p dir="auto">The value 0x0f72 is the coded equivalent of the Forth word '+'. Remember the description above. The word '+' pops the last two stack entries, adds them together and pushes the result back on top of the stack. According to indirect threading this 16-Bit value 0x0f72 is a pointer to a location that in turn points to machine code. When you read the memory content Read16(0x0f72) you get the pointer to 0x0f74. And indeed, when you look at this memory location and disassemble it, you receive the following</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="0x0f72: dw 0x0f74
0x0f74: pop    ax
0x0f75: pop    bx
0x0f76: add    ax, bx
0x0f78: push   ax
0x0f79: lodsw
0x0f7a: mov    bx, ax
0x0f7c: jmp    word ptr [bx]"><pre><span>0x0f72</span><span>: dw </span><span>0x0f74</span>
<span>0x0f74</span><span>: </span><span>pop</span><span>    </span><span>ax</span>
<span>0x0f75</span><span>: </span><span>pop</span><span>    </span><span>bx</span>
<span>0x0f76</span><span>: </span><span>add</span><span>    </span><span>ax</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>bx</span>
<span>0x0f78</span><span>: </span><span>push</span><span>   </span><span>ax</span>
<span>0x0f79</span><span>: </span><span>lodsw</span>
<span>0x0f7a</span><span>: </span><span>mov</span><span>    </span><span>bx</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>ax</span>
<span>0x0f7c</span><span>: </span><span>jmp</span><span>    word ptr </span><span>[</span><span>bx</span><span>]</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The first four instructions perform exactly the operations that the word "+" should perform. The last three assembler instructions starting from the "lodsw" increase the instruction pointer and jump to the next code.</p>
<p dir="auto">Let us go on. Now the instruction pointer points to 0x1002</p>

<p dir="auto">Reading the address 0x53a3 reveals</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="0x53a3: dw 0x1d29
0x53a5: dw 0x0001"><pre><span>0x53a3</span><span>: dw </span><span>0x1d29</span>
<span>0x53a5</span><span>: dw </span><span>0x0001</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">and the corresponding code</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="0x1d29: inc    bx
0x1d2a: inc    bx
0x1d2b: push   bx
0x1d2c: lodsw
0x1d2d: mov    bx,ax
0x1d2f: jmp    word ptr [bx]"><pre><span>0x1d29</span><span>: </span><span>inc</span><span>    </span><span>bx</span>
<span>0x1d2a</span><span>: </span><span>inc</span><span>    </span><span>bx</span>
<span>0x1d2b</span><span>: </span><span>push</span><span>   </span><span>bx</span>
<span>0x1d2c</span><span>: </span><span>lodsw</span>
<span>0x1d2d</span><span>: </span><span>mov</span><span>    </span><span>bx</span><span>,</span><span>ax</span>
<span>0x1d2f</span><span>: </span><span>jmp</span><span>    word ptr </span><span>[</span><span>bx</span><span>]</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">At this time the register bx contains the word address 0x53a3. So this code just pushes the address 0x53a5 on top of the stack.  What we have done is to provide the program a pointer to a variable. The variable has the content 0x0001. The Forth word '@' would pop the address from the stack, reads its content and pushes it back on the stack.</p>
<p dir="auto">So far I could identify 6256 words that contain either code or data.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>3711 are words, which execute other words. I guess you can call them functions.</li>
<li>906 16-Bit variables or data arrays. In very rare cases (~20) the data array contains x86 machine code</li>
<li>356 data structures which define content of the tables stored on disk (see below)</li>
<li>346 data structures which define content of the instance tree data structure (see below)</li>
<li>278 words contain x86 machine code</li>
<li>235 16-Bit constants</li>
<li>127 switch-case expressions</li>
<li>105 words contain data structures to define the code overlays</li>
<li>the other words are of different type</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">And that's actually all you need to know about the code structure.
As you can see this can be a space efficient encoding, but speedwise it is a catastrophe. Every few machine code instructions you have to jump to a different code block.</p>
<p dir="auto">The equivalent of indirect threading in C would look like this.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="uint16_t instruction_pointer = start_of_program_pointer;
    
void Call(uint16_t word_adress)
{
    // the first two byte of the word's address contain 
    // the address of the corresponding code, which must be executed for this word
    uint16_t code_address = Read16(word_address);

    switch(code_address)
    {
        .
        .
        .
        case 0x0f74: // word '+'
            Push16(Pop16() + Pop16());
            break;
        .
        .
        .
    }
}

void Run()
{
    while(1)
    {
        uint16_t word_address = Read16(instruction_pointer);
        instruction_pointer += 2;
        Call(word_address);
    }
}
"><pre><span>uint16_t</span> <span>instruction_pointer</span> <span>=</span> <span>start_of_program_pointer</span>;
    
<span>void</span> <span>Call</span>(<span>uint16_t</span> <span>word_adress</span>)
{
    <span>// the first two byte of the word's address contain </span>
    <span>// the address of the corresponding code, which must be executed for this word</span>
    <span>uint16_t</span> <span>code_address</span> <span>=</span> <span>Read16</span>(<span>word_address</span>);

    <span>switch</span>(<span>code_address</span>)
    {
        .
        .
        .
        <span>case</span> <span>0x0f74</span>: <span>// word '+'</span>
            <span>Push16</span>(<span>Pop16</span>() <span>+</span> <span>Pop16</span>());
            <span>break</span>;
        .
        .
        .
    }
}

<span>void</span> <span>Run</span>()
{
    <span>while</span>(<span>1</span>)
    {
        <span>uint16_t</span> <span>word_address</span> <span>=</span> <span>Read16</span>(<span>instruction_pointer</span>);
        <span>instruction_pointer</span> <span>+=</span> <span>2</span>;
        <span>Call</span>(<span>word_address</span>);
    }
}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The code executed for a specific word has access to 5 major variables (16-Bit)</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>instruction pointer (register si): This points inside of a more complex function ("word") in Forth. It points to the address of the Forth "word" in memory which must be executed next. The instruction pointer can be altered by the word's code for branch and loop control.</li>
<li>stack pointer (register sp): This is a stack machine and therefore needs a stack pointer. Push will put an item on the stack. Pop retrieves an item from the top of the stack.</li>
<li>call stack pointer (register bp): contains the return addresses of the functions. Also used to temporarily store items.</li>
<li>word address (register bx): The first 2 byte contain the address to the x86 machine code of this word. Afterwards, there can be optional data such as constants, variables and arrays. In the above example for '+' it contains the machine code itself.</li>
<li>code address (register ip): The x86-machine code which must be executed</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Translation</h2><a id="user-content-translation" aria-label="Permalink: Translation" href="#translation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The disassember transpiles the FORTH code into C-style code.. Most of the transpiled code compiles. To understand what the program does take a look at the following table. It takes the "bytecode" (which are mainly 16-Bit pointers) as input and transforms it into C.</p>
<p dir="auto">Forth code:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content=": .C ( -- )
\ Display context stack contents.
  CR CDEPTH IF CXSP @ 3 + END-CX
               DO I 1.5@ .DRJ -3 +LOOP
            ELSE .&quot; MT STK&quot;
            THEN CR ;
  EXIT"><pre>: .C <span>( -- )</span>
<span>\ Display context stack contents.</span>
  CR CDEPTH <span>IF</span> CXSP @ <span>3</span> + END-CX
               <span>DO</span> <span>I</span> 1.5@ .DRJ <span>-3</span> <span>+LOOP</span>
            <span>ELSE</span> ." <span>MT STK"</span>
            <span>THEN</span> CR ;
  EXIT</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Transformation:</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>16-Bit Pointers</th>
<th>FORTH</th>
<th>C</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>: .C ( -- )</td>
<td><code>void DrawC() { </code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><code> unsigned short int i, imax;</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x0642</td>
<td>CR</td>
<td><code> Exec("CR");</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x75d5</td>
<td>CDEPTH</td>
<td><code> CDEPTH();</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x15fa 0x0020</td>
<td>IF</td>
<td><code> if (Pop() != 0) {</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x54ae</td>
<td>CXSP</td>
<td><code>    Push(Read16(pp_CXSP) + 3);</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0xbae</td>
<td>@</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x3b73</td>
<td>3</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x0f72</td>
<td>+</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x4ffd</td>
<td>END-CX</td>
<td><code>    Push(Read16(cc_END_dash_CX));</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x15b8</td>
<td>DO</td>
<td><code>    i = Pop();</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><code>    imax = Pop();</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><code>    do {</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x50e0</td>
<td>I</td>
<td><code>        Push(i);</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x4995</td>
<td>1.5@</td>
<td><code>        _1_dot_5_at_();</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x81d5</td>
<td>.DRJ</td>
<td><code>        DrawDRJ();</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x175d 0xfffd</td>
<td>-3</td>
<td><code>        Push(-3);</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x155c 0xffff</td>
<td>+LOOP</td>
<td><code>    int step = Pop();</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><code>    i += step;</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><code>    if (((step&gt;=0) &amp;&amp; (i&gt;=imax)) || ((step&lt;0) &amp;&amp; (i&lt;=imax))) break;</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><code>    } while(1);</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x1660 0x000b</td>
<td>ELSE</td>
<td><code>  } else {</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x1bdc</td>
<td>" MT STK"</td>
<td><code>    PRINT("MT STK", 6);</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x06</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x4d</td>
<td>'M'</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x54</td>
<td>'T'</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x20</td>
<td>' '</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x53</td>
<td>'S'</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x54</td>
<td>'T'</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x4b</td>
<td>'K'</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>THEN</td>
<td><code>  }</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x0642</td>
<td>CR</td>
<td><code>  Exec("CR");</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0x1690</td>
<td>EXIT</td>
<td><code>}</code></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Files</h2><a id="user-content-files" aria-label="Permalink: Files" href="#files"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The game comes in 3 Files</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>STARA.COM and STARB.COM: Both contain the game data and the game executable stored in a its own directory structure.</li>
<li>STARFLT.COM: This file is a DOS executable and contains the initialitzation routines, general Forth routines and routines to read and write of the on-disk data structures in STARA.COM and STARB.COM.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Directory in STARA.COM and STARB.COM</h2><a id="user-content-directory-in-staracom-and-starbcom" aria-label="Permalink: Directory in STARA.COM and STARB.COM" href="#directory-in-staracom-and-starbcom"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Content of STARA.com</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>entry</th>
<th>size</th>
<th>description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>DIRECTORY</td>
<td>4096</td>
<td>contains directory of STARA and STARB</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ELO-CPIC</td>
<td>4816</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GAZ-CPIC</td>
<td>3120</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MEC-CPIC</td>
<td>2848</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MYS-CPIC</td>
<td>6064</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NOM-CPIC</td>
<td>1136</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SPE-CPIC</td>
<td>1888</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>THR-CPIC</td>
<td>2480</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VEL-CPIC</td>
<td>4672</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VPR-CPIC</td>
<td>1248</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MIN-CPIC</td>
<td>2096</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SPLASH</td>
<td>16384</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MED-PIC</td>
<td>2048</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PHAZES</td>
<td>6144</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HUM-PIC</td>
<td>480</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VEL-PIC</td>
<td>432</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>THR-PIC</td>
<td>272</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ELO-PIC</td>
<td>608</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AND-PIC</td>
<td>640</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SAVE</td>
<td>124000</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MUSIC</td>
<td>4960</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EARTH</td>
<td>1152</td>
<td>Map of the planet earth</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GALAXY</td>
<td>6304</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CREDITS</td>
<td>16384</td>
<td>picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COP-CPIC</td>
<td>2928</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FONTS</td>
<td>768</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CGA</td>
<td>3600</td>
<td>Machine Code routines for the CGA graphics card</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>EGA</td>
<td>3600</td>
<td>Machine Code routines for the EGA graphics card</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto">Content of STARB.COM</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>entry</th>
<th>size</th>
<th>description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>DIRECTORY</td>
<td>4096</td>
<td>contains directory of STARA and STARB</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>INSTANCE</td>
<td>150528</td>
<td>Tree structure with most of the content of the game</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BOX</td>
<td>1024</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BANK-TRANS</td>
<td>144</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CREWMEMBER</td>
<td>128</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VESSEL</td>
<td>1936</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ELEMENT</td>
<td>544</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ARTIFACT</td>
<td>1584</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PLANET</td>
<td>1360</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SPECIMEN</td>
<td>448</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BIO-DATA</td>
<td>448</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TPORT-PIC</td>
<td>2416</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BPORT-PIC</td>
<td>3984</td>
<td>Picture</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ANALYZE-TEXT</td>
<td>3200</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BUTTONS</td>
<td>944</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICON1:1</td>
<td>912</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICON1:2</td>
<td>912</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICON1:4</td>
<td>912</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICON-NAME</td>
<td>736</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DPART-OV</td>
<td>1552</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>REGIONS</td>
<td>176</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CREATURE</td>
<td>17024</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CHKFLIGHT-OV</td>
<td>960</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FRACT-OV</td>
<td>4640</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ICONP-OV</td>
<td>832</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SITE-OV</td>
<td>1888</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HYPERMSG-OV</td>
<td>4112</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GPOLY</td>
<td>368</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FACET</td>
<td>288</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VERTEX</td>
<td>416</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BLT-OV</td>
<td>864</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MISC-OV</td>
<td>1440</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BANK-OV</td>
<td>1520</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ASSCREW-OV</td>
<td>2800</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PERSONNEL-OV</td>
<td>4192</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SHIPGRPH-OV</td>
<td>2112</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CONFIG-OV</td>
<td>3072</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TDEPOT-OV</td>
<td>4800</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PORTMENU-OV</td>
<td>3120</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VITA-OV</td>
<td>3552</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HP-OV</td>
<td>4832</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LP-OV</td>
<td>5280</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SENT-OV</td>
<td>4784</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>TV-OV</td>
<td>3472</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COMM-OV</td>
<td>7232</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COMMSPEC-OV</td>
<td>2864</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SEED-OV</td>
<td>2400</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LISTICONS</td>
<td>720</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MOVE-OV</td>
<td>3808</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ENGINEER</td>
<td>2320</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DOCTOR</td>
<td>1280</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ORBIT-OV</td>
<td>6640</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CAPTAIN</td>
<td>5952</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SCIENCE</td>
<td>3952</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>NAVIGATR</td>
<td>880</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SHIPBUTTONS</td>
<td>1984</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MAP-OV</td>
<td>4160</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HYPER-OV</td>
<td>7168</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ANALYZE-OV</td>
<td>2560</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LAUNCH-OV</td>
<td>1360</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>FLUX-EFFECT</td>
<td>464</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OP-OV</td>
<td>4400</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ITEMS-OV</td>
<td>6016</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LSYSICON</td>
<td>752</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MSYSICON</td>
<td>448</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SSYSICON</td>
<td>176</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>BEHAV-OV</td>
<td>5360</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CMAP</td>
<td>1008</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>INSTALL</td>
<td>800</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HEAL-OV</td>
<td>1232</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>REPAIR-OV</td>
<td>1696</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GAME-OV</td>
<td>5920</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PLSET-OV</td>
<td>2400</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>MAPS-OV</td>
<td>2240</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>VES-BLT</td>
<td>4528</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>STORM-OV</td>
<td>1232</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COMPOUNDS</td>
<td>176</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>IT-OV</td>
<td>1936</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>COMBAT-OV</td>
<td>6192</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DAMAGE-OV</td>
<td>2752</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LAND-OV</td>
<td>1088</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PSTATS</td>
<td>64</td>
<td>Table</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>STP-OV</td>
<td>1440</td>
<td>Code Overlay</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Put the files of the original Starflight game into the folders <code>starflt1-in</code> and <code>starflt2-in</code> and run <code>make</code>. You should get two executables (<code>disasOV1</code> and <code>disasOV2</code>), which produces the content in the folders <code>starflt1-out</code> and <code>starflt2-out</code>. The generated output is part of this repository.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Fixed Windows Native Development (729 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://marler8997.github.io/blog/fixed-windows/</link>
            <guid>47022891</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 11:25:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://marler8997.github.io/blog/fixed-windows/">https://marler8997.github.io/blog/fixed-windows/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=47022891">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Imagine you’re maintaining a native project. You use Visual Studio for building on Windows, so you do the responsible thing and list it as a dependency</p><blockquote><p>Build Requirements: Install Visual Studio</p></blockquote><p>If you’re lucky enough not to know this yet, I envy you.  Unfortunately, at this point even Boromir knows…</p><figure><img src="https://marler8997.github.io/SimplyInstallVs.png">
<figcaption>Well put Boromir</figcaption></figure><p>What you may not realize is, you’ve actually signed up to be unpaid tech support for Microsoft’s “Visual Studio Installer”. You might notice GitHub Issues becoming less about your code and more about broken builds, specifically on Windows. You find yourself explaining to a contributor that they didn’t check the “Desktop development with C++” workload, but specifically the v143 build tools and the 10.0.22621.0 SDK. No, not that one, the <em>other</em> one. You spend less time on your project because you’re too busy being a human-powered dependency resolver for a 50GB IDE.</p><p>Saying “Install Visual Studio” is like handing contributors a choose-your-own-adventure book riddled with bad endings, some of which don’t let you go back. I’ve had to re-image my entire OS more than once over the years.</p><h3>Why is this tragedy unique to Windows?</h3><p>On <strong>Linux</strong>, the toolchain is usually just a package manager command away. On the other hand, “Visual Studio” is thousands of components. It’s so vast that Microsoft distributes it with a sophisticated GUI installer where you navigate a maze of checkboxes, hunting for which “Workloads” or “Individual Components” contain the actual compiler. Select the wrong one and you might lose hours installing something you don’t need. Miss one, like “Windows 10 SDK (10.0.17763.0)” or “Spectre-mitigated libs,” and your build fails three hours later with a cryptic error like <code>MSB8101</code>. And heaven help you if you need to downgrade to an older version of the build tools for a legacy project.</p><p>The Visual Studio ecosystem is built on a legacy of ‘all-in-one’ monoliths. It conflates the editor, the compiler, and the SDK into a single, tangled web. When we list ‘Visual Studio’ as a dependency, we’re failing to distinguish between the tool we use to write code and the environment required to compile it.</p><p>The pain compounds quickly:</p><ul><li><strong>Hours-long waits</strong>: You spend an afternoon watching a progress bar download 15GB just to get a 50MB compiler.</li><li><strong>Zero transparency</strong>: You have no idea which files were installed or where they went. Your registry is littered with cruft and background update services are permanent residents of your Task Manager.</li><li><strong>No version control</strong>: You can’t check your compiler into Git. If a teammate has a slightly different Build Tools version, your builds can silently diverge.</li><li><strong>The “ghost” environment</strong>: Uninstalling is never truly clean. Moving to a new machine means repeating the entire GUI dance, praying you checked the same boxes.</li></ul><p>Even after installation, compiling a single C file from the command line requires finding the Developer Command Prompt. Under the hood, this shortcut invokes <code>vcvarsall.bat</code>, a fragile batch script that globally mutates your environment variables just to locate where the compiler is hiding this week.</p><p>Ultimately, you end up with build instructions that look like a legal disclaimer:</p><blockquote><p>“Works on my machine with VS 17.4.2 (Build 33027.167) and SDK 10.0.22621.0. If you have 17.5, please see Issue #412. If you are on ARM64, godspeed.”</p></blockquote><p>On Windows, this has become the “cost of doing business”. We tell users to wait three hours for a 20GB install just so they can compile a 5MB executable. <strong>It’s become an active deterrent to native development</strong>.</p><h2>A new way</h2><p>I’m not interested in being a human debugger for someone else’s installer. I want the MSVC toolchain to behave like a modern dependency: versioned, isolated, declarative.</p><p>I spent a few weeks building an open source tool to make things better. It’s called <a href="https://github.com/marler8997/msvcup" target="_blank">msvcup</a>. It’s a small CLI program. On good network/hardware, it can install the toolchain/SDK in a few minutes, including everything to cross-compile to/from ARM. Each version of the toolchain/SDK gets its own isolated directory. It’s idempotent and fast enough to invoke every time you build. Let’s try it out.</p><p>Create <code>hello.c</code> and <code>build.bat</code>:</p><pre><code><span>#include</span> <span>&lt;stdio.h&gt;</span>
<span>int</span> <span>main</span>() { <span>printf</span>(<span>"Hello, World\n"</span>)<span>;</span> }
</code></pre>
<pre><code>@setlocal

@if not exist msvcup.exe (
    echo msvcup.exe: installing...
    curl -L -o msvcup.zip https://github.com/marler8997/msvcup/releases/download/v2026_02_07/msvcup-x86_64-windows.zip
    tar xf msvcup.zip
    del msvcup.zip
) else (
    echo msvcup.exe: already installed
)
@if not exist msvcup.exe exit /b 1

set MSVC=msvc-14.44.17.14
set SDK=sdk-10.0.22621.7

msvcup install --lock-file msvcup.lock --manifest-update-off %MSVC% %SDK%
@if %errorlevel% neq 0 (exit /b %errorlevel%)

msvcup autoenv --target-cpu x64 --out-dir autoenv %MSVC% %SDK%
@if %errorlevel% neq 0 (exit /b %errorlevel%)

.\autoenv\cl hello.c
</code></pre><p>And we’re done.</p><p>Believe it or not, this <code>build.bat</code> script replaces the need to “Install Visual Studio”. This script should run on any Windows system since Windows 10 (assuming it has curl/tar which have been shipped since 2018). It installs the MSVC toolchain, the Windows SDK and then compiles our program.</p><p>For my fellow Windows developers, go ahead and take a moment. Visual Studio can’t hurt you anymore. The <code>build.bat</code> above isn’t just a helper script; it’s a declaration of independence from the Visual Studio Installer. Our dependencies are fully specified, making builds reproducible across machines. And when those dependencies are installed, they won’t pollute your registry or lock you into a single global version.</p><p>Also note that after the first run, the <code>msvcup</code> commands take milliseconds, meaning we can just leave these commands in our build script and now we have a fully self-contained script that can build our project on virtually any modern Windows machine.</p><h2>How?</h2><p>msvcup is inspired by a <a href="https://gist.github.com/mmozeiko/7f3162ec2988e81e56d5c4e22cde9977" target="_blank">small Python script</a> written by Mārtiņš Možeiko. The key insight is that Microsoft publishes JSON manifests describing every component in Visual Studio, the same manifests the official installer uses. msvcup parses these manifests, identifies just the packages needed for compilation (the compiler, linker, headers, and libraries), and downloads them directly from Microsoft’s CDN. Everything lands in versioned directories under <code>C:\msvcup\</code>. For details on lock files, cross-compilation, and other features, see the <a href="https://github.com/marler8997/msvcup" target="_blank">msvcup README.md</a>.</p><p>The astute will also notice that our <code>build.bat</code> script never sources any batch files to set up the “Developer Environment”. The script contains two msvcup commands. The first installs the toolchain/SDK, and like a normal installation, it includes “vcvars” scripts to set up a developer environment. Instead, our <code>build.bat</code> leverages the <code>msvcup autoenv</code> command to create an “Automatic Environment”. This creates a directory that contains wrapper executables to set the environment variables on your behalf before forwarding to the underlying tools. It even includes a <code>toolchain.cmake</code> file which will point your CMake projects to these tools, allowing you to build your CMake projects outside a special environment.</p><p>At <a href="https://tuple.app/" target="_blank">Tuple</a> (a pair-programming app), I integrated msvcup into our build system and CI, which allowed us to remove the requirement for the user/CI to pre-install Visual Studio. Tuple compiles hundreds of C/C++ projects including WebRTC. This enabled both x86_64 and ARM builds on the CI as well as keeping the CI and everyone on the same toolchain/SDK.</p><p>The benefits:</p><ul><li><strong>Everything installs into a versioned directory.</strong> No problem installing versions side-by-side. Easy to remove or reinstall if something goes wrong.</li><li><strong>Cross-compilation enabled out of the box.</strong> msvcup currently always downloads the tools for all supported cross-targets, so you don’t have to do any work looking for all the components you need to cross-compile.</li><li><strong>Lock file support.</strong> A self-contained list of all the payloads/URLs. Everyone uses the same packages, and if Microsoft changes something upstream, you’ll know.</li><li><strong>Blazing fast.</strong> The <code>install</code> and <code>autoenv</code> commands are idempotent and complete in milliseconds when there’s no work to do.</li></ul><p>No more “it works on my machine because I have the 2019 Build Tools installed.” No more registry-diving to find where <code>cl.exe</code> is hiding this week. With msvcup, your environment is defined by your code, portable across machines, and ready to compile in milliseconds.</p><h3>Limitations</h3><p>msvcup focuses on the core compilation toolchain. If you need the full Visual Studio IDE, MSBuild-based project systems, or components like the C++/CLI compiler, you’ll still need the official installer. For most native development workflows, though, it covers what you actually need.</p><h2>A Real-World Example: Building Raylib</h2><p>Let’s try this on a real project. Here’s a script that builds <a href="https://github.com/raysan5/raylib" target="_blank">raylib</a> from scratch on a clean Windows system. In this case, we’ll just use the SDK without the autoenv:</p><pre><code>@setlocal

set TARGET_CPU=x64

@if not exist msvcup.exe (
    echo msvcup.exe: installing...
    curl -L -o msvcup.zip https://github.com/marler8997/msvcup/releases/download/v2026_02_07/msvcup-x86_64-windows.zip
    tar xf msvcup.zip
    del msvcup.zip
)

set MSVC=msvc-14.44.17.14
set SDK=sdk-10.0.22621.7

msvcup.exe install --lock-file msvcup.lock --manifest-update-off %MSVC% %SDK%
@if %errorlevel% neq 0 (exit /b %errorlevel%)

@if not exist raylib (
    git clone https://github.com/raysan5/raylib -b 5.5
)

call C:\msvcup\%MSVC%\vcvars-%TARGET_CPU%.bat
call C:\msvcup\%SDK%\vcvars-%TARGET_CPU%.bat

cmd /c "cd raylib\projects\scripts &amp;&amp; build-windows"
@if %errorlevel% neq 0 (exit /b %errorlevel%)

@echo build success: game exe at:
@echo .\raylib\projects\scripts\builds\windows-msvc\game.exe
</code></pre><p>No Visual Studio installation. No GUI. No prayer. Just a script that does exactly what it says.</p><p>P.S. <a href="https://marler8997.github.io/build-zig/windows.html" target="_blank">Here</a> is a page that shows how to use msvcup to build LLVM and Zig from scratch on Windows.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>