<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 22:00:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Dillo 3.1.0 released after 9 years (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dillo-browser.github.io/latest.html</link>
            <guid>40260035</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 20:22:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dillo-browser.github.io/latest.html">https://dillo-browser.github.io/latest.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40260035">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p><i>Released on 2024-05-04</i></p><h2>Summary of changes</h2>

<p>Since the last release 3.0.5 from 2015 a lot of things have happened to the
Dillo project.

<a href="https://dillo-browser.github.io/img/commits-author.png">
<img alt="A plot of number of commits over time colored by authors. There is a missing gap from mid 2002 to mid 2008. And from 2017 to end of 2023 there is almost no commits." src="https://dillo-browser.github.io/img/commits-author.png">
</a>

Here is a short timeline to put things into perspective:

</p><ul>
  <li>On 2016, the main developer of the layout engine, Sebastian Geerken,
    <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/dillo/c/Kpuh3d6nNL8/">passed away</a>.</li>
  <li>On 2017, the development stopped.</li>
  <li>On 2019, the last email from Jorge Arellano Cid, the lead
    developer of Dillo,
    <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/dillo/c/UQ1nWyMa3yo/m/07qhu9KqAgAJ">was
      recorded by the mailing list</a>.</li>
  <li>On 2022, the domain <code>dillo.org</code> <a href="https://dillo-browser.github.io/dillo.org.html">was
      lost</a>.</li>
  <li>On 2024, an
    <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38847613">attempt to
      resurrect the project</a> began by Rodrigo
    Arias Mallo.</li>
</ul>

<p>This release contains a lot of changes accumulated from the 2015-2017 period,
as well as fixes and small features introduced in 2024. Here is a summary:
</p><ul>
  <li>Add support for floating HTML elements, which involved a big redesign.</li>
  <li>Add support for OpenSSL, LibreSSL and mbed TLS for HTTPS, which is now
    enabled by default.</li>
  <li>Add a CI pipeline to build Dillo on Ubuntu, MacOS, FreeBSD and
    Windows (via cygwin).</li>
  <li>Add automatic HTML rendering tests.</li>
  <li>Improve and extend the Dillo manual.</li>
</ul>

<p>In memory of Sebastian Geerken.</p>

<h2>Download</h2><p>

To download the release, get it from the
<a href="https://github.com/dillo-browser/dillo/releases/tag/v3.1.0">GitHub
releases</a>.

</p><h2>Detailed changes</h2><p>
This is the list of changes from the ChangeLog of this release:
</p><ul>
  <li>Patches by Sebastian Geerken:
    <ul>
      <li>Floating elements.</li>
      <li>Redesign of widget sizes ("GROWS").</li>
      <li>Applied CSS attribute 'width' to all elements, 'height' is now also
        supported.</li>
      <li>Suport for 'min-width', 'max-width', 'min-height' and 'max-height'.</li>
      <li>Suport for 'display: inline-block'.</li>
      <li>&lt;BUTTON&gt;'s are now inline.</li>
      <li>Image aspect ratio is preserved when one dimension is specified by a
        percentage value.</li>
      <li>New dillorc options 'adjust_min_width' and 'adjust_table_min_width'.</li>
      <li>Make building of test/ files more robust.</li>
      <li>Work on collapsing spaces: more cases supported.</li>
      <li>Fix crash that's possible searching for text while page still being
        built.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Patches by corvid:
    <ul>
      <li>HTML5 character references.</li>
      <li>Give images lower priority when requesting resources (responsiveness).</li>
      <li>Reuse of connections for HTTP (disable w/ http_persistent_conns in
        dillorc).</li>
      <li>Abort failed queries.</li>
      <li>HTTP Strict Transport Security (disable with http_strict_transport_security
        preference in dillorc).</li>
      <li>Fix bug when closing popup using window manager (bug introduced in
        3.0.3).</li>
      <li>Block mixed content.</li>
      <li>Improve cookies date recognition.</li>
      <li>Use <a href="https://tls.mbed.org/">Mbed TLS</a></li>
      <li>Iterate through the IP addrs for a host when trying to connect().</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Patches by Jeremy Henty:
    <ul>
      <li>Doxygen fixes.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Patches by corvid and Benjamin Johnson:
    <ul>
      <li>Move HTTPS from dpi into the browser, enable SNI, check more locations
        for CA bundles and add --with-ca-certs-file and --with-ca-certs-dir to
        configure, some improvement to security warning popups, etc.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Patches by Johannes Hofmann:
    <ul>
      <li>Fix bookmarks DPI crash.</li>
      <li>Fix OSX compilation issue with xembed.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Patches by Rodrigo Arias Mallo &lt;rodarima@gmail.com&gt;:
    <ul>
      <li>Fix DuckDuckGo search links</li>
      <li>Add scroll_step option to control the mouse wheel vertical step</li>
      <li>Add support for OpenSSL 1.1, OpenSSL 3, mbedTLS 2 and mbedTLS 3</li>
      <li>Replace configure flag --enable-ssl to --enable-tls</li>
      <li>Enable TLS support by default for https.</li>
      <li>Add automatic rendering tests (only enabled with --enable-html-tests).</li>
      <li>Fix width calculation when using 'min-width' and 'max-width'.</li>
      <li>Update website URL to https://dillo-browser.github.io/</li>
      <li>Add ui_tab_height option to control the tab height. Default value increased
        from 16 to 20 pixels to improve usability.</li>
      <li>Switch tabs using the mouse wheel by default. Use the new option
        scroll_switches_tabs to disable the behavior.</li>
      <li>Fix OpenSSL handling of unexpected EOF without close notify alert.</li>
      <li>Expand home tilde '~' in the file plugin.</li>
      <li>Ignore width attribute with relative values for td and th elements.</li>
      <li>Enable Doxygen for C files and use Awesome Doxygen theme.</li>
      <li>Fix DPIs extension (.dpi.exe) in Windows systems via Cygwin.</li>
      <li>Add support for the &lt;main&gt; HTML tag.</li>
      <li>Fix W3C validator and remove broken WDG validator.</li>
      <li>Simplify bookmark DPI page style and improve readability.</li>
      <li>Improve the Dillo manual available from the help button.</li>
      <li>Improve detection of XHTML documents.</li>
      <li>Install desktop file with Dillo icon.</li>
      <li>Add version in user manual and about:splash.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Patches by Mark Walker:
    <ul>
      <li>Add http_force_https mode.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Does the American Diabetes Association work for patients or companies? (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/global/commentisfree/2024/may/02/american-diabetes-association-lawsuit</link>
            <guid>40259196</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 17:52:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/global/commentisfree/2024/may/02/american-diabetes-association-lawsuit">https://www.theguardian.com/global/commentisfree/2024/may/02/american-diabetes-association-lawsuit</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40259196">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p><span>A</span> cloak of silence has descended over the recent whistleblower lawsuit <a href="https://fingfx.thomsonreuters.com/gfx/legaldocs/myvmgloeovr/Hanna%20v%20ADA%20complaint%2011-15.pdf" data-link-name="in body link">claiming</a> that the American Diabetes Association, or ADA, accepted corporate money in return for recommending recipes that threatened the health of people with diabetes.</p><figure id="5390fdfd-4665-4d83-8f5d-ac34830da37a" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:1,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Study: ‘gamechanger’ diabetes drugs cost up to 400 times more than needed&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;5390fdfd-4665-4d83-8f5d-ac34830da37a&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2024/mar/28/drug-companies-diabetes-drugs-medicines-ozempic-trulicity&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0,&quot;design&quot;:10}}" config="{&quot;renderingTarget&quot;:&quot;Web&quot;,&quot;darkModeAvailable&quot;:false,&quot;assetOrigin&quot;:&quot;https://assets.guim.co.uk/&quot;}"></gu-island></figure><p>Elizabeth Hanna, the ex-ADA chief nutritionist who alleged that her former employer fired her over her refusal to endorse Splenda-filled salads, has quietly settled her case. In a statement to the Guardian, Hanna’s attorney, Lauren Davis, said that “the matter has been resolved”. No details were provided either by Davis or by a spokesperson for the ADA, which declined to comment.</p><p>For Hanna, accepting a settlement from the ADA was no doubt a simpler and less stressful and risky alternative to a trial, but for me and the country’s other 38 million people with diabetes, it is a letdown. What a great opportunity a trial would have been to expose the inner workings of the ADA, the patient advocacy organization up to its eyeballs in big-business funding.</p><p>I recently <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2024/apr/18/splenda-diabetes-lawsuit" data-link-name="in body link">wrote</a> about Hanna’s lawsuit as part of our series <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/series/death-by-diabetes--america-s-preventable-epidemic" data-link-name="in body link">Death by Diabetes: America’s Preventable Epidemic</a>. My view is that diabetes is an urgent national scandal. Over 100 million Americans have diabetes or prediabetes, and 100,000 die from the condition annually. In addition, every year hundreds of thousands of people with diabetes have limbs amputated or suffer blindness or kidney disease. Diabetes costs our country $400bn annually to treat.</p><p>And although type-2 diabetes is often reversible through a low-carbohydrate diet, the ADA and the pharmaceutical industry <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2024/apr/17/ada-american-diabetes-association-big-pharma" data-link-name="in body link">don’t seem</a> very interested in acknowledging that. Instead, they promote a laundry list of corporate deals and pharmaceutical treatments that have failed to stem the disease’s lethal and expensive impact on American life.</p><p>Hanna’s complaint, filed last year in a New Jersey court, alleged a litany of wrongdoings by one of the country’s most powerful patient advocacy organizations. Hanna said that ADA higher-ups pressured her to approve recipes that included generous helpings of the artificial sweetener Splenda, despite research published in the ADA’s own scientific journal <a href="https://diabetesjournals.org/care/article/46/9/1681/153434/Artificial-Sweeteners-and-Risk-of-Type-2-Diabetes" data-link-name="in body link">finding</a> that artificial sweeteners may raise consumers’ risk of type-2 diabetes.</p><p>Hanna further alleged that the pressure was the result of a $1m contribution made to the ADA by Heartland Food Products Group. Finally, she said the ADA was a revolving door of nutrition directors, with seven leaders coming and going over the past four years – largely because, she asserted, her predecessors “were either terminated by the ADA when they refused to comply with the ADA’s unethical and unlawful practices or were constructively terminated by the ADA by the abusive and hostile work environment they faced for refusing to comply”.</p><p>The ADA rejects the allegations in the lawsuit. The Heartland Food Products Group, which was not named in the lawsuit, has also said that it rejects any allegations of wrongdoing, and indicated it would continue working with the ADA. “Heartland will continue to support the ADA and honorably provide recipes and educational information to help people successfully reduce sugar levels and live happier and healthier lives,” Heartland said in a statement.</p><p>By settling, the ADA manages to avoid the discovery process, and the potentially embarrassing revelations that might have come with it.</p><p>Hanna’s lawyers appear to have grasped the implications of her lawsuit, and originally suggested her quest could take on heroic dimensions. “Hanna’s story could be the next movie that Americans need to see to understand what is going on behind closed doors between major for-profit corporations and the not-for-profit health sector,” they wrote in their legal complaint.</p><p>Although she chose to settle with the ADA, in reality Hanna has already performed a giant public service. Her <a href="https://fingfx.thomsonreuters.com/gfx/legaldocs/myvmgloeovr/Hanna%20v%20ADA%20complaint%2011-15.pdf" data-link-name="in body link">legal complaint</a> is a public document open for the ADA’s board of directors, clinicians across the US and the world, and members of Congress to read. Her meticulous account depicts the world’s most important diabetes patient advocacy organization as a cynical fund-raising machine, anxious to please its corporate overlords at the expense of the millions of people with diabetes it is supposed to be trying to help.</p><p>“The defendant’s conduct shows that they were party to a scheme to defraud the American people by approving and endorsing recipes submitted by Splenda to be lauded by the ADA as a healthy choice for people with diabetes, when the ADA knew that those recipes were contrary to the ADA’s guidelines and well-established and emerging scientific principles,” the complaint reads.</p><p>In case you’re curious, the ADA and Splenda appear to be still at it. As I write this, the ADA’s Diabetes Food Hub web page still <a href="https://www.diabetesfoodhub.org/search-results.html?banners=5&amp;keywords=splenda&amp;per_page=32" data-link-name="in body link">features</a> no fewer than 203 recipes – some marked “sponsored”, some not – that include Splenda, whose parent company’s $1m contribution has brought to light the utter insanity of our diabetes epidemic.</p><p>Isn’t it long overdue for the ADA’s board to act?</p><ul>
 <li><p>Neil Barsky, a former Wall Street Journal reporter and investment manager, is the founder of the Marshall Project</p></li>
</ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Spotify getting into enterprise IT tools (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2024/04/30/spotifys-getting-serious-about-its-enterprise-and-dev-tools-business-play/</link>
            <guid>40258315</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 15:22:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/04/30/spotifys-getting-serious-about-its-enterprise-and-dev-tools-business-play/">https://techcrunch.com/2024/04/30/spotifys-getting-serious-about-its-enterprise-and-dev-tools-business-play/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40258315">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<p id="speakable-summary"><span>You know that</span> mildly jarring experience whenever that well-known celebrity shows up in an entirely different context — e.g. a <a href="https://www.billboard.com/music/music-news/musicians-horror-movies-best-roles-8539942/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">musician making a horror flick cameo</a>; an <a href="https://www.si.com/extra-mustard/2015/05/28/entourage-tom-brady-manning-brothers-jerry-ferrara-cameo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NFL player rearing their head</a> in a comedy series; or a <a href="https://www.mirror.co.uk/money/city-news/kevin-bacon-helps-telecoms-giant-2998642" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hollywood movie icon selling mobile phone plans</a> on TV? Well, it’s starting to feel like that with Spotify’s foray into the enterprise and developer tooling space — nothing wrong with it per se, but it makes you flinch just a little due to its divergence from the norm.</p>
<p>What we’re talking about is <a href="https://backstage.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-mrf-link="https://backstage.io/">Backstage</a>, a platform and framework Spotify introduced internally in 2016 to bring order to its developer infrastructure. Backstage powers customizable “developer portals” that combine tooling, apps, data, services, APIs and documents in a single interface. Want to monitor Kubernetes, check your CI/CD status or track security incidents? Backstage to the rescue.</p>
<p>Lots of companies construct their own internal systems to help developers work more efficiently. And lots of companies release such systems to the public via an open source license to spur wider adoption, <a href="https://engineering.atspotify.com/2020/03/what-the-heck-is-backstage-anyway/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">as Spotify did with Backstage in 2020</a>. But it’s highly unusual for a consumer technology company to actively monetize this side of its business, which <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/15/spotifys-plan-to-monetize-its-open-source-backstage-developer-project/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spotify has been doing since 2022</a>.</p>
<p>Now, Spotify is leaning even further into this play with the launch of a new suite of products and services designed to make Backstage the de facto developer portal platform for the software development industry.</p>

<h2>Modular</h2>
<p>Backstage is built on a modular, plug-in based architecture that allows engineers to layer-up their developer portal to meet their own needs. There is already a thriving <a href="https://backstage.io/plugins/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">marketplace for Backstage plug-ins</a>, some developed by Spotify itself and some by the wider community, including developers from Red Hat and Amazon Web Services (AWS) — AWS, for example, <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/backstage-plugins-for-aws/tree/main/plugins/ecs#readme" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has developed a plug-in</a> to make data from Amazon Elastic Container Service (<a href="https://aws.amazon.com/ecs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ECS</a>) available in Backstage.</p>
<p>Since late 2022, Spotify has been selling a handful of premium plug-ins as a subscription, such as <a href="https://backstage.spotify.com/marketplace/spotify/plugin/insights/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Backstage Insights</a>, which serves up data related to Backstage usage across an organization, including which plugins they’re engaging with most.</p>
<div id="attachment_2698286"><p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2698286" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/EngagementPlugin-e1714476021804.png" alt="Backstage Insights plugin" width="817" height="485" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/EngagementPlugin-e1714476021804.png 817w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/EngagementPlugin-e1714476021804.png?resize=150,89 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/EngagementPlugin-e1714476021804.png?resize=300,178 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/EngagementPlugin-e1714476021804.png?resize=768,456 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/EngagementPlugin-e1714476021804.png?resize=680,404 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/EngagementPlugin-e1714476021804.png?resize=50,30 50w" sizes="(max-width: 817px) 100vw, 817px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-2698286">Backstage Insights plug-in. <strong>Image Credits:</strong> Spotify</p></div>
<p>The open source Backstage project <a href="https://github.com/backstage/backstage/blob/master/ADOPTERS.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener">has been adopted internally</a> by some of the world’s most well-known companies, including LinkedIn, Twilio, American Airlines, Unity, Splunk, Ikea, HP and more than 3,000 organizations. But as with just about any open source project, the main issue with Backstage is the complexity involved in getting set up — lots of integrations, configurations and figuring out how it all glues together.</p>
<p>Thus, Spotify is now introducing an out-the-box version of the open source project called Spotify Portal, available in beta from today, which is pitched as a “full-featured, low-/no-code internal developer portal (IDP)” built atop Backstage.</p>
<div id="attachment_2698332"><p><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2698332" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Portal-is-ready-for-you-e1714481557503.png" alt="Spotify Portal" width="1024" height="622" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Portal-is-ready-for-you-e1714481557503.png 1370w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Portal-is-ready-for-you-e1714481557503.png?resize=150,91 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Portal-is-ready-for-you-e1714481557503.png?resize=300,182 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Portal-is-ready-for-you-e1714481557503.png?resize=768,466 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Portal-is-ready-for-you-e1714481557503.png?resize=680,413 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Portal-is-ready-for-you-e1714481557503.png?resize=1200,729 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Portal-is-ready-for-you-e1714481557503.png?resize=50,30 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-2698332">Spotify Portal. <strong>Image Credits:</strong> Spotify</p></div>
<p>Spotify Portal ships with quick-start tools for connecting all their internal services and libraries, replete with setup wizard for installing Portal and connecting it with a company’s GitHub and cloud provider.</p>
<p>“When you set up your IDP, typically you need to ingest a lot of software into that, because the point of the IDP is to capture your full software catalogue and map that to the user base, and there’s potentially a lot of integrations involved in,” Tyson Singer, Spotify’s head of technology and platforms, explained to TechCrunch. “And so with Spotify Portal for Backstage, we’ve basically given folks a no-code way to do that.”</p>
<div id="attachment_2698333"><p><img decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2698333" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png" alt="Spotify Portal: Ingesting software catalog" width="1024" height="587" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png 2981w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png?resize=150,86 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png?resize=300,172 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png?resize=768,440 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png?resize=680,390 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png?resize=1536,881 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png?resize=2048,1174 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png?resize=1200,688 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Software-Catalog.png?resize=50,29 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-2698333">Spotify Portal: Ingesting software catalog. <strong>Image Credits:</strong> Spotify</p></div>
<h2>Getting SaaS-y?</h2>
<p>On the surface, this seems like some sort of SaaS play, similar to how a commercial company might offer a fully managed, hosted version of a popular open source product. But that isn’t quite what’s happening here — there is no hosted element to this, though that might change in the future. It’s what Singer calls “Backstage in a box,” one which is deployed within the customer’s own ecosystem either on-premises, or in their own cloud.</p>
<p>“It’s the customer who manages it,” Singer said. “What’s important from our perspective is that we’ve really focused on both reducing the startup time and the maintenance time. So that means not only is the setup and the onboarding ‘no-code,’ it’s also the maintenance where we’re reducing code. That really makes it quite easy to manage in your own particular context.”</p>
<p>However, in a follow-up question, a Spotify spokesperson clarified that Spotify Portal for Backstage is its “first step towards a managed product,” which means that it more than likely will be offered more like a SaaS service in the future. “We’ve seen a growing appetite for a more managed product that would allow us to share our expertise more directly with companies, and we want to be able to offer more in support of that need,” the spokesperson said. “Portal is our first step on that journey, but in the future, we’re going to expand our offerings as managed.”</p>
<p>In addition, Spotify is adding various enterprise support and services to the mix, which it says it has already been providing since last summer but hasn’t disclosed this until now. This includes one-on-one tech support from dedicated Backstage personnel at Spotify, and includes service-level agreements (SLAs), security reviews and incident notifications. And for those wanting to get up-and-running with Backstage in the first instance, Spotify is also offering consulting services.</p>
<h2>Spooling up</h2>
<p>In essence, Spotify is now catering to three broad category of users: the core open source project for those with the resources and technical nous to self-deploy everything; the “hybrid adopters,” which is what Spotify calls those that have some of the necessary skills but need some support along the way; and the businesses that need something a bit more oven-baked — which is where Spotify Portal enters the fray.</p>
<p>Similar to the pricing structure for its existing plugin subscriptions, which are charged based on “individual customer parameters” such as usage and capacity, the new Portal and enterprise services don’t come with up-front costs.</p>
<p>“For pricing, we are referring customers back to our sales organization,” Singer said. “It’s custom pricing.”</p>
<p>Given this transition to an enterprise-focused developer tools company, Spotify is also having to staff-up accordingly, though Singer wouldn’t share how many people it would be hiring or allocating to these new support roles.</p>
<p>“We are changing how we go forward with both our sales organization and support,” Singer said. “So we’re shifting more focus towards how can we support customers in their initial journey and then also, once they’ve got it set up, their ongoing journey because we do want to be able to support them to get to value as quickly as possible.”</p>
<p>All this, it seems, is just the tip of the iceberg as far as Spotify’s developer tooling shift is concerned. The company is adding new features to some of its existing premium plug-ins, and it’s adding more plug-ins to the mix, too. One of these is the “data experience” plug-in, which makes it easier to add individual data entities to a software catalog — this includes built-in “ingestors” to scoop metadata from external data platforms, and make this available across Backstage.</p>
<p>Last year, Spotify <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/04/spotify-introduces-new-product-to-help-software-development-teams-with-with-a-b-testing/">also teased a totally separate&nbsp;product</a> for software development teams called <a href="https://confidence.spotify.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Confidence</a>, which is like an A/B experimentation platform based on one of its own internal tools. For now, that remains a beta product, but Singer says that it’s “all systems go” as it readies things for prime-time in the future.</p>
<p>“We are super happy with the feedback that we’ve been getting from our [Confidence] beta customers so far,” Singer said. “We built out an experimentation platform that is broad and deep, covering a tremendous amount of use cases covering everything from your typical A/B testing on a user surface, to being able to do that across all of our ML [machine learning] use cases. And I think that really sets it aside, as more and more companies are using ML in the same sorts of ways that we are to optimize things.<span>“</span></p>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[In praise of idleness – Bertrand Russell (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://libcom.org/article/praise-idleness-bertrand-russell</link>
            <guid>40257677</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 13:51:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://libcom.org/article/praise-idleness-bertrand-russell">https://libcom.org/article/praise-idleness-bertrand-russell</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40257677">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Like most of my generation, I was brought up on the saying: 'Satan finds some mischief for idle hands to do.' Being a highly virtuous child, I believed all that I was told, and acquired a conscience which has kept me working hard down to the present moment. But although my conscience has controlled my actions, my opinions have undergone a revolution. I think that there is far too much work done in the world, that immense harm is caused by the belief that work is virtuous, and that what needs to be preached in modern industrial countries is quite different from what always has been preached. Everyone knows the story of the traveler in Naples who saw twelve beggars lying in the sun (it was before the days of Mussolini), and offered a lira to the laziest of them. Eleven of them jumped up to claim it, so he gave it to the twelfth. this traveler was on the right lines. But in countries which do not enjoy Mediterranean sunshine idleness is more difficult, and a great public propaganda will be required to inaugurate it. I hope that, after reading the following pages, the leaders of the YMCA will start a campaign to induce good young men to do nothing. If so, I shall not have lived in vain.</p>
<p>Before advancing my own arguments for laziness, I must dispose of one which I cannot accept. Whenever a person who already has enough to live on proposes to engage in some everyday kind of job, such as school-teaching or typing, he or she is told that such conduct takes the bread out of other people's mouths, and is therefore wicked. If this argument were valid, it would only be necessary for us all to be idle in order that we should all have our mouths full of bread. What people who say such things forget is that what a man earns he usually spends, and in spending he gives employment. As long as a man spends his income, he puts just as much bread into people's mouths in spending as he takes out of other people's mouths in earning. The real villain, from this point of view, is the man who saves. If he merely puts his savings in a stocking, like the proverbial French peasant, it is obvious that they do not give employment. If he invests his savings, the matter is less obvious, and different cases arise.</p>
<p>One of the commonest things to do with savings is to lend them to some Government. In view of the fact that the bulk of the public expenditure of most civilized Governments consists in payment for past wars or preparation for future wars, the man who lends his money to a Government is in the same position as the bad men in Shakespeare who hire murderers. The net result of the man's economical habits is to increase the armed forces of the State to which he lends his savings. Obviously it would be better if he spent the money, even if he spent it in drink or gambling.</p>
<p>But, I shall be told, the case is quite different when savings are invested in industrial enterprises. When such enterprises succeed, and produce something useful, this may be conceded. In these days, however, no one will deny that most enterprises fail. That means that a large amount of human labor, which might have been devoted to producing something that could be enjoyed, was expended on producing machines which, when produced, lay idle and did no good to anyone. The man who invests his savings in a concern that goes bankrupt is therefore injuring others as well as himself. If he spent his money, say, in giving parties for his friends, they (we may hope) would get pleasure, and so would all those upon whom he spent money, such as the butcher, the baker, and the bootlegger. But if he spends it (let us say) upon laying down rails for surface card in some place where surface cars turn out not to be wanted, he has diverted a mass of labor into channels where it gives pleasure to no one. Nevertheless, when he becomes poor through failure of his investment he will be regarded as a victim of undeserved misfortune, whereas the gay spendthrift, who has spent his money philanthropically, will be despised as a fool and a frivolous person.</p>
<p>All this is only preliminary. I want to say, in all seriousness, that a great deal of harm is being done in the modern world by belief in the virtuousness of work, and that the road to happiness and prosperity lies in an organized diminution of work.</p>
<p>First of all: what is work? Work is of two kinds: first, altering the position of matter at or near the earth's surface relatively to other such matter; second, telling other people to do so. The first kind is unpleasant and ill paid; the second is pleasant and highly paid. The second kind is capable of indefinite extension: there are not only those who give orders, but those who give advice as to what orders should be given. Usually two opposite kinds of advice are given simultaneously by two organized bodies of men; this is called politics. The skill required for this kind of work is not knowledge of the subjects as to which advice is given, but knowledge of the art of persuasive speaking and writing, i.e. of advertising.</p>
<p>Throughout Europe, though not in America, there is a third class of men, more respected than either of the classes of workers. There are men who, through ownership of land, are able to make others pay for the privilege of being allowed to exist and to work. These landowners are idle, and I might therefore be expected to praise them. Unfortunately, their idleness is only rendered possible by the industry of others; indeed their desire for comfortable idleness is historically the source of the whole gospel of work. The last thing they have ever wished is that others should follow their example.</p>
<p>From the beginning of civilization until the Industrial Revolution, a man could, as a rule, produce by hard work little more than was required for the subsistence of himself and his family, although his wife worked at least as hard as he did, and his children added their labor as soon as they were old enough to do so. The small surplus above bare necessaries was not left to those who produced it, but was appropriated by warriors and priests. In times of famine there was no surplus; the warriors and priests, however, still secured as much as at other times, with the result that many of the workers died of hunger. This system persisted in Russia until 1917 [1], and still persists in the East; in England, in spite of the Industrial Revolution, it remained in full force throughout the Napoleonic wars, and until a hundred years ago, when the new class of manufacturers acquired power. In America, the system came to an end with the Revolution, except in the South, where it persisted until the Civil War. A system which lasted so long and ended so recently has naturally left a profound impress upon men's thoughts and opinions. Much that we take for granted about the desirability of work is derived from this system, and, being pre-industrial, is not adapted to the modern world. Modern technique has made it possible for leisure, within limits, to be not the prerogative of small privileged classes, but a right evenly distributed throughout the community. The morality of work is the morality of slaves, and the modern world has no need of slavery.</p>
<p>It is obvious that, in primitive communities, peasants, left to themselves, would not have parted with the slender surplus upon which the warriors and priests subsisted, but would have either produced less or consumed more. At first, sheer force compelled them to produce and part with the surplus. Gradually, however, it was found possible to induce many of them to accept an ethic according to which it was their duty to work hard, although part of their work went to support others in idleness. By this means the amount of compulsion required was lessened, and the expenses of government were diminished. To this day, 99 per cent of British wage-earners would be genuinely shocked if it were proposed that the King should not have a larger income than a working man. The conception of duty, speaking historically, has been a means used by the holders of power to induce others to live for the interests of their masters rather than for their own. Of course the holders of power conceal this fact from themselves by managing to believe that their interests are identical with the larger interests of humanity. Sometimes this is true; Athenian slave-owners, for instance, employed part of their leisure in making a permanent contribution to civilization which would have been impossible under a just economic system. Leisure is essential to civilization, and in former times leisure for the few was only rendered possible by the labors of the many. But their labors were valuable, not because work is good, but because leisure is good. And with modern technique it would be possible to distribute leisure justly without injury to civilization.</p>
<p>Modern technique has made it possible to diminish enormously the amount of labor required to secure the necessaries of life for everyone. This was made obvious during the war. At that time all the men in the armed forces, and all the men and women engaged in the production of munitions, all the men and women engaged in spying, war propaganda, or Government offices connected with the war, were withdrawn from productive occupations. In spite of this, the general level of well-being among unskilled wage-earners on the side of the Allies was higher than before or since. The significance of this fact was concealed by finance: borrowing made it appear as if the future was nourishing the present. But that, of course, would have been impossible; a man cannot eat a loaf of bread that does not yet exist. The war showed conclusively that, by the scientific organization of production, it is possible to keep modern populations in fair comfort on a small part of the working capacity of the modern world. If, at the end of the war, the scientific organization, which had been created in order to liberate men for fighting and munition work, had been preserved, and the hours of the week had been cut down to four, all would have been well. Instead of that the old chaos was restored, those whose work was demanded were made to work long hours, and the rest were left to starve as unemployed. Why? Because work is a duty, and a man should not receive wages in proportion to what he has produced, but in proportion to his virtue as exemplified by his industry.</p>
<p>This is the morality of the Slave State, applied in circumstances totally unlike those in which it arose. No wonder the result has been disastrous. Let us take an illustration. Suppose that, at a given moment, a certain number of people are engaged in the manufacture of pins. They make as many pins as the world needs, working (say) eight hours a day. Someone makes an invention by which the same number of men can make twice as many pins: pins are already so cheap that hardly any more will be bought at a lower price. In a sensible world, everybody concerned in the manufacturing of pins would take to working four hours instead of eight, and everything else would go on as before. But in the actual world this would be thought demoralizing. The men still work eight hours, there are too many pins, some employers go bankrupt, and half the men previously concerned in making pins are thrown out of work. There is, in the end, just as much leisure as on the other plan, but half the men are totally idle while half are still overworked. In this way, it is insured that the unavoidable leisure shall cause misery all round instead of being a universal source of happiness. Can anything more insane be imagined?</p>
<p>The idea that the poor should have leisure has always been shocking to the rich. In England, in the early nineteenth century, fifteen hours was the ordinary day's work for a man; children sometimes did as much, and very commonly did twelve hours a day. When meddlesome busybodies suggested that perhaps these hours were rather long, they were told that work kept adults from drink and children from mischief. When I was a child, shortly after urban working men had acquired the vote, certain public holidays were established by law, to the great indignation of the upper classes. I remember hearing an old Duchess say: 'What do the poor want with holidays? They ought to work.' People nowadays are less frank, but the sentiment persists, and is the source of much of our economic confusion.</p>
<p>Let us, for a moment, consider the ethics of work frankly, without superstition. Every human being, of necessity, consumes, in the course of his life, a certain amount of the produce of human labor. Assuming, as we may, that labor is on the whole disagreeable, it is unjust that a man should consume more than he produces. Of course he may provide services rather than commodities, like a medical man, for example; but he should provide something in return for his board and lodging. to this extent, the duty of work must be admitted, but to this extent only.</p>
<p>I shall not dwell upon the fact that, in all modern societies outside the USSR, many people escape even this minimum amount of work, namely all those who inherit money and all those who marry money. I do not think the fact that these people are allowed to be idle is nearly so harmful as the fact that wage-earners are expected to overwork or starve.</p>
<p>If the ordinary wage-earner worked four hours a day, there would be enough for everybody and no unemployment -- assuming a certain very moderate amount of sensible organization. This idea shocks the well-to-do, because they are convinced that the poor would not know how to use so much leisure. In America men often work long hours even when they are well off; such men, naturally, are indignant at the idea of leisure for wage-earners, except as the grim punishment of unemployment; in fact, they dislike leisure even for their sons. Oddly enough, while they wish their sons to work so hard as to have no time to be civilized, they do not mind their wives and daughters having no work at all. the snobbish admiration of uselessness, which, in an aristocratic society, extends to both sexes, is, under a plutocracy, confined to women; this, however, does not make it any more in agreement with common sense.</p>
<p>The wise use of leisure, it must be conceded, is a product of civilization and education. A man who has worked long hours all his life will become bored if he becomes suddenly idle. But without a considerable amount of leisure a man is cut off from many of the best things. There is no longer any reason why the bulk of the population should suffer this deprivation; only a foolish asceticism, usually vicarious, makes us continue to insist on work in excessive quantities now that the need no longer exists.</p>
<p>In the new creed which controls the government of Russia, while there is much that is very different from the traditional teaching of the West, there are some things that are quite unchanged. The attitude of the governing classes, and especially of those who conduct educational propaganda, on the subject of the dignity of labor, is almost exactly that which the governing classes of the world have always preached to what were called the 'honest poor'. Industry, sobriety, willingness to work long hours for distant advantages, even submissiveness to authority, all these reappear; moreover authority still represents the will of the Ruler of the Universe, Who, however, is now called by a new name, Dialectical Materialism.</p>
<p>The victory of the proletariat in Russia has some points in common with the victory of the feminists in some other countries. For ages, men had conceded the superior saintliness of women, and had consoled women for their inferiority by maintaining that saintliness is more desirable than power. At last the feminists decided that they would have both, since the pioneers among them believed all that the men had told them about the desirability of virtue, but not what they had told them about the worthlessness of political power. A similar thing has happened in Russia as regards manual work. For ages, the rich and their sycophants have written in praise of 'honest toil', have praised the simple life, have professed a religion which teaches that the poor are much more likely to go to heaven than the rich, and in general have tried to make manual workers believe that there is some special nobility about altering the position of matter in space, just as men tried to make women believe that they derived some special nobility from their sexual enslavement. In Russia, all this teaching about the excellence of manual work has been taken seriously, with the result that the manual worker is more honored than anyone else. What are, in essence, revivalist appeals are made, but not for the old purposes: they are made to secure shock workers for special tasks. Manual work is the ideal which is held before the young, and is the basis of all ethical teaching.</p>
<p>For the present, possibly, this is all to the good. A large country, full of natural resources, awaits development, and has has to be developed with very little use of credit. In these circumstances, hard work is necessary, and is likely to bring a great reward. But what will happen when the point has been reached where everybody could be comfortable without working long hours?</p>
<p>In the West, we have various ways of dealing with this problem. We have no attempt at economic justice, so that a large proportion of the total produce goes to a small minority of the population, many of whom do no work at all. Owing to the absence of any central control over production, we produce hosts of things that are not wanted. We keep a large percentage of the working population idle, because we can dispense with their labor by making the others overwork. When all these methods prove inadequate, we have a war: we cause a number of people to manufacture high explosives, and a number of others to explode them, as if we were children who had just discovered fireworks. By a combination of all these devices we manage, though with difficulty, to keep alive the notion that a great deal of severe manual work must be the lot of the average man.</p>
<p>In Russia, owing to more economic justice and central control over production, the problem will have to be differently solved. the rational solution would be, as soon as the necessaries and elementary comforts can be provided for all, to reduce the hours of labor gradually, allowing a popular vote to decide, at each stage, whether more leisure or more goods were to be preferred. But, having taught the supreme virtue of hard work, it is difficult to see how the authorities can aim at a paradise in which there will be much leisure and little work. It seems more likely that they will find continually fresh schemes, by which present leisure is to be sacrificed to future productivity. I read recently of an ingenious plan put forward by Russian engineers, for making the White Sea and the northern coasts of Siberia warm, by putting a dam across the Kara Sea. An admirable project, but liable to postpone proletarian comfort for a generation, while the nobility of toil is being displayed amid the ice-fields and snowstorms of the Arctic Ocean. This sort of thing, if it happens, will be the result of regarding the virtue of hard work as an end in itself, rather than as a means to a state of affairs in which it is no longer needed.</p>
<p>The fact is that moving matter about, while a certain amount of it is necessary to our existence, is emphatically not one of the ends of human life. If it were, we should have to consider every navvy superior to Shakespeare. We have been misled in this matter by two causes. One is the necessity of keeping the poor contented, which has led the rich, for thousands of years, to preach the dignity of labor, while taking care themselves to remain undignified in this respect. The other is the new pleasure in mechanism, which makes us delight in the astonishingly clever changes that we can produce on the earth's surface. Neither of these motives makes any great appeal to the actual worker. If you ask him what he thinks the best part of his life, he is not likely to say: 'I enjoy manual work because it makes me feel that I am fulfilling man's noblest task, and because I like to think how much man can transform his planet. It is true that my body demands periods of rest, which I have to fill in as best I may, but I am never so happy as when the morning comes and I can return to the toil from which my contentment springs.' I have never heard working men say this sort of thing. They consider work, as it should be considered, a necessary means to a livelihood, and it is from their leisure that they derive whatever happiness they may enjoy.</p>
<p>It will be said that, while a little leisure is pleasant, men would not know how to fill their days if they had only four hours of work out of the twenty-four. In so far as this is true in the modern world, it is a condemnation of our civilization; it would not have been true at any earlier period. There was formerly a capacity for light-heartedness and play which has been to some extent inhibited by the cult of efficiency. The modern man thinks that everything ought to be done for the sake of something else, and never for its own sake. Serious-minded persons, for example, are continually condemning the habit of going to the cinema, and telling us that it leads the young into crime. But all the work that goes to producing a cinema is respectable, because it is work, and because it brings a money profit. The notion that the desirable activities are those that bring a profit has made everything topsy-turvy. The butcher who provides you with meat and the baker who provides you with bread are praiseworthy, because they are making money; but when you enjoy the food they have provided, you are merely frivolous, unless you eat only to get strength for your work. Broadly speaking, it is held that getting money is good and spending money is bad. Seeing that they are two sides of one transaction, this is absurd; one might as well maintain that keys are good, but keyholes are bad. Whatever merit there may be in the production of goods must be entirely derivative from the advantage to be obtained by consuming them. The individual, in our society, works for profit; but the social purpose of his work lies in the consumption of what he produces. It is this divorce between the individual and the social purpose of production that makes it so difficult for men to think clearly in a world in which profit-making is the incentive to industry. We think too much of production, and too little of consumption. One result is that we attach too little importance to enjoyment and simple happiness, and that we do not judge production by the pleasure that it gives to the consumer.</p>
<p>When I suggest that working hours should be reduced to four, I am not meaning to imply that all the remaining time should necessarily be spent in pure frivolity. I mean that four hours' work a day should entitle a man to the necessities and elementary comforts of life, and that the rest of his time should be his to use as he might see fit. It is an essential part of any such social system that education should be carried further than it usually is at present, and should aim, in part, at providing tastes which would enable a man to use leisure intelligently. I am not thinking mainly of the sort of things that would be considered 'highbrow'. Peasant dances have died out except in remote rural areas, but the impulses which caused them to be cultivated must still exist in human nature. The pleasures of urban populations have become mainly passive: seeing cinemas, watching football matches, listening to the radio, and so on. This results from the fact that their active energies are fully taken up with work; if they had more leisure, they would again enjoy pleasures in which they took an active part.</p>
<p>In the past, there was a small leisure class and a larger working class. The leisure class enjoyed advantages for which there was no basis in social justice; this necessarily made it oppressive, limited its sympathies, and caused it to invent theories by which to justify its privileges. These facts greatly diminished its excellence, but in spite of this drawback it contributed nearly the whole of what we call civilization. It cultivated the arts and discovered the sciences; it wrote the books, invented the philosophies, and refined social relations. Even the liberation of the oppressed has usually been inaugurated from above. Without the leisure class, mankind would never have emerged from barbarism.</p>
<p>The method of a leisure class without duties was, however, extraordinarily wasteful. None of the members of the class had to be taught to be industrious, and the class as a whole was not exceptionally intelligent. The class might produce one Darwin, but against him had to be set tens of thousands of country gentlemen who never thought of anything more intelligent than fox-hunting and punishing poachers. At present, the universities are supposed to provide, in a more systematic way, what the leisure class provided accidentally and as a by-product. This is a great improvement, but it has certain drawbacks. University life is so different from life in the world at large that men who live in academic milieu tend to be unaware of the preoccupations and problems of ordinary men and women; moreover their ways of expressing themselves are usually such as to rob their opinions of the influence that they ought to have upon the general public. Another disadvantage is that in universities studies are organized, and the man who thinks of some original line of research is likely to be discouraged. Academic institutions, therefore, useful as they are, are not adequate guardians of the interests of civilization in a world where everyone outside their walls is too busy for unutilitarian pursuits.</p>
<p>In a world where no one is compelled to work more than four hours a day, every person possessed of scientific curiosity will be able to indulge it, and every painter will be able to paint without starving, however excellent his pictures may be. Young writers will not be obliged to draw attention to themselves by sensational pot-boilers, with a view to acquiring the economic independence needed for monumental works, for which, when the time at last comes, they will have lost the taste and capacity. Men who, in their professional work, have become interested in some phase of economics or government, will be able to develop their ideas without the academic detachment that makes the work of university economists often seem lacking in reality. Medical men will have the time to learn about the progress of medicine, teachers will not be exasperatedly struggling to teach by routine methods things which they learnt in their youth, which may, in the interval, have been proved to be untrue.</p>
<p>Above all, there will be happiness and joy of life, instead of frayed nerves, weariness, and dyspepsia. The work exacted will be enough to make leisure delightful, but not enough to produce exhaustion. Since men will not be tired in their spare time, they will not demand only such amusements as are passive and vapid. At least one per cent will probably devote the time not spent in professional work to pursuits of some public importance, and, since they will not depend upon these pursuits for their livelihood, their originality will be unhampered, and there will be no need to conform to the standards set by elderly pundits. But it is not only in these exceptional cases that the advantages of leisure will appear. Ordinary men and women, having the opportunity of a happy life, will become more kindly and less persecuting and less inclined to view others with suspicion. The taste for war will die out, partly for this reason, and partly because it will involve long and severe work for all. Good nature is, of all moral qualities, the one that the world needs most, and good nature is the result of ease and security, not of a life of arduous struggle. Modern methods of production have given us the possibility of ease and security for all; we have chosen, instead, to have overwork for some and starvation for others. Hitherto we have continued to be as energetic as we were before there were machines; in this we have been foolish, but there is no reason to go on being foolish forever.</p>
<p>[1] Since then, members of the Communist Party have succeeded to this privilege of the warriors and priests.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vulture shortage threatens Zoroastrian burial rites (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/world/article/2024/may/04/vulture-shortage-threatens-zoroastrian-burial-rites-india-iran-pakistan</link>
            <guid>40257064</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 12:13:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/article/2024/may/04/vulture-shortage-threatens-zoroastrian-burial-rites-india-iran-pakistan">https://www.theguardian.com/world/article/2024/may/04/vulture-shortage-threatens-zoroastrian-burial-rites-india-iran-pakistan</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40257064">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>Traditional Zoroastrian burial rites are becoming increasingly impossible to perform because of the precipitous decline of vultures in India, Iran and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/pakistan" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Pakistan</a>.</p><p>For millennia, Parsi communities have traditionally disposed of their dead in structures called <em>dakhma,</em> or “towers of silence”. These circular, elevated edifices are designed to prevent the soil, and the sacred elements of earth, fire and water, from being contaminated by corpses.</p><p>Bodies are placed on top of the towers, where they decompose, while vultures and other scavengers eat the flesh on the bones. After being bleached by the sun and wind for up to a year, the bones are collected in an ossuary pit at the centre of the tower. Lime hastens their gradual disintegration, and the remaining material, along with rainwater runoff, filters through coal and sand before it is washed out to sea.</p><p>“We are no longer able to fulfil our traditions,” Hoshang Kapadia, a Karachi resident in his 80s, said. “We’ve lost a way of life, our culture.”</p><p>Kapadia explained that the purpose behind the Parsi burial customs was to “take less and give more” to the world. “The whole idea is not to pollute the earth,” he said</p><figure id="a5ef5466-621d-4603-b779-9e88b27fe98e" data-spacefinder-role="supporting" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-2"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="An illustration of vultures gathering  on a Parsi ‘tower of silence’" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/d894136fc4c3ed22216553bdbce9daabf40fcb07/0_0_4781_3759/master/4781.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" width="445" height="349.87554904831626" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Vultures gather on a Parsi ‘tower of silence’, circa 1880. Offering one’s deceased body to the birds is regarded as the devout Zoroastrian’s ultimate act of charity.</span> Photograph: Sean Sexton/Getty Images</figcaption></figure><p>Karachi, which is built upon a river ecosystem on the western bank of the Indus River delta, is home to only 800 Parsis out of a population of 20 million people. The city has just two remaining towers of silence, both barely functional.</p><p>Another Karachi Parsi, Shirin, said: “The vulture’s mystical eye is believed to aid the soul’s cosmic transition, and offering one’s deceased body to the birds is regarded as the devout Zoroastrian’s ultimate act of charity.”</p><p>“The massive urbanisation and environmental changes in Karachi have led us to revisit our burial rites, as <em>dakhmas</em> were usually built on top of hills in locations distant from urban areas.</p><p>“Our tradition is dying. Our culture is dying in a time of increasing environmental change.”</p><p>Unlike many scavengers, vultures are classified as “obligate”. This means they do not opportunistically switch between predation and scavenging, as their mammalian counterparts do, but rely solely on locating and feeding on animal carcasses.</p><p>In recent decades, vultures have been <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/bird-conservation-international/article/recent-changes-in-populations-of-critically-endangered-gyps-vultures-in-india/668FE4AE0A18DA293CAF8870189B7DD0?utm_campaign=shareaholic&amp;utm_medium=copy_link&amp;utm_source=bookmark" data-link-name="in body link">dying in large numbers across the Indian subcontinent</a>, primarily due to inadvertent poisoning with the anti-inflammatory drug diclofenac, which is extensively administered to cattle in India and Pakistan.</p><p>When these cattle die, vultures feed on their carcasses and ingest the drug, which causes painful swelling, inflammation, and ultimately kidney failure and death in vultures. Research in 2007 estimated that about 97% of the three main vulture species in <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/india" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">India</a> and the surrounding region had disappeared.</p><figure id="aa3e421f-dc1e-4896-9dbb-ed9a4b09d8c1" data-spacefinder-role="supporting" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-3"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="An illustration showing vultures flying away from a funeral dakhma" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/05b2ad0a8ee31c270219ef010add6d46dfd2c656/0_0_4545_3156/master/4545.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" width="445" height="309.00330033003297" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Bombay, the Parsee Repository for their Dead, an illustration from 1722.</span> Photograph: CPA Media Pte Ltd/Alamy</figcaption></figure><p>The Parsi community in India is exploring captive vulture breeding and the use of “solar concentrators" to expedite the decomposition of bodies. As the solar concentrators only work in clear weather, some have been forced to opt for burial instead.</p><p>Kapadia said: “Parsis in Karachi [are forced to] opt for alternative methods of disposal, such as cremation or burial in designated Parsi cemeteries, as the two towers of silence in Karachi are barely functional”. He added that when vulture numbers declined at the towers of silence, some community members suggested creating a small captive group of vultures in an aviary to continue the traditional practice.</p><p>To prevent the extinction of vulture species, scientists have recommended banning the use of diclofenac in livestock, a move so far taken by India, Pakistan and Nepal. Captive-bred vultures have also been released into the wild in India in a bid to boost the threatened populations.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I don't want to fill out your contact form (203 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://adamjones.me/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/</link>
            <guid>40256868</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 11:36:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://adamjones.me/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/">https://adamjones.me/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40256868">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p><em>This article is written solely in my personal capacity, and does not represent the views of any organisations I am affiliated with.</em></p><div itemprop="articleBody"><p>Contact forms are almost always worse for users than just putting an email on your website. I explore why they’re terrible, why you’ve done it anyway, and what to do about it.</p>

<h3 id="your-contact-form-is-completely-broken">Your contact form is completely broken</h3>
<p>It’s remarkable how many contact forms are just straight-up broken. A WordPress upgrade here, a change to your CRM there, and your contact form silently breaks.</p>
<p>At time of writing, B&amp;Q’s contact form just plainly doesn’t work<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-1" id="user-content-fnref-1" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup>. I am fairly amazed that a retailer with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%26Q">revenues in the billions</a> doesn’t notice written queries have stopped coming in.</p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/bandq.png" alt="B&amp;Q Contact form, with an error box saying 'Sorry, something went wrong. Please try again.'"></p>
<p>(as a side note: your form should have <a href="https://wix-ux.com/when-life-gives-you-lemons-write-better-error-messages-46c5223e1a2f">better error messages</a>. The error above gives the user no way out, given that trying again would not help)</p>
<p>This is not an isolated incident. I’ve been stung by broken contact forms on all kinds of websites, from many other big and small organisations. <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38554522">AWS’s abuse contact form has been broken for months</a>. And here’s a particularly gnarly example from <a href="https://www.elastoplast.co.uk/pages/contact">Elastoplast</a>, one of the largest plaster brands in the UK:</p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/elastoplast.png" alt="Elastoplast contact form with a very long error message that looks like a stacktrace displayed, beginning 'CrmApi.Client.Common.HttpStatusException: Failed with status InternalServerError...'"></p>
<h3 id="your-contact-form-is-broken-for-some-users">Your contact form is broken for some users</h3>
<p>Axa, an insurer with almost <a href="https://www.axa-im.com/who-we-are/axa-im-numbers">a trillion euros of assets under management</a>, offers <a href="https://customer.axa.co.uk/contact/email-general/">a contact form</a> that looks like it’s time travelled from the early 2000s. Unfortunately, it doesn’t seem like that time has made it work better: it incorrectly rejects some valid emails<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-2" id="user-content-fnref-2" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup> and doesn’t show all the relevant Axa products.</p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/axa.png" alt="AXA's contact form, showing the email test+test@example.com being rejected, and listing only four insurance products in the dropdown"></p>
<p>Vodafone, a major UK mobile network, has <a href="https://www.vodafone.co.uk/webcenter/portal/myvodafone/lostandstolen">a form to report devices lost and stolen</a>. However, their site is frequently unavailable for maintenance overnight. I can’t imagine how frustrating having a phone stolen, only to try to report it and be presented with this:</p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/vodafone.png" alt="A page with Vodafone branding saying 'Sorry, we're down for schduled maintenance right now'"></p>
<p>Finally, a lot of contact forms do not meet basic web accessibility standards, making it hard for assistive technology users to properly complete them. For example, <a href="https://www.virginmedia.com/help/virgin-mobile-complaint">Virgin Mobile’s complaint page</a> is nearly unnavigable by keyboard due to hiding any kind of selection indicators.</p>
<h3 id="your-contact-form-takes-ages-to-fill-out">Your contact form takes ages to fill out</h3>
<p>I’m not sure how it’s been achieved, but the <a href="https://forms.charitycommission.gov.uk/Complaints-to-the-Charity-Commission-for-England-and-Wales/">UK’s Charity Commission’s complaints form</a> takes about 6-7 seconds to load every single page! It offers no indication of progress, and you have to get through 11 pages to complete it.</p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/cc-slow.png" alt="The Chrome network tab, showing a request taking 6.85 seconds"></p>
<p>At this rate, you spend <strong>75 seconds</strong> just waiting for pages in the form to load.</p>
<p>And that’s not including the time to answer the questions asked - or even processing some of them. Don’t worry, you’ll get to review each one carefully because none of them have <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Attributes/autocomplete">autocomplete attributes</a> set.</p>
<p>You’ll also have to read through all the options in this monstrosity of a dropdown - which is helpfully not grouped or sorted in any coherent way:</p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/cc-dropdown.png" alt="A dropdown with 28 options such as 'Trustee', 'Employee', 'Press/Media', 'Donor', 'Auditor', 'PHSO', 'Umbrella Organisation' and 'Other'"></p>
<p>(Additionally, this question doesn’t make sense to ask in the first place. The complaint is about a service by the Charity Commission, after answering ‘No’ to the question ‘Does your question or query relate to a specific registered charity?’)</p>
<h3 id="your-contact-form-asks-for-irrelevant-personal-information">Your contact form asks for irrelevant personal information</h3>
<p>National Grid has <a href="https://www.nationalgrid.co.uk/contact-us/contacting-national-grid-electricity-distribution/general-contact-enquiries">contact</a> and <a href="https://www.nationalgrid.co.uk/contact-us/contacting-national-grid-electricity-distribution/feedback-and-compliments">feedback</a> forms.<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-3" id="user-content-fnref-3" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">3</a></sup> I might want to give them some minor feedback like ‘hey this link on your site is broken’, however I then need to figure out whether I really want to provide all my personal details to do this - like my home address and phone number (or at least make up something that looks plausible).</p>
<p>I’ve also seen some complaints forms asking for more sensitive data, like date of birth or copies of ID documents. Sometimes this is despite them not holding this information in the first place, so they’re not comparing it to what they have on record as a security measure.<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-4" id="user-content-fnref-4" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">4</a></sup></p>
<p>You do need to collect some contact details, but do you really need <strong>three</strong> different contact methods to respond to some off-hand feedback? Other things you probably don’t actually need on a general contact form include <a href="https://writefulcopy.com/blog/why-title-should-not-be-a-required-field-on-online-forms">title</a>, job function, company size, and <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-56831212">landline</a> number.</p>
<p>This unnecessarily increases the risk of my data being stolen and used for identity fraud. For less trustworthy organisations, this also directly increases the chance I get spam - so I either don’t submit the form, or <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/CasualUK/comments/1b6up7p/does_anyone_actually_give_their_email_address/">make up data</a>.</p>
<h3 id="your-contact-form-is-less-useful-for-customers">Your contact form is less useful for customers</h3>
<p>Email allows customers to create drafts, schedule messages, and easily keep a record of what’s been said. It also often integrates into their workflows more easily, for example the ability to <a href="https://support.google.com/mail/answer/7622010">snooze emails</a> to chase up on them later.</p>
<p>Your form likely doesn’t have any of these features. In fact, even if it’s fully working users often don’t get any form of confirmation they can refer back to later, let alone a confirmation that contains all the details they submitted.</p>
<p>I’m not certain there is malicious intent behind it, but I have experienced several companies ‘accidentally’ losing form submissions, only to mysteriously find them again once I pull up copies of the form I saved a screenshot of. If you’re forcing your customers to do this, you’re doing it wrong.</p>
<h3 id="your-contact-form-is-wasting-your-resources">Your contact form is wasting your resources</h3>
<p>It takes time and energy to build and maintain a contact form properly. It almost always gets routed to an email behind the scenes (or a system that accepts email), so skip the middleman and put up the email address!</p>
<p>It also can mean that customers contacting you can’t remember what their original message was about. I’ve experienced getting a response from an organisation and then having to ask them what the original query was about - had this been an email in the first place this could have been avoided.</p>
<h3 id="your-contact-form-is-irritating-in-other-ways">Your contact form is irritating in other ways</h3>
<p>There are probably hundreds of ways you could set up your contact form to be maximally irritating, and I can’t cover them all here. I’ll leave you with one final example that doesn’t fit into the categories above though.</p>
<p>Sainsbury’s has a <a href="https://help.sainsburys.co.uk/help/contact-us">contact form</a> that forces you to navigate down a long options tree. Only to open a modal and ask you to select the topic again. They then present the tiniest form window ever, which makes it near impossible to fill out:</p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/sainsburys.gif" alt="Contact form displayed in a modal with limited vertical height, such that only 1-2 fields of about 20 are visible at any time"></p>
<h2 id="why-youve-done-this-and-what-to-do-instead">Why you’ve done this, and what to do instead</h2>
<p>Beyond just ‘it’s what we’ve always done’, there are a few reasons you might think a contact form is a good idea. Here we’ll go through some of them and what you might do instead.</p>
<h3 id="to-collect-structured-data-that-speeds-up-resolving-problems">To collect structured data that speeds up resolving problems</h3>
<p>You might want to use a contact form to collect structured data, so it saves you time processing requests. For example, making sure the customer provides the right identifiers for you to find them on your systems quickly, or automatically assigning queries to the right teams.</p>
<p>This <em>can</em> be okay in some circumstances. Amazon does this well: it shows you the recent items you’ve purchased and also allows you to completely self-serve common customer service workflows (like requesting a return) - while still allowing you to speak to a human fairly easily.</p>
<p>However, unless you’ve got an excellent customer service portal (you probably don’t), you should just stick with an email for general contact purposes.</p>
<p>To make sure you have the right details, just set up a sensible auto-reply. Here’s a good example from GP at hand:<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-5" id="user-content-fnref-5" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">5</a></sup></p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/gpathand-autoreply.png" alt="An autoresponder email stating 'If you haven't already, please ensure you have provided us with your full name, postal address and a contact phone number'"></p>
<p>Next, before automating assigning queries to the right teams, consider whether you need to do this: I’ve seen very small teams try to justify ‘a contact form will help us categorise emails’ when they receive two emails a day, or they all go to the same person anyways.</p>
<p>If you really do need to automate assigning emails, take a look at platforms like <a href="https://support.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/articles/5608652527386-Getting-started-with-Zendesk-AI-and-Advanced-AI#h_01HH0BTYYBV6ETWHG8779M9Y8C">Zendesk and their AI systems</a> - this kind of thing is exactly what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_language_model">LLMs</a> thrive at (or often just <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Guide/Regular_expressions">regular expressions</a> will get you far enough).</p>
<h3 id="you-want-people-to-contact-you-and-think-your-form-will-lower-the-barrier">You want people to contact you, and think your form will lower the barrier</h3>
<p>Empirically, this doesn’t hold up. I previously thought this was true, but I’ve since seen at 3 different organisations who’ve made the switch that this doesn’t seem to be the case - i.e. they get the same number of genuine contacts by listing an email as having a contact form. I’d love to rigorously analyse and publish the data on this to help convince others.</p>
<p>One category where this might not be true by default is for very ‘low-effort’ feedback forms. I think this can probably be mitigated by making it clear that you’re friendly and would be happy to receive informal emails.</p>
<p>The other category where I think this might be more likely to lower the barrier is where people prefer to be anonymous. For example, someone who might not be public about their sexual orientation might not want to have related comments so easily linked back to them, but still want to give feedback on some article. The UK Government website, GOV.UK, has a delightfully simple example that works well for collecting anonymous feedback:</p>
<p><img src="https://adamjones.me/images/blog/dont-use-contact-forms/govuk-feedback.png" alt="Form titled 'Help us improve GOV.UK', with two questions: 'What were you doing?' and 'What went wrong?'"></p>
<h3 id="youre-worried-youll-get-spam-if-you-list-an-email-online">You’re worried you’ll get spam if you list an email online</h3>
<p>Surprisingly, not really. I found we often ended up getting <em>less</em> spam compared to WordPress forms - there might be something about it being easier to submit anonymous forms with rubbish, compared to actually sending emails with decent enough reputation to get past today's spam filters.</p>
<p>If you really worry about this, you can <a href="https://superuser.com/questions/235937/does-e-mail-address-obfuscation-actually-work">obfuscate your email from spam bots</a>. But I think this is usually wasted time given just how rare this kind of email spam is, and how good spam filters have gotten. Plus this risks you messing this up and breaking something.</p>
<h3 id="you-want-to-manage-messages-as-a-team">You want to manage messages as a team</h3>
<p>You can do this with email! Hook up a <a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-gb/office/open-and-use-a-shared-mailbox-in-outlook-d94a8e9e-21f1-4240-808b-de9c9c088afd">shared mailbox</a>, <a href="https://support.google.com/a/users/answer/167430">collaborative inbox</a>, or one of the many off-the-shelf customer service solutions like <a href="https://www.zendesk.co.uk/service/ticketing-system/customer-service-email-management-software/">Zendesk</a>, <a href="https://www.zoho.com/desk/">Zoho Desk</a>, <a href="https://www.freshworks.com/freshdesk/">Freshdesk</a>, <a href="https://zammad.org/">Zammad</a>, <a href="https://osticket.com/">osTicket</a>, or <a href="https://freescout.net/">FreeScout</a> to your email.</p>
<h3 id="you-think-email-isnt-secure-enough">You think email isn’t secure enough</h3>
<p>Email used to be very insecure because it wasn’t encrypted.<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-6" id="user-content-fnref-6" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">6</a></sup> This meant that people between mail servers could read the contents of messages.</p>
<p>However, unless you’ve done something weird with your email setup, it’ll probably be encrypted securely like <a href="https://transparencyreport.google.com/safer-email/overview">99% of other email traffic</a> is in 2024.</p>
<p>In theory, your customer might be using an email provider that doesn’t support encryption - which could lead them to sending something to you insecurely and putting them at risk. I think most organisations can accept this risk given how rare this is, given that this is on the customer’s end. For what it’s worth, the UK’s National Cyber Security Centre <a href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/organisation/ncsc">is happy to list a contact email for themselves</a>.</p>
<p>Another question to ask yourself if you don’t list an email for this reason: do you respond via email after people contact you?</p>
<h3 id="you-think-email-isnt-accessible-to-assistive-technology-users">You think email isn't accessible to assistive technology users</h3>
<p>I've heard the claim that you need a contact form to be compliant with some common accessibility standard - this is simply not true. If you don't beleive me, try and actually find this rule.<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-7" id="user-content-fnref-7" data-footnote-ref="true" aria-describedby="footnote-label">7</a></sup></p>
<p>Listing an email is almost certainly easier to parse and understand than your contact form.</p>
<h3 id="you-dont-want-people-to-fill-in-your-form">You don't want people to fill in your form</h3>
<p>Yeah - this is one I'm not really here to help you with.</p>
<p>There are some organisations that intentionally want their form to be difficult to complete - perhaps it’s a regulatory requirement that you don’t really want to comply with. If you’re doing this, you should probably feel bad.</p>
<p>It’s unclear how intentional this is, but in this vein Meta (Facebook) makes it very difficult to contact them about data protection matters. Some charities <a href="https://noyb.eu/en/no-bullsht-opt-out-free-noyb-tool-quick-and-broad-facebook-objections">have already highlighted</a> that Meta’s forms seem to be particularly difficult to find, and difficult to complete. My own experiences with this process have been complex and drawn out, having been referred to several different broken forms.</p>
<p>Regulators should be doing a better job ensuring they are setting the bar appropriately in these cases, in a way that rewards actors who are complying with both the letter and spirit of laws or regulations.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Contact forms are hard to get right, and often just a worse experience for everyone involved. Go forth and remove your contact form and list your email on your website now!</p>
<section data-footnotes="true">
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1">
<p>As in, it’s impossible to submit from the website - the error appears when submitting. Inspecting the network requests suggests this error is because a ‘title’ property is missing: likely some mismatch between the backend and the frontend (there is no title field on the frontend). Yes, these problems happen in software development from time to time: but there’s no need to incur this if email already ‘just works’. <a href="#user-content-fnref-1" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-2">
<p><code>test+test@example.com</code>, <code>tést@example.com</code> and <code>test@éxample.com</code> are all valid emails as per <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6532">RFC 6532</a>, but are all rejected by this form <a href="#user-content-fnref-2" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-3">
<p>As a fun side bonus, if you make a single mistake on this form it deletes everything and forces you to start from scratch. For example, if you format your phone number ‘wrong’, your entire message you typed up is wiped. <a href="#user-content-fnref-3" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 3">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-4">
<p>I don't think people's birthdays should be a security measure, but unfortunately it seems to be the world we live in. I'll have to explore this in another rant. <a href="#user-content-fnref-4" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 4">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-5">
<p>It could probably place this a bit more prominently by cutting some of the other stuff, but on the whole the message is fairly clear and not an unreasonable length. <a href="#user-content-fnref-5" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 5">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-6">
<p>There are also other email security risks, such as email spoofing (solvable with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DMARC">DMARC</a>!). But on the whole, the email security risk seems overblown (especially compared to 'crappy WordPress form' security risk). <a href="#user-content-fnref-6" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 6">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-7">
<p>Further examples that would seem to suggest that this is not necessary is that the following organisations list an email to contact them: <a href="https://www.equalityhumanrights.com/contact-us">Equality and Human Rights Commission</a> (the public body responsible for disability rights), <a href="https://www.scope.org.uk/contact-us/">Scope</a> (a major disability equality charity) and <a href="https://abilitynet.org.uk/how-contact-us">AbilityNet</a> (a charity building assistive technologies). <a href="#user-content-fnref-7" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 7">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A love letter to bicycle maintenance and repair (208 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tegowerk.eu/posts/bicycle-repair/</link>
            <guid>40255209</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 05:50:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tegowerk.eu/posts/bicycle-repair/">https://tegowerk.eu/posts/bicycle-repair/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40255209">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p>It was the 28th of June, 2020; the perfect summer day. I remember it distinctly because of two important events that took place on that day. The first was the unfortunate discovery that I am highly sensitive to the venomous hairs of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oak_processionary">Oak processionary</a> caterpillar. If you’ve never wished you could use a cheese grater to remove the skin off your arms and legs just to be rid of the itching, then you can’t really understand how I felt for two whole weeks that summer.</p><p>The second thing that happened on that 28th of June was the seemingly inconsequential purchase of two secondhand bicycles. My wife and I drove out to a local park to test ride a couple of ’90s-era Trek 970 bikes that a guy had restored in his garage. We didn’t know a thing about bicycles, but we liked what we saw; the bikes worked great and felt very nice to ride around the park–the fact that I also happened to ride through a floating cloud of Oak-processionary hairs would only become apparent the next day.</p><p>So we took our new old bikes home, and we started riding them around. We got into bicycle touring too around that time, and that’s worth an entire future post on its own for the joy it’s brought us, but for now I’d like to get back on track. See, I kept thinking about the guy we bought the bikes from. I don’t know if he did this as a hobby, side business, or what, but I became increasingly fascinated by the idea of fixing up and restoring old bicycles. As I said, at that time I didn’t know a thing about bikes; I couldn’t even change a brake cable, but I’d always wanted to pick up a hobby that would take me away from the computer, something that would get my hards dirty at the same time, so why not give this a try?</p><p>Back then I still had my previous bike too, gathering dust and cobwebs somewhere in the basement. It was a Cube Aim that I’d had for at least a decade and had practically never serviced. It worked like crap, but I suspected most of it was just lack of maintenance and proper adjustment. In fact, it was in a lot of ways a nicer bike than the one I’d just bought. So I set a goal for myself: I would take the bike apart, down to the last bolt; I would clean everything up, change whatever parts were broken, and put it back together again. After all, how hard could it be?</p><p>At its core, a bike is a very simple, very old machine. The basic operating principles have remained virtually unchanged since the first <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safety_bicycle">“safety bicycle”</a> of the late 19th century: you push on the pedals to rotate a crank arm; a chain transfers the power to the rear sprockets; the sprockets turn the rear wheel. That’s it, that’s all there is to it; a wonderfully simple device that is nonetheless the single <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bicycle_performance#Energy_efficiency">most energy-efficient</a> mode of transportation humanity has come up with.</p><p>Of course, modern bikes are a lot more complicated than that: inflatable tires; the freewheel; derailleurs; suspension; hydraulic disk brakes; electric motors and electronic gear shifting. Every major technological advancement has brought with it increased safety, ease of use, and performance, at the cost of adding extra layers of complexity on top of the basic initial machine. It’s increasingly rare now for people to know how to repair their own bicycles, and bicycle mechanics themselves have more and more skills to learn if they want to keep on top of the fast changes in their field.</p><p>Which brings me back to my modest Cube. I grossly underestimated just how complex a task I’d set for myself, of course, but at the same time I also underestimated just how much I would love doing it. I had never considered myself mechanically inclined; my dad didn’t teach me much, and by that time I hadn’t yet truly internalized something that has since become one of my main mantras in life: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K4J_QfiGRRc">what one man can do, another can do</a> (by the way, if you haven’t watched <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0119051/">The Edge</a> yet, you really should). Thankfully, we live in glorious informational times that our forefathers didn’t even dream of. A trove of knowledge of incalculable value is available at the fingertips of every self-learner, and bicycle repair is no exception. YouTube channels like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCzaZ1sPWEuZN-I8_XT6AH8g">Park Tool</a> or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaAK2FaxQ2xiBbAUVZsvDYQ">RJ The Bike Guy</a> provide a visual, hands-on learning experience that is comparable to the tragically fading practice of apprenticeship. Internet forums like <a href="http://reddit.com/r/bikewrench">/r/bikewrench</a> give one the ability to pick the brains of real-life professional mechanics (although, just like every other subreddit, it does have its idiots that one needs to learn to steer clear of), and no list of bike repair resources could be complete without mentioning <em>the Bible</em>, the website of the late <a href="https://www.sheldonbrown.com/">Sheldon Brown</a>. May he rest in peace.</p><p>Eventually, I finished the project. It didn’t go smoothly at all. On more than one occasion I realized I was missing some vital tool, or some tiny part that I hadn’t even known existed until I suddenly needed it–like <a href="https://tegowerk.eu/img/2022-02-04-repair/EfCKYf2.jpg">cable ferrules</a>, or a <a href="https://tegowerk.eu/img/2022-02-04-repair/UqbJC1q.png">star nut</a>–and without which the whole project ground to a halt. Nevertheless, the bike progressed, then finally it was done, and from that moment on I knew I was hooked. I’ve been working as a web developer since 2006. Coding has always been my great passion. I have literally lost count of the number of apps and projects I worked on for the past sixteen years. But let me tell you something: not a single launch has given me the same high, has been as memorable or as character-defining as rebuilding that cheap bicycle in 2020; I simply had to have more of it.</p><p>Almost two years have passed since then. I’ve rebuilt almost twenty more bikes in that time. I’ve learned to reliably <a href="https://www.wheelpro.co.uk/wheelbuilding/book.php">build wheels</a>, and I’ve become the go-to guy for bike repair in my circle of friends–and even for some folks who I didn’t even know before. There isn’t a single bicycle repair task that scares me anymore. I’ve gone from not being able to change a brake cable, to bravely <a href="https://tegowerk.eu/posts/sram-automatix/">taking apart complex components</a> or <a href="https://tegowerk.eu/posts/drop-bar-shifter-tutorial/">hacking them</a> for use-cases that they weren’t designed for. We have since sold the bikes we bought back in 2020, and both my wife and I are now riding bikes that I’ve built from scratch. The pride I feel when we go out on a ride cannot be overstated, and I love biking now more than I ever did as a result.</p><p>I realize this may sound overblown, but the changes this hobby has wrought in me go beyond just teaching me a fun and useful skill. Learning to fix bicycles has changed my outlook on manual labor, on the nature of work, and ultimately on life itself:</p><h3 id="thinking-versus-doing">Thinking versus doing</h3><p>Looking back, I realize I had a terribly naive perspective on manual labor. I lived with the misconception–drilled into me since childhood–that work can be neatly split into two categories: knowledge work and manual work; that there are those who think, and those who do, and by extension (and it greatly shames me to admit this) that there is a clear difference in value between the two.</p><p>I have since realized that the line that separates thinking from doing doesn’t actually exist; instead, the two are facets of the same coin, and neither can exist in isolation. This came to me when I noticed that there is just as much thinking going into solving a bike repair problem as there is in solving a bug in my code (and, incidentally, the same high when I finally crack it). I later ended up reading <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6261332-shop-class-as-soulcraft">Shop Class as Soulcraft: An Inquiry Into the Value of Work</a>, by Matthew B. Crawford; it was an eye-opening read that eloquently put into words a concept I had merely sniffed the edges of. I highly recommend you give it a read.</p><h3 id="what-one-man-can-do-another-can-do">What one man can do, another can do</h3><p>I touched on this a bit earlier in the text. I have a lot more courage now in tackling all sorts of repairs around the house, not just on bikes. This is because I now know that I have the capacity to learn the necessary skills, but more importantly, it’s because I’ve learned to look at objects and <em>see them</em>. Something has shifted inside me, and it has altered my perception of the world. Before, I used to look at an object and only see it on the surface; I saw the function it performed and nothing more. Now I see the bolts, the screws, the cables, the hinges, the motors, and I know that each one of those can be fixed or replaced independently of the object as a whole. Maybe this has always been obvious to you, but as I’ve already said, I didn’t learn much of this stuff growing up; it’s a failing I put on my shoulders and the shoulders of my father both, and it’s something I’m only truly making up for now, in the fourth decade of my life. Better late than never.</p><h3 id="tangibility-of-objects-and-people">Tangibility, of objects and people</h3><p>At work I build websites. Well, that’s not strictly true. I build web apps, I write unit tests, I manage databases, I architect and set up the cloud infrastucture, I set up continuous integration and continuous delivery pipelines, and sometimes I even help my colleagues fix the Docker setup on their machines. My daily conversations are peppered with such acronyms as PHP, TDD, CI, CD, K8s, SQL, JSON, AWS, GCP, CF, SSH, SSL, and on and on and on.</p><p>If you’re not an IT person, most of these words won’t mean anything to you, and therein lies my next point. Conceptually, it’s easier for humans to relate to occupations that produce something you can point a finger at. The further removed a person is from the results of their own work, the greater the disconnect they feel, and the greater the chance they’ll conclude they’re working in a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullshit_job">bullshit job</a>.</p><p>Now, I don’t actually believe I’m working a bullshit job. I don’t really believe they exist. I believe jobs provide value even when the value is not immediately, tangibly apparent. But I do believe in the disconnect that makes people feel this way, and I do believe that’s a distinct hallmark of the modern service-oriented industries. You’ll never hear a baker say their job is bullshit.</p><p>And it’s not just the tangible aspect of the work itself, either. The same can be said of the people who ultimately benefit from the work. Websites that I’ve built are being used right now by hundreds of thousands of people, yet for some reason I still feel I’m making a greater impact when I see a person ride away on a bike I’ve just repaired for them. It’s senseless, yet there it is.</p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nintendo blitzes GitHub with over 8k emulator-related DMCA takedowns (212 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.engadget.com/nintendo-blitzes-github-with-over-8000-emulator-related-dmca-takedowns-200021877.html</link>
            <guid>40254602</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 03:37:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.engadget.com/nintendo-blitzes-github-with-over-8000-emulator-related-dmca-takedowns-200021877.html">https://www.engadget.com/nintendo-blitzes-github-with-over-8000-emulator-related-dmca-takedowns-200021877.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40254602">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main role="main"><div id="module-moreStories" data-wf-sticky-offset="130px   10px" data-wf-sticky-position="" data-wf-sticky-target="#adsStream" data-wf-trigger-percentage=""><ul><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/1gUFCX8h7IVNhH2Gi._Bgg--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2024-05/d9f08690-0974-11ef-bd8f-8eb0887821c4" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="dd2d602a-2c2f-4e26-95cf-e8aa604a3a44" href="https://www.engadget.com/redfalls-two-dlc-heroes-are-still-mia-a-year-later-180838827.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:3;ct:story;g:dd2d602a-2c2f-4e26-95cf-e8aa604a3a44" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">Redfall’s two DLC heroes are still MIA a year later</a></h4><p>Microsoft may want to be more careful about leaving a trail of broken promises when games don’t go as planned. A year after Redfall landed with a thud, players are still waiting for the advertised post-launch DLC they already paid for.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/7aEQ.4fdWuMUUrnwA97sAw--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2023-09/a4fc4790-5749-11ee-8fb2-b86b1385cef0" alt=""></p></div></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/_TvVDHp9inz_19yiMJ93Lg--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2024-04/f97e0620-f8e1-11ee-b6c6-1e329bded0bb" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="779f199a-c821-4fb1-9321-0fe080c20b4d" href="https://www.engadget.com/best-tech-upgrades-laptops-tablets-headphones-smartphones-monitors-bags-for-graduates-150049903.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:12;ct:story;g:779f199a-c821-4fb1-9321-0fe080c20b4d" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">The best gifts to upgrade your grad’s tech setup</a></h4><p>College grads are probably using the same tech they started out with four years ago. Here are the best gadgets you can get them to upgrade their kit, including laptops, headphones, monitors and more.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/jXbFa1iT1I43q580qMv7LA--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2021-12/7e185d50-5a8c-11ec-97de-17cd16d432dd" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="90f488a8-a981-4d8d-ad71-e507477d020b" href="https://www.engadget.com/the-morning-after-pelotons-grim-post-pandemic-reality-111518934.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:14;ct:story;g:90f488a8-a981-4d8d-ad71-e507477d020b" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">The Morning After: Peloton's grim post-pandemic reality</a></h4><p>The biggest news stories this morning: 
Huawei has been secretly funding research in America after being blacklisted, The best noise-canceling earbuds, Olivia Rodrigo, Drake and other Universal artists return to TikTok.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/FGRSzt3Sm8ws6w4klf1wYA--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2024-04/1b3e6980-fb4e-11ee-a1db-b3af8fdba41a" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="a649d9d6-10c3-35af-94c2-dfe91925156a" href="https://www.engadget.com/best-password-manager-134639599.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:16;ct:story;g:a649d9d6-10c3-35af-94c2-dfe91925156a" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">The best password manager for 2024</a></h4><p>Remembering dozens of passwords can be difficult for anyone. These are the best password managers you can use to keep your information safe and secure.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/MdPqMZ1Zp5TMGVrtHJQd2A--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2024-05/e8ff96c0-08b2-11ef-bbfe-5d492495948d" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="5a90c300-7585-4546-a1fc-c9ad59966021" href="https://www.engadget.com/audible-is-testing-a-cheaper-plan-in-australia-191347871.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:20;ct:story;g:5a90c300-7585-4546-a1fc-c9ad59966021" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">Audible is testing a cheaper plan in Australia</a></h4><p>Audible is testing a cheaper subscription tier in Australia that sounds like an answer to Spotify’s audiobook push. The service’s new Standard plan gives you one free title per month, but your credits don’t roll over.</p></div></div></li></ul></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I joined landlord groups to persuade them to be better people to their tenants (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thisisalot.com/unhinged-opinions/i-joined-a-bunch-of-landlord-groups-to-subtly-manipulate-them-into-being-better-people/118/</link>
            <guid>40254573</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 03:30:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thisisalot.com/unhinged-opinions/i-joined-a-bunch-of-landlord-groups-to-subtly-manipulate-them-into-being-better-people/118/">https://www.thisisalot.com/unhinged-opinions/i-joined-a-bunch-of-landlord-groups-to-subtly-manipulate-them-into-being-better-people/118/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40254573">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<h2>It’s actually kinda working</h2>



<div><p>So, about a year ago I joined a bunch of a landlord groups on Facebook and Nextdoor. I’ve worked diligently to manipulate them into taking pro-tenant actions, and it actually has kind of worked? Here’s the general strategy:</p><figure><img title="noun-landlord-111368 » This is a lot" decoding="async" width="512" height="512" src="https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/noun-landlord-111368.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/noun-landlord-111368.png 512w, https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/noun-landlord-111368-300x300.png 300w, https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/noun-landlord-111368-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px"></figure></div>







<ol>
<li>Make some posts detailing how I run my “businesss”<sup data-fn="6a55418c-f453-4de4-a1a6-4282352192ef"><a id="6a55418c-f453-4de4-a1a6-4282352192ef-link" href="#6a55418c-f453-4de4-a1a6-4282352192ef">1</a></sup> and ask a few questions.</li>



<li>Establish credibility by earning their trust by posting helpful information. </li>



<li>Politely suggest taking actions that unequivocally benefit the tenant by dressing them up as beneficial to the landlord.  </li>
</ol>



<p>These three steps, of which order matters a lot, have given me a few wins I’d like to share with y’all. </p>



<h2>Establishing your credentials by lying </h2>



<p>Landlords won’t listen to tenants. In the same way that Republicans won’t seriously engage with Democrats and <em>vice versa</em>. The two roles are viewed as kind of adversarial, so going directly into trying to change their behavior is not a  going proposition. </p>



<p>However, <em>all</em> humans listen to people that they think are like themselves. Naturally, we place more weight on people with whom we have a common reference point. This shared reference binds us together, and its through those ties that bind you can persuade effectively. So, the first move was to convince them that I am in fact a landlord<sup data-fn="d458854b-cbc0-43c7-a9c3-cc614f72f476"><a href="#d458854b-cbc0-43c7-a9c3-cc614f72f476" id="d458854b-cbc0-43c7-a9c3-cc614f72f476-link">2</a></sup>.</p>



<p>So, when the question was posed “do you own a property?” when I applied to join the group, I chose a random 2-flat at the other end of my street and said “yes”. </p>



<h2>Asking Questions to get your name out there</h2>



<p>When I was still new in the groups, I asked some questions about common landlord issues to win cheap interactions. The exposure of seeing my name in the group and interacting with a few of them was the actual goal. People are much more easily influenced by familiar faces than complete strangers, unless they are paying them (e.g. consultants). Tragically, no one paid me to go on this campaign. </p>



<figure><img title="GreaseDownDrain » This is a lot" decoding="async" width="707" height="234" src="https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/GreaseDownDrain.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/GreaseDownDrain.png 707w, https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/GreaseDownDrain-300x99.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 707px) 100vw, 707px"><figcaption>literally every landlord probably has</figcaption></figure>



<p>A week or two of a few questions sprinkled-in is really all that’s needed. Maybe a total of two questions per group. Bonus points in the questions are about common sources of frustration/anger for landlords. People interact more with content that angers them, and our goal is just to get some interactions. </p>



<h2>Creating friendly-informative content to establish credibility and gain favor of the landlords</h2>



<p>The next phase was a campaign of friendly, helpful, and more importantly strictly factual posts to establish credibility. I spent some time reading the comments of other posts in the group, so I could tailor each post to whatever common misconceptions were being repeated. The more people who could learn something new from my posts, the better. </p>



<figure><img title="LLCs » This is a lot" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="697" height="340" src="https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/LLCs.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/LLCs.png 697w, https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/LLCs-300x146.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 697px) 100vw, 697px"></figure>



<p>Notice, there’s not much room to comment from the content of the post. That’s by design. I’m not trying to start a discussion or an argument here. I want people to read the post, smash the like button, and feel a little more informed. Notice the increase in reactions from our beginning questions. The goal is to slowly but steadily build-up reactions and discussions. Don’t come in with too much controversy. </p>



<h2>Cashing in the social currency</h2>



<p>Then it was time to take the offensive. After reading many posts of landlords asking if they can <em>pre-file</em> eviction paperwork (they can’t) to general posts complaining about tenants <em>cooking in their own apartment</em>, I was ready. </p>



<figure><img title="landlords » This is a lot" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="702" height="703" src="https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/landlords.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/landlords.png 702w, https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/landlords-300x300.png 300w, https://www.thisisalot.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/landlords-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 702px) 100vw, 702px"><figcaption>they paid the $1000</figcaption></figure>



<p>I had to resist my urge to respond with “<strong>I THINK THE FUCK NOT</strong>“. Instead, I calmly laid out an alternative in which this landlord looks like the hero, instead of someone who seriously just asked if they can <em>pre-file</em> an eviction. Ridiculous. However, the appeal to ego worked. Somewhere, some tenant got a $1,000 check. <strong>Mission accomplished</strong>.</p>







<figure><blockquote><p>It ain’t much but it’s honest work. </p></blockquote></figure>


<ol><li id="6a55418c-f453-4de4-a1a6-4282352192ef">There is no business. I don’t own any real estate.  <a href="#6a55418c-f453-4de4-a1a6-4282352192ef-link" aria-label="Jump to footnote reference 1">↩︎</a></li><li id="d458854b-cbc0-43c7-a9c3-cc614f72f476">Once again, I am not a landlord. <a href="#d458854b-cbc0-43c7-a9c3-cc614f72f476-link" aria-label="Jump to footnote reference 2">↩︎</a></li></ol>


<div>
			<p><img src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/aea30111d3f88654af35064c2dac662b?s=300&amp;d=blank&amp;r=g" alt="author avatar">
		</p>
			<div><p>
			
			Luke A man on a crusade against apathy.

I created this website on April Fool’s Day 2024, after noticing the sharp uptick in garbage writing on the internet. My day job is as a data something. I also do consulting work for small-business’ trying to modernize their data situations and make a buck off them. I write a lot about technology, economics, my own antics, and opinions.&nbsp;

If my writing has entertained, informed, aggravated, or made you reconsider anything, then I consider this blog a fantastic success.
							</p>
				
					</div>
</div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Insects and other animals have consciousness (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nautil.us/insects-and-other-animals-have-consciousness-571584/</link>
            <guid>40254054</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 01:25:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nautil.us/insects-and-other-animals-have-consciousness-571584/">https://nautil.us/insects-and-other-animals-have-consciousness-571584/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40254054">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p><span>I</span>n 2022, researchers at the Bee Sensory and Behavioral Ecology Lab at Queen Mary University of London observed bumblebees doing something remarkable: The diminutive, fuzzy creatures were engaging in activity that&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2022.08.013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">could only be described as play</a>. Given small wooden balls, the bees pushed them around and rotated them. The behavior had no obvious connection to mating or survival, nor was it rewarded by the scientists. It was, apparently, just for fun.</p><p>The study on playful bees is part of a body of research that a group of prominent scholars of animal minds cited last month, buttressing&nbsp;<a href="http://www.nydeclaration.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a new declaration</a>&nbsp;that extends scientific support for consciousness to a wider suite of animals than has been formally acknowledged before. For decades, there’s been a broad agreement among scientists that animals similar to us—the great apes, for example—have conscious experience, even if their consciousness differs from our own. In recent years, however, researchers have begun to acknowledge that consciousness may also be widespread among animals that are very different from us, including invertebrates with completely different and far simpler nervous systems.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>We have much more in common with other animals than we do with things like ChatGPT.</p>
</blockquote><p>The new declaration, signed by biologists and philosophers, formally embraces that view. It reads, in part: “The empirical evidence indicates at least a realistic possibility of conscious experience in all vertebrates (including all reptiles, amphibians, and fishes) and many invertebrates (including, at minimum, cephalopod mollusks, decapod crustaceans, and insects).” Inspired by recent research findings that describe complex cognitive behaviors in these and other animals, the document represents a new consensus and suggests that researchers may have overestimated the degree of neural complexity required for consciousness.</p>
<p>The four-paragraph New York Declaration on Animal Consciousness was unveiled on April 19, at a one-day conference called “<a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/events/ptbAnN83QHwazPJ6a/the-emerging-science-of-animal-consciousness" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Emerging Science of Animal Consciousness</a>” held at New York University. Spearheaded by the philosopher and cognitive scientist&nbsp;<a href="https://profiles.laps.yorku.ca/profiles/andrewsk/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kristin Andrews</a>&nbsp;of York University in Ontario, the philosopher and environmental scientist&nbsp;<a href="https://as.nyu.edu/faculty/jeff-sebo.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jeff Sebo</a>&nbsp;of New York University, and the philosopher&nbsp;<a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/cpnss/people/jonathan-birch" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jonathan Birch</a>&nbsp;of the London School of Economics and Political Science, the declaration has so far been signed by more than 100 researchers, including the psychologists&nbsp;<a href="https://www.psychol.cam.ac.uk/people/nsc22%40cam.ac.uk" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Nicola Clayton</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bu.edu/psych/profile/irene-pepperberg/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Irene Pepperberg</a>, the neuroscientists&nbsp;<a href="https://www.anilseth.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Anil Seth</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://alleninstitute.org/person/christof-koch/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Christof Koch</a>, the zoologist&nbsp;<a href="http://chittkalab.sbcs.qmul.ac.uk/Lars.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lars Chittka</a>, and the philosophers&nbsp;<a href="https://consc.net/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">David Chalmers</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://petergodfreysmith.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Peter Godfrey-Smith</a>.</p><p>The declaration focuses on the most basic kind of consciousness, known as phenomenal consciousness. Roughly put, if a creature has phenomenal consciousness, then it is “like something” to be that creature—an idea enunciated by the philosopher Thomas Nagel in his influential 1974 essay, “<a href="https://www.sas.upenn.edu/~cavitch/pdf-library/Nagel_Bat.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">What is it like to be a bat?</a>” Even if a creature is very different from us, Nagel wrote, “fundamentally an organism has conscious mental states if and only if there is something that it is like to&nbsp;<em>be</em>&nbsp;that organism. … We may call this the subjective character of experience.” If a creature is phenomenally conscious, it has the capacity to experience feelings such as pain or pleasure or hunger, but not necessarily more complex mental states such as self-awareness.</p><p>“I hope the declaration [draws] greater attention to the issues of nonhuman consciousness, and to the ethical challenges that accompany the possibility of conscious experiences far beyond the human,” wrote Seth, a neuroscientist at the University of Sussex, in an email. “I hope it sparks discussion, informs policy and practice in animal welfare, and galvanizes an understanding and appreciation that we have much more in common with other animals than we do with things like ChatGPT.”</p><p><strong>A Growing Awareness</strong></p>
<p>The declaration began to take shape last fall, following conversations between Sebo, Andrews, and Birch. “The three of us were talking about how much has happened over the past 10 years, the past 15 years, in the science of animal consciousness,” Sebo recalled. We now know, for example, that&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2021.102229" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">octopuses feel pain</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-62335-x" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cuttlefish remember details</a>&nbsp;of specific past events. Studies in fish have found that&nbsp;<a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/a-self-aware-fish-raises-doubts-about-a-cognitive-test-20181212/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cleaner wrasse appear to pass</a>&nbsp;a version of the “mirror test,” which indicates a degree of self-recognition, and that&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.1062420" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">zebra fish show signs of curiosity</a>. In the insect world,&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anbehav.2022.08.013" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bees show apparent play behavior</a>, while&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.88198.2" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Drosophila</em>&nbsp;fruit flies have distinct sleep patterns</a>&nbsp;influenced by their social environment. Meanwhile,&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/srep39935" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">crayfish display anxiety-like states</a>—and those states can be altered by anti-anxiety drugs.</p><figure><img width="800" height="342" alt="In Body Image" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Falk_Hero.png?auto=compress&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=png&amp;h=438&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;w=1024&amp;wpsize=large" srcset="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Falk_Hero.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1600 800w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Falk_Hero.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1200 600w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Falk_Hero.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=800 400w" loading="lazy"><figcaption><strong>INQUIRING MINDS:</strong> After reflecting on recent research into diverse animal minds, Jeff Sebo, Kristin Andrews, and Jonathan Birch (from left) decided to organize scientists and philosophers to sign a declaration that extends consciousness to more animals. <em>Credit: From left: Kate Reeder; Ben Wulf; Maria Moore/LSE.</em></figcaption></figure><p>These and other signs of conscious states in animals that had long been considered less than conscious excited and challenged biologists, cognitive scientists, and philosophers of mind. “A lot of people have now accepted for a while that, for example, mammals and birds are either conscious or very likely to be conscious, but less attention has been paid to other vertebrate and especially invertebrate taxa,” Sebo said. In conversations and at meetings, experts largely agreed that these animals must have consciousness. However, this newly formed consensus wasn’t being communicated to the wider public, including other scientists and policymakers. So the three researchers decided to draft a clear, concise statement and circulate it among their colleagues for endorsement. The declaration is not meant to be comprehensive but rather “to point to where we think the field is now and where the field is headed,” Sebo said.</p><p>The new declaration updates the most recent effort to establish scientific consensus on animal consciousness. In 2012, researchers published the&nbsp;<a href="http://fcmconference.org/img/CambridgeDeclarationOnConsciousness.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cambridge Declaration on Consciousness</a>, which said that an array of nonhuman animals, including but not limited to mammals and birds, have “the capacity to exhibit intentional behaviors” and that “humans are not unique in possessing the neurological substrates that generate consciousness.”</p>
<p>The new declaration expands the scope of its predecessor and is also worded more carefully, Seth wrote. “It doesn’t try to do science by diktat, but rather emphasizes what we should take seriously regarding animal consciousness and the relevant ethics given the evidence and theories that we have.” He wrote that he is “not in favor of avalanches of open letters and the like,” but that he ultimately “came to the conclusion that this declaration was very much worth supporting.”</p><blockquote>
<p>It’s not enough for people to prevent animals in captivity from experiencing bodily pain and discomfort.</p>
</blockquote><p>Godfrey-Smith, a philosopher of science at the University of Sydney who has worked extensively with octopuses, believes that the complex behaviors those creatures exhibit—including problem-solving, tool use, and play behavior—can only be interpreted as indicators of consciousness. “They’ve got this attentive engagement with things, with us and with novel objects that makes it very hard not to think that there’s quite a lot going on inside them,” he said. He noted that recent papers looking at pain and dreamlike states in octopuses and cuttlefish “point in the same direction … toward experience as being a real part of their lives.”</p><p>While many of the animals mentioned in the declaration have brains and nervous systems that are very different from those of humans, the researchers say that this needn’t be a barrier to consciousness. For example, a bee’s brain contains only about a million neurons, compared to some 86 billion in the case of humans. But each of those bee neurons may be as structurally complex as an oak tree. The network of connections they form is also incredibly dense, with each neuron contacting perhaps 10,000 or 100,000 others. The nervous system of an octopus, by contrast, is complex in other ways. Its organization is highly distributed rather than centralized; a severed arm can exhibit many of the behaviors of the intact animal.</p>
<figure><img width="800" height="496" alt="In Body Image" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Falk_breaker.png?auto=compress&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=png&amp;h=635&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;w=1024&amp;wpsize=large" srcset="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Falk_breaker.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1600 800w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Falk_breaker.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1200 600w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Falk_breaker.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=800 400w" loading="lazy"><figcaption><strong>ANIMAL AWARENESS:</strong> Recent research on animal minds—including those of crayfish, octopuses, snakes, and fish—suggests that consciousness “can exist in a [neural] architecture that looks completely alien” to ours, Peter Godfrey-Smith said. <em>Credit: Clockwise from top left: Svetlana123/iStock; Colin Marshal/Biosphoto/Science Source; MATTHIASRABBIONE/iStock; Jim Maley/iStock.</em></figcaption></figure><p>The upshot, Andrews said, is that “we might not need nearly as much equipment as we thought we did” to achieve consciousness. She noted, for example, that even a cerebral cortex—the outer layer of the mammalian brain, which is believed to play a role in attention, perception, memory, and other key aspects of consciousness—may not be necessary for the simpler phenomenal consciousness targeted in the declaration.</p><p>“There was a big debate about whether fish are conscious, and a lot of that had to do with them lacking the brain structures that we see in mammals,” she said. “But when you look at birds and reptiles and amphibians, they have very different brain structures and different evolutionary pressures—and yet some of those brain structures, we’re finding, are doing the same kind of work that a cerebral cortex does in humans.”</p><p>Godfrey-Smith agreed, noting that behaviors indicative of consciousness “can exist in an architecture that looks completely alien to vertebrate or human architecture.”</p>
<p><strong>Mindful Relations</strong></p><p>While the declaration has implications for the treatment of animals, and especially for the prevention of animal suffering, Sebo noted that the focus should go beyond pain. It’s not enough for people to prevent animals in captivity from experiencing bodily pain and discomfort, he said. “We also have to provide them with the kinds of enrichment and opportunities that allow them to express their instincts and explore their environments and engage in social systems and otherwise be the kinds of complex agents they are.”</p><p>But the consequences of bestowing the label of “conscious” onto a wider array of animals—particularly animals whose interests we are not used to considering—are not straightforward. For example, our relationship with insects may be “inevitably a somewhat antagonistic one,” Godfrey-Smith said. Some pests eat crops, and mosquitoes can carry diseases. “The idea that we could just sort of make peace with the mosquitoes—it’s a very different thought than the idea that we could make peace with fish and octopuses,” he said.</p><p>Similarly, little attention is given to the well-being of insects such as<em>&nbsp;Drosophila</em>, which are widely used in biology research. “We think about the welfare of livestock and of mice in research, but we never think about the welfare of the insects,” said&nbsp;<a href="https://hosting.med.upenn.edu/hearing/team/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matilda Gibbons</a>, who researches the neural basis of consciousness at the University of Pennsylvania and has signed the declaration.</p>
<p>While scientific bodies have created some standards for the treatment of lab mice, it’s not clear if today’s declaration will lead to new standards for the treatment of insects. But new scientific findings do sometimes spark new policies. Britain, for example,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/News/Latest-news-from-LSE/2021/k-November-21/Octopuses-crabs-and-lobsters-welfare-protection" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">enacted legislation</a>&nbsp;to increase protection for octopuses, crabs, and lobsters after a London School of Economics&nbsp;<a href="https://www.lse.ac.uk/business/consulting/reports/review-of-the-evidence-of-sentiences-in-cephalopod-molluscs-and-decapod-crustaceans" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">report</a>&nbsp;indicated that those animals can experience pain, distress, or harm.</p><p>While the declaration makes no mention of artificial intelligence, the issue of possible AI consciousness has been on the minds of animal-consciousness researchers. “Current AI systems are very unlikely to be conscious,” Sebo said. However, what he’s learned about animal minds “does give me pause and makes me want to approach the topic with caution and humility.”</p><p>Andrews hopes that the declaration will spark more research into animals that have often been overlooked, a move that has the potential to further expand our awareness of the scope of consciousness in the animal world. “All these nematode worms and fruit flies that are in almost every university—study consciousness in them,” she said. “You already have them. Somebody in your lab is going to need a project. Make that project a consciousness project. Imagine that!”</p><p><em>This article was&nbsp;<a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/insects-and-other-animals-have-consciousness-experts-declare-20240419/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">originally published</a>&nbsp;on the</em>&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/abstractions/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Quanta Abstractions</a><em>&nbsp;blog.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p><em>Lead image: What’s going on in the mind of a bee? There’s “a realistic possibility” of consciousness, according to a new declaration. Credit: Tran The Ngoc/Shutterstock.</em></p> <ul>
<li>
<div>
<h6>
Dan Falk </h6>
<p>
Posted on May 3, 2024 </p>
</div>
<p>
Dan Falk (@danfalk) is a science journalist and broadcaster based in Toronto. His books include <i>The Science of Shakespeare</i> and <i>In Search of Time</i>. </p>
</li>
</ul>
<div>
<p><img src="https://nautil.us/wp-content/themes/nautilus-block-theme/images/icons/logo-icon.svg" alt="new_letter"></p><div>
<h4>Get the Nautilus newsletter</h4>
<p>Cutting-edge science, unraveled by the very brightest living thinkers.</p>
</div>

</div> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I never stopped learning from Daniel Dennett (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nautil.us/i-never-stopped-learning-from-daniel-dennett-569904/</link>
            <guid>40254047</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 01:23:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nautil.us/i-never-stopped-learning-from-daniel-dennett-569904/">https://nautil.us/i-never-stopped-learning-from-daniel-dennett-569904/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40254047">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p><span>T</span>hey say, never meet your heroes. Daniel Dennett, who was exceptional in so many ways, and who died last month, was for me an exception to this rule, too.</p><p>Like so many, I was first inspired by Dennett on reading one of his many bestsellers: <a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.hachettebookgroup.com/titles/daniel-c-dennett/consciousness-explained/9780316439480/?lens=little-brown" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Consciousness Explained</em></a>. It was 1991 and I was a fresh undergraduate with a powerful but undirected interest in consciousness. I had no idea how to go about studying it, or how to think about it. I was studying physics at Cambridge and had just plowed my way through Roger Penrose’s <a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/the-emperors-new-mind-9780198784920?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>The Emperor’s New Mind</em></a>, which had left me confused and despondent. Dennett’s book, with its presumptuous but oh-so-appealing title, was both a tease and a salve. I devoured it.</p>

<p>I didn’t agree with, or follow, everything. But I learned so much from his clear, witty writing, and from his famous “<a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://wwnorton.com/books/Intuition-Pumps-And-Other-Tools-for-Thinking/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">intuition pump</a>” thought experiments. I was left with the strong impression that consciousness, if not explained, was explainable, and I now had a north star to steer by.</p><blockquote>
<p>Learning from him could sometimes feel like looking straight at the sun.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Years passed. I thought I might meet him when he examined the doctoral thesis of a friend of mine who was studying with me at the University of Sussex, but it turned out they met over Skype. I would hear stories about him from one of my mentors at the University of Sussex and one of Dennett’s great friends, the philosopher Maggie Boden. These were tales of philosophical bust-ups, of sailing adventures, and of a voracious and seemingly unbounded intellectual appetite. The impression was of someone larger-than-life, who delighted in engaging with the world rather than preaching from an ivory tower. I read every book he wrote, and many of his papers. But the man himself remained remote.</p><p>I finally met Dennett in 2016. I’d recently joined a group of researchers at the <a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://cifar.ca/research-programs/brain-mind-consciousness/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brain, Mind, and Consciousness Program</a> of the Canadian Institute for Advanced Research, where Dennett had served as a long-time advisor. I remember feeling nervous when approaching him in the hotel bar before one of our meetings to say hello for the first time, but I needn’t have worried. Dennett was as approachable and avuncular in person as he was esteemed and revered in academia. Which is <em>very</em>. I don’t remember what we talked about then, but in the conversations and email exchanges that followed over the years he unfailingly exuded kindness, intellectual generosity, and perspicuity. He would tell you exactly what he thought, and he had the ability to do so in a way that made you feel improved, rather than dumb for making some stupid mistake.</p><p>Two examples stand out. The first is from seven years ago. I was in Vancouver, about to give a <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/anil_seth_your_brain_hallucinates_your_conscious_reality?language=en" target="_blank" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" rel="noreferrer noopener">TED talk</a>, and I was terrified. There were hundreds of influential people watching in person, and thousands more online. The next 16 minutes could be transformational or a total flop. But of all the people there whose opinions might matter, the one person I really didn’t want to disappoint was Dan Dennett.</p><p>Afterward, amid the high-fiving and catharsis, I noticed a short tweet from Dennett.</p>
<figure><img width="800" height="231" alt="In Body Image" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/TgDmwTgL-Seth_BREAKER.png?auto=compress&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=png&amp;h=296&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;w=1024&amp;wpsize=large" srcset="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/TgDmwTgL-Seth_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1600 800w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/TgDmwTgL-Seth_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1200 600w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/TgDmwTgL-Seth_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=800 400w" loading="lazy"></figure><p>“Almost perfect but not quite.” This combination of generosity and gentle criticism was typical. And he was right. In my talk I’d made the mistake of using the phrase “inner movie” to describe the multisensory immersive nature of conscious experience. But an inner movie implies an inner movie-watcher, a Cartesian homunculus of exactly the sort that Dennett—and I—wanted to expunge. This wasn’t a technicality. It was a give-away that I hadn’t really internalized the insight.</p><p>The second example was from a pandemic year. I was finalizing the first draft of my book <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/566315/being-you-by-anil-seth/" target="_blank" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>Being You</em></a> and, with some hesitation, I’d asked Dan if he’d be willing to consider writing a blurb for the cover. He declined, disarmingly—explaining that he’d decided some time back not to do any more blurbs, and if he changed his mind for me he’d risk upsetting many of his colleagues and friends he’d already said no to. But to my amazement he offered something much more valuable. He said he would set the draft as the reading for his next course at Tufts University, and then we could have two or three long Zoom sessions going through each chapter in detail with him and his class of talented students. It still astounds me that he took the time to do this, but he did, and the discussions we had in these sessions improved the book no end.</p><figure><img width="800" height="569" alt="In Body Image" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Seth_BREAKER-2.png?auto=compress&amp;fm=png&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1" srcset="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Seth_BREAKER-2.png?auto=compress&amp;fm=png&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1 800w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Seth_BREAKER-2.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1200 600w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/Seth_BREAKER-2.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=800 400w" loading="lazy"><figcaption><strong>THE GENTLE GIANT: </strong>Anil Seth with his personal hero Daniel Dennett. Seth was struck by Dennett’s combination of kindness, intellectual generosity, and perspicuity—his talent for gentle criticism that made one feel improved rather than chastened. <em>Photo courtesy of Anil Seth.</em></figcaption></figure>
<p>I never stopped learning from Dennett. I found myself coming round to his way of thinking on many things: <a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/Darwins-Dangerous-Idea/Daniel-C-Dennett/9780684824710" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the centrality of evolution</a> for understanding the mind, <a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262540421/elbow-room/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">how to think about free will</a> (though in 2021 we found ourselves on opposite sides of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MA4tGpJPc8Q" target="_blank" aria-label="a debate (opens in a new tab)" rel="noreferrer noopener">a debate</a> on the topic), and of course the absence of—or any need for—an inner observer, homunculus, or theater in the brain where everything “comes together.” But learning from him could sometimes feel like looking straight at the sun. I had to look away, to approach things sidelong, sparking the worry that I’d never fully grasp the weight of his arguments.</p><p>Dennett was often described as a philosophical “<a aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://keithfrankish.github.io/articles/Frankish_Illusionism%20as%20a%20theory%20of%20consciousness_eprint.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">illusionist</a>,” a position sometimes caricatured as saying that consciousness doesn’t exist. (A criticism of his 1991 book was that it should’ve been called <em>Consciousness Explained Away</em>.) But illusionism doesn’t, in fact, say this. On one reading, it says we are mistaken to think that the relationship between consciousness and physical, biological processes in the brain is a big mystery—the mystery that fellow philosopher David Chalmers calls the “<a href="https://nautil.us/whats-so-hard-about-understanding-consciousness-238421/" target="_blank" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" rel="noreferrer noopener">hard problem</a>” of consciousness. On another reading, which I’m more sympathetic to, it says that consciousness exists, but it might not be what we think it is—in the same way that the color red exists, but is not what we might think it is—there is no redness out there in the world nor is there a red “figment” in the mind, to borrow another of Dennett’s delightful terms.</p><p>I always looked forward to discussing these ideas with Dennett, and to chatting about them with my colleagues and friends, all of us trying to figure out what Dennett might really be thinking. One dimension of the sense of loss I now feel is that these discussions will become historical, a matter of interpretation and exegesis, rather than the living, vital process they so recently were.</p><p>In his later years, Dennett was fond of riffing on Chalmers’ hard problem with what he called the “hard question”: Once some (mental) content reaches consciousness, “then what happens?” This was his way of sending up the many theories that propose that conscious experience might somehow arise out of, or emerge from, this-or-that aspect of brain activity. Neurons fire in synchrony? Or with a certain form of complexity? <em>And then what happens? </em>In his diagnosis, the struggles of consciousness science lay in the systematic failure to properly ask, and answer, this question.</p>
<p>Daniel Clement Dennett was a gentle giant of the intellectual world. I, along with many others, will miss him deeply. He leaves an unmatched legacy in his books and papers, in how he brought philosophy and science together, and in the legions of students and researchers he taught and inspired. He was, I will assume, a materialist to the end. And in dying, perhaps Dan put his materialist beliefs to the ultimate test. And then what happens? <img decoding="async" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/nautilus-favicon-14.png?fm=png" alt=""></p><p><em>Lead image: Master1305 / Shutterstock</em></p> <ul>
<li>
<div>
<h6>
Anil Seth </h6>
<p>
Posted on May 2, 2024 </p>
</div>
<p>
Anil Seth is Professor of Cognitive and Computational Neuroscience and Director of the Centre for Consciousness Science at the University of Sussex. He is also Co-Director of the Canadian Institute for Advanced Research Program on Brain, Mind, and Consciousness, and author of the bestselling book <i>Being You—A New Science of Consciousness.</i> </p>
</li>
</ul>
<div>
<p><img src="https://nautil.us/wp-content/themes/nautilus-block-theme/images/icons/logo-icon.svg" alt="new_letter"></p><div>
<h4>Get the Nautilus newsletter</h4>
<p>Cutting-edge science, unraveled by the very brightest living thinkers.</p>
</div>

</div> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Value of one of S.F.'s biggest buildings plunges by 80% after Uber, Block leave (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sfchronicle.com/sf/article/s-f-office-building-value-19438429.php</link>
            <guid>40253831</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:32:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/sf/article/s-f-office-building-value-19438429.php">https://www.sfchronicle.com/sf/article/s-f-office-building-value-19438429.php</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40253831">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.sfchronicle.com/sf/article/s-f-office-building-value-19438429.php: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Bloom – A shadcn like UI library for Elixir and Phoenix (158 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bloom-ui.fly.dev/</link>
            <guid>40253774</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:23:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bloom-ui.fly.dev/">https://bloom-ui.fly.dev/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40253774">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <div>
  <div>
    <h2>
    <img src="https://bloom-ui.fly.dev/images/bloom-73d514c8254d4d96629ebf3f805cd78f.png?vsn=d">
    <span>
  Bloom
</span>
    </h2>
  </div>
  <p>
    
      The opinionated, open-source extension to Phoenix Core Components.<br>
      Install a copy of each component using the mix command in seconds.<br>
      Yours to edit and customise.
    
  </p>
  
</div>

  <section>
    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 128 128">
      <linearGradient id="elixir-original-a" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse" x1="835.592" y1="-36.546" x2="821.211" y2="553.414" gradientTransform="matrix(.1297 0 0 .2 -46.03 17.198)">
        <stop offset="0" stop-color="#d9d8dc"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#fff" stop-opacity=".385"></stop>
      </linearGradient>
      <path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="url(#elixir-original-a)" d="M64.4.5C36.7 13.9 1.9 83.4 30.9 113.9c26.8 33.5 85.4 1.3 68.4-40.5-21.5-36-35-37.9-34.9-72.9z"></path>
      <linearGradient id="elixir-original-b" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse" x1="942.357" y1="-40.593" x2="824.692" y2="472.243" gradientTransform="matrix(.1142 0 0 .2271 -47.053 17.229)">
        <stop offset="0" stop-color="#8d67af" stop-opacity=".672"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#9f8daf"></stop>
      </linearGradient>
      <path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="url(#elixir-original-b)" d="M64.4.2C36.8 13.6 1.9 82.9 31 113.5c10.7 12.4 28 16.5 37.7 9.1 26.4-18.8 7.4-53.1 10.4-78.5C68.1 33.9 64.2 11.3 64.4.2z"></path>
      <linearGradient id="elixir-original-c" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse" x1="924.646" y1="120.513" x2="924.646" y2="505.851" gradientTransform="matrix(.1227 0 0 .2115 -46.493 17.206)">
        <stop offset="0" stop-color="#26053d" stop-opacity=".762"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#b7b4b4" stop-opacity=".278"></stop>
      </linearGradient>
      <path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="url(#elixir-original-c)" d="M56.7 4.3c-22.3 15.9-28.2 75-24.1 94.2 8.2 48.1 75.2 28.3 69.6-16.5-6-29.2-48.8-39.2-45.5-77.7z"></path>
      <linearGradient id="elixir-original-d" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse" x1="428.034" y1="198.448" x2="607.325" y2="559.255" gradientTransform="matrix(.1848 0 0 .1404 -42.394 17.138)">
        <stop offset="0" stop-color="#91739f" stop-opacity=".46"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#32054f" stop-opacity=".54"></stop>
      </linearGradient>
      <path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="url(#elixir-original-d)" d="M78.8 49.8c10.4 13.4 12.7 22.6 6.8 27.9-27.7 19.4-61.3 7.4-54-37.3C22.1 63 4.5 96.8 43.3 101.6c20.8 3.6 54 2 58.9-16.1-.2-15.9-10.8-22.9-23.4-35.7z"></path>
      <linearGradient id="elixir-original-e" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse" x1="907.895" y1="540.636" x2="590.242" y2="201.281" gradientTransform="matrix(.1418 0 0 .1829 -45.23 17.18)">
        <stop offset="0" stop-color="#463d49" stop-opacity=".331"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#340a50" stop-opacity=".821"></stop>
      </linearGradient>
      <path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="url(#elixir-original-e)" d="M38.1 36.4c-2.9 21.2 35.1 77.9 58.3 71-17.7 35.6-56.9-21.2-64-41.7 1.5-11 2.2-16.4 5.7-29.3z"></path>
      <linearGradient id="elixir-original-f" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse" x1="1102.297" y1="100.542" x2="1008.071" y2="431.648" gradientTransform="matrix(.106 0 0 .2448 -47.595 17.242)">
        <stop offset="0" stop-color="#715383" stop-opacity=".145"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#f4f4f4" stop-opacity=".234"></stop>
      </linearGradient>
      <path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="url(#elixir-original-f)" d="M60.4 49.7c.8 7.9 3.9 20.5 0 28.8S38.7 102 43.6 115.3c11.4 24.8 37.1-4.4 36.9-19 1.1-11.8-6.6-38.7-1.8-52.5L76.5 41l-13.6-4c-2.2 3.2-3 7.5-2.5 12.7z"></path>
      <linearGradient id="elixir-original-g" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse" x1="1354.664" y1="140.06" x2="1059.233" y2="84.466" gradientTransform="matrix(.09173 0 0 .2828 -48.536 17.28)">
        <stop offset="0" stop-color="#a5a1a8" stop-opacity=".356"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#370c50" stop-opacity=".582"></stop>
      </linearGradient>
      <path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="url(#elixir-original-g)" d="M65.3 10.8C36 27.4 48 53.4 49.3 81.6l19.1-55.4c-1.4-5.7-2.3-9.5-3.1-15.4z"></path><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="#330A4C" fill-opacity=".316" d="M68.3 26.1c-14.8 11.7-14.1 31.3-18.6 54 8.1-21.3 4.1-38.2 18.6-54z"></path><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="#FFF" d="M45.8 119.7c8 1.1 12.1 2.2 12.5 3 .3 4.2-11.1 1.2-12.5-3z"></path><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" fill="#EDEDED" fill-opacity=".603" d="M49.8 10.8c-6.9 7.7-14.4 21.8-18.2 29.7-1 6.5-.5 15.7.6 23.5.9-18.2 7.5-39.2 17.6-53.2z"></path>
    </svg>
    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 128 128">
      <path fill="#fd4f00" d="m48.067 81.275-1.006-.183c-7.145-1.329-11.66-5.65-13.797-12.447-1.337-4.237 1.087-7.355 5.53-7.56 3.637-.17 6.129 1.922 8.33 4.355 2.839 3.135 5.44 6.486 8.228 9.67 4.014 4.583 8.744 7.534 15.215 6.623 5.801-.816 10.86-3.144 15.258-6.977.661-.576 1.387-1.079 2.085-1.615l-.44-.518c-3.694 1.15-7.46 1.533-11.31 1.34-5.823-.292-11.373-1.51-16.338-4.706-4.531-2.918-7.873-6.828-9.46-12.05-1.283-4.22 1.34-7.171 5.715-6.561 1.727.242 3.181 1.02 4.489 2.122 1.062.9 2.083 1.85 3.167 2.722 5.104 4.102 12.235 4.33 18.71-.124-10.648-.048-17.893-5.907-24.256-13.33-2.49-2.905-4.921-5.861-7.464-8.722-4.919-5.533-10.375-10.407-17.844-12.072-9.548-2.122-18.762-.732-27.606 3.316-1.763.807-3.456 1.748-5.273 3.26.9 0 1.39.01 1.88 0 4.46-.117 7.802 1.864 10.212 5.512 1.754 2.655 2.58 5.657 3.21 8.745.935 4.584.45 9.255.991 13.861 1.387 11.837 7.437 20.097 18.701 24.327 4.132 1.552 8.368 2.068 13.072 1.01zm-28.471-54c-1.779.448-3.201-.27-4.666-1.753 2.51-.625 4.724-.868 7.103-.963-.195 1.546-1.107 2.38-2.435 2.716zm58.332 69.126c-.155-1.141-1.13-1.643-1.896-2.238-3.384-2.636-7.345-3.57-11.543-3.646-2.506-.047-4.986-.233-7.347-1.112-1.084-.4-2.298-.92-2.268-2.318.027-1.422 1.263-1.823 2.388-2.159.92-.272 1.87-.45 2.917-.695-2.661-1.706-5.261-1.941-8.726-.547-5.456 2.19-10.833 1.932-16.27-.03-3.07-1.11-5.795-2.85-8.63-4.39l-.078.055a5.395 5.395 0 0 0 .072-.054c-.07-.213-.195-.219-.359-.098l.222.195c2.351 3.855 5.53 6.957 9.121 9.608 6.914 5.103 14.465 8.148 23.302 6.798a121.601 121.601 0 0 1 8.608-1.008c3.61-.292 7.047.726 10.487 1.639zm-16.66-55.31c-.192-.138-.376-.484-.767-.126 3.181 4.302 7.264 7.47 12.182 9.466 7.936 3.221 15.991 3.773 24.23.93 6.397-2.206 10.995-.051 13.384 6.16.346-7.209-3.896-12.462-10.65-13.49-3.8-.58-7.31.68-10.867 1.713-9.905 2.872-19.112 1.455-27.513-4.653zm49.367 28.116c1.29.107 2.582.224 3.872.337-2.916-2.56-6.47-2.765-10.067-2.56-5.473.31-9.417 3.47-13.014 7.24-3.17 3.326-6.034 7.055-10.76 8.392.08.142.1.214.122.214.636.009 1.272.038 1.907.009 6.868-.31 13.338-1.759 18.483-6.744 1.622-1.568 3.07-3.311 4.636-4.94 1.306-1.36 2.887-2.113 4.821-1.95zm-15.954-8.512c-5.125.449-9.576 2.568-13.757 5.364-3.22 2.15-6.66 3.168-10.529 2.497-.68-.12-1.366-.208-2.049-.31l-.023.284c.246.128.483.275.738.378.645.255 1.28.562 1.95.72 7.442 1.77 14.568.864 20.991-3.286 4.049-2.616 8.24-3.112 12.783-2.436.46.07.917.151 1.378.196.426.04.872.463 1.449.005-3.971-2.869-8.25-3.82-12.931-3.412zM76.366 43.298c2.688.093 5.364-.26 8.177-1.93-.825.072-1.172.072-1.508.138-3.875.772-7.351-.073-10.45-2.521-1.135-.898-2.29-1.775-3.442-2.656-4.563-3.488-9.797-4.656-15.52-4.556.091.28.1.474.198.574 6.229 6.297 13.435 10.637 22.545 10.95zm45.07 32.319c-3.853-3.823-9.026-4.314-13.812-.979 3.168.141 5.546 1.152 7.474 3.15a23.695 23.695 0 0 0 2.155 2.015c2.917 2.352 7.858 2.465 10.747.282-3.392-1.323-3.392-1.323-6.563-4.468zm-38.384 29.272c-3.386-6.306-9.079-7.728-15.657-7.305a17.62 17.62 0 0 1 5.426 2.534c1.532 1.068 2.82 2.388 4.09 3.745 2.514 2.685 6.44 4.33 9.043 3.774-1.195-.751-2.257-1.547-2.902-2.748zm31.516-35.215c0-.042.001-.081.004-.124l-.01.011.01-.01-.065-.008.038.032.022.097zM78.114 96.55a13.871 13.871 0 0 0-.132-.076.232.232 0 0 0 .027.079c.01.015.07 0 .106-.003zm-.132-.076-.015-.061-.015.018.015-.018-.04-.01.01.046.043.025z"></path>
    </svg>
    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 54 33">
      <g clip-path="url(#prefix__clip0)">
        <path fill="#38bdf8" fill-rule="evenodd" d="M27 0c-7.2 0-11.7 3.6-13.5 10.8 2.7-3.6 5.85-4.95 9.45-4.05 2.054.513 3.522 2.004 5.147 3.653C30.744 13.09 33.808 16.2 40.5 16.2c7.2 0 11.7-3.6 13.5-10.8-2.7 3.6-5.85 4.95-9.45 4.05-2.054-.513-3.522-2.004-5.147-3.653C36.756 3.11 33.692 0 27 0zM13.5 16.2C6.3 16.2 1.8 19.8 0 27c2.7-3.6 5.85-4.95 9.45-4.05 2.054.514 3.522 2.004 5.147 3.653C17.244 29.29 20.308 32.4 27 32.4c7.2 0 11.7-3.6 13.5-10.8-2.7 3.6-5.85 4.95-9.45 4.05-2.054-.513-3.522-2.004-5.147-3.653C23.256 19.31 20.192 16.2 13.5 16.2z" clip-rule="evenodd"></path>
      </g>
      <defs>
        <clipPath id="prefix__clip0"><path fill="#fff" d="M0 0h54v32.4H0z"></path></clipPath>
      </defs>
    </svg>
  </section>

  <h2>
    <span>
  
      Use in seconds
    
</span>
    <p>
      Install the dependency, use the mix task, customise, use.
    </p>
  </h2>

  <div>
    <div>
  
  <pre before="$">    
      defp deps do
      [
      {:bloom, "~&gt; 0.0.7"},
      ]
      end
    
  </pre>
</div>
    <div>
  
  <pre before="$">    
      mix bloom.install code_snippet
    
  </pre>
</div>
  </div>

  <h2>
    <span>
  
      Avatars! Avatars!
    
</span>
    <p>
      From dicebear.fm (or your own images)
    </p>
  </h2>

  

  <h2>
    <span>
  
      Look, a bento grid Phoenix Component!
    
</span>
    <p>
      For showing off features, or just for fun.
    </p>
  </h2>

  

  <h2>
    <span>
  
      Marquee &amp; Card Components
    
</span>
    <p>
      Think social proof, showing company logos, and more.
    </p>
  </h2>
  

  <section>
    <h2>
      <span>
  
        Missing a component you want? This is Open Source!
      
</span>
    </h2>
    <a href="https://github.com/chrisgreg/bloom/issues">
      
    </a>
  </section>

  
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>