<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 14:00:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Copyright is not a moral right, it's a monetization strategy (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/Plinz/status/1740597001652461895</link>
            <guid>38803614</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 10:37:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/Plinz/status/1740597001652461895">https://twitter.com/Plinz/status/1740597001652461895</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38803614">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/Plinz/status/1740597001652461895: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why are Apple Silicon VMs so different? (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://eclecticlight.co/2023/12/29/why-are-apple-silicon-vms-so-different/</link>
            <guid>38803556</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 10:29:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://eclecticlight.co/2023/12/29/why-are-apple-silicon-vms-so-different/">https://eclecticlight.co/2023/12/29/why-are-apple-silicon-vms-so-different/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38803556">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-77454">
	
	<!-- .entry-header -->

	
		<div data-first_letter="R">
		<p>Running macOS virtual machines (VMs) on Apple silicon Macs may not seem popular, but it has long been one of Apple’s important goals. Yet, if you do use a virtualiser on an M-series Mac, you’ll know how different it is from those that virtualise macOS and other operating systems on Intel Macs. This article explains why virtualisation is so important, and how it has become so different.</p>
<p>Wind the clock back to WWDC in June 2020, when Craig Federighi announced details of what was coming in Apple silicon, and he identified three pillars to support a rich diversity of software on these new Macs: Universal apps that run on both architectures, Rosetta 2 to translate Intel code to Arm instructions, and virtualisation. At the time, before Apple had even released its Developer Transition Kit, Andreas Wendker went on to demonstrate a pre-release version of Parallels Desktop running Linux as a guest, but there was no mention at all of Windows.</p>
<p>Although the first version of macOS to run on Apple silicon, Big Sur, didn’t support the lightweight virtualisation that was to follow in Monterey, it brought what Apple termed its Virtualization Extensions, an implementation of Arm’s <a href="https://developer.arm.com/documentation/100942/0100/AArch64-virtualization?lang=en" target="_blank">AArch64 virtualization</a>.</p>
<p>In the early days of virtualisation, two distinct types were distinguished. Type 1 runs a hypervisor (the core of the virtualiser) direct on the computer’s hardware. Type 2, also known as <em>hosted,</em> runs a primary host operating system on the hardware, and hypervisors then run on top of, or in close conjunction with, that to deliver the same range of services to guest operating systems. A host operating system can run more than one hypervisor at a time, and each hypervisor in turn can run more than one guest, but ultimately all converge on the host operating system and its kernel. These are now much more common on desktop computers, and include popular products such as VMware Fusion, Parallels Desktop and Oracle VirtualBox.</p>
<p>Running unmodified guest operating systems is made simpler when there’s hardware support for a hypervisor. Those adopting that approach can use Intel’s VT-x feature set, typically with Extended Page Tables (EPT) and Unrestricted Mode, or, in the case of Arm CPUs, AArch64 virtualization. This still leaves the problem of device support, which can either be left to the virtualiser to address, or can be provided for in a higher-level virtualisation framework. Over the years, and thanks to the effort of many engineers, virtualisers running on Intel hardware including Macs have grown extensive device support, and that’s what we rely on when virtualising macOS on Intel Macs.</p>
<p>Every single hardware device in an Apple silicon chip is different from its equivalent (if there is one) in Intel Macs. Even if Apple had wanted to document them fully for external use, the engineering effort to match device support in Intel Macs would have been too costly for any third party. Thus starting with a hypervisor and expecting others to build a complete virtualiser wasn’t feasible, nor was it likely to result in the high performance that Apple and users expected. What Apple did instead was to build device support into macOS, in the form of Virtio drivers.</p>
<p>Virtio is a standard originally developed by Rusty Russell that provides an abstraction layer over I/O devices. When the guest operating system calls to open a file, for example, that’s passed to a front-end Virtio storage device para-driver, and from there into a Virtio back-end driver that interacts with the storage device. Although this might seem less efficient than traditional virtualisation, in practice it can prove far more efficient. Its most obvious advantage is that creating a virtualiser app becomes a matter of configuring and opening the required Virtio devices, and letting the guest, Virtio and the host get on with it. And that’s essentially what an app using Apple’s Virtualisation framework does.</p>
<p><span><img data-attachment-id="66331" data-permalink="https://eclecticlight.co/virtualisation1/" data-orig-file="https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg" data-orig-size="2148,1386" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="virtualisation1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg?w=940" src="https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg?w=940" alt="virtualisation1" srcset="https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg 2148w, https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=97 150w, https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=194 300w, https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=496 768w, https://eclecticlightdotcom.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/virtualisation1.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=661 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2148px) 100vw, 2148px"></span></p>
<p>Apple’s choice of Virtio was undoubtedly swayed by the fact that Linux already has good Virtio support, but at the time macOS had none. In the couple of years preceding the release of Monterey, Apple’s engineers thus set about building Virtio support into macOS, which explains why macOS lightweight virtualisation is only available on Monterey and later hosts, and when running Monterey and later guests. As implemented in macOS (both as guest and host), there are also extensions to support keyboard and pointing devices, a shared clipboard (‘Spice’), and high-performance graphics with Metal and GPU support.</p>
<p>In the Virtio model, providing such support is the task of the operating system, not the virtualiser. For vendors like VMware and Parallels this reduces not only the cost of development, but also the commercial value of their products; there’s no scope for either of them to engineer better or faster graphics support, as that’s determined by features provided in both guest and host operating systems, via Virtio or an equivalent. That puts Apple in charge of what hardware and features are supported by virtualisation on Apple silicon, and the difficulties that have arisen over Apple ID access for VMs.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it guarantees optimum performance in VMs. Not only is their CPU and GPU code run direct on the hardware, just as in the host, but Virtio devices deliver almost as good performance as on the host.</p>
<p>The reward for Apple is flexibility in the future of macOS. Running older versions of macOS in a VM enables users to run Intel-only apps long after Rosetta 2 support is dropped from the current macOS, and for newer Apple silicon Macs to run software that’s incompatible with their minimum version of macOS. Using either Linux or macOS, developers can distribute Docker-like lightweight VM packages, something already done by Cirrus Labs’ <a href="https://tart.run/" target="_blank">Tart</a>.</p>
<p>Virtualisation may seem to be a minority pursuit just now. That’s likely to change over the coming few years, thanks to lightweight virtualisation and Virtio.</p>
<p><strong>Further reading</strong></p>
<p>Edouard Bugnion, Jason Nieh, Dan Tsafrir (2017) <em>Hardware and Software Support for Virtualization,</em> Morgan &amp; Claypool. ISBN 978 1 62705 693 9. Bugnion was a co-founder of VMware.</p>
	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	
	<!-- .entry-footer -->

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: What are good books/blogs to read for a first time CTO (188 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38803092</link>
            <guid>38803092</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 09:18:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38803092">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="38803405"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803405" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803405&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Depends a lot on your situation:<p>Does "CTO" mean you are the tech lead of a small (single team) engineering organization? Then everything written for staff engineers applies. E.g I've heard good things about "Staff engineer's path" by Tanya Reilly.</p><p>Does "CTO" mean you are leading an org that is too large to be hands-on with tech, and need to build an effective structure and culture? Then I second the recommendation for "an elegant puzzle" by Will Larson.</p><p>Or does "CTO" mean that you switched from being an engineer to managing a team of engineers? Then everything for new managers applies, for starters I'd recommend "Becoming an effective software engineering manager" by James Stanier, or "Engineering management for the rest of us" by Sarah Drasner.</p><p>For some good general material, I'd also recommend the resources that Gergely Orosz makes available for subscribers to his "pragmatic engineer" newsletter. Those are templates for the kind of documents and processes you will most likely need - if you're new to the role, you will not go too wrong by using them, and if you want to create your own they are excellent starting points.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="38803697"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803697" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803697&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>And maybe CTO means “the founding programmer of a new startup” in which case my advice would be to stop reading and start coding :-)</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="38804026"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38804026" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38804026&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>And honestly, pre product-market fit my advice would be not even coding, but iterating in an extremely scrappy way (read: Google Sheets, Jupyter Notebooks, no-/low code, handwritten invoices) until you have people paying for your product and not churning after the first month. Everything else comes secondary. For every company that didn‘t manage to scale their tech and teams fast enough, there‘s 100 that die by „building and they will come“ a polished app with great UX through 4 ecosystems that get launched to deafening silence.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803966"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="38803972"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803972" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803972&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I was CTO of a startup from pre-seed stage ($0 raised, bootstrapping) thru Series A + B stages ($millions raised, scaling). I then promoted a senior engineer to the CTO role, around the time that we had ~20-30 engineers organized into sub-teams with engineering leads. As part of that, I ran an engineering management book club internally for the new CTO and engineering leads (which was also open to any engineers to join). I then published that reading list as a neatly organized blog post.<p>The team wrote web / SaaS / analytics software in Python and JavaScript, deployed on Linux + AWS, using lightweight planning tools like GitHub and Notion. It was also a fully distributed team long before the pandemic. Over time, the company (Parse.ly) gained hundreds of enterprise customers and established itself via profitable growth in a straightforward SaaS business model. In 2021, less than a year after this blog post was published, the company was acquired by one of the largest open web internet companies (Automattic, creators of WordPress.com).</p><p>"Managing software teams: the definitive reading list"</p><p><a href="https://amontalenti.com/2020/11/28/definitive-reading-list" rel="nofollow">https://amontalenti.com/2020/11/28/definitive-reading-list</a></p><p>The blog post is organized into a few sections, each featuring a few relevant books:</p><p>- Management as a high-leverage activity</p><p>- Product marketing and product management</p><p>- Debugging dysfunctional product cultures</p><p>- The psychology of deep work</p><p>- Fully distributed teams</p><p>- Programmer mindset and philosophy</p><p>It's easy to skip around to find a good starting point or make your own (smaller) reading list. Hope that helps. Good luck!
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803901"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803901" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803901&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I've been a CTO a couple of times (VMware, startup), I don't think I'm a good one (I am better as an individual contributor, rather than as a manager), but I have one piece of advice for you: ignore books, or use them as secondary source of truth.<p>You should instead TALK to long-time or former CTOs and ask them for advice. You won't find that advice in any book. It's invaluable.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803795"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803616"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803616" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803616&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Whichever books you read - some great suggestions in the comments so far - please treat them as advice, and not religious texts.<p>So many managers and higher fail terribly at being effective because they believe all they need to do is encourage/enforce the practices in the books on the engineering teams, and that is the path to failure and the death of morale.</p><p>Take the books as guidance, but listen and engage with your reports (and their reports) to find the problems that need to be solved. Don't dictate or drive people, let them use their expertise in the direction you lead.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="38803663"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803663" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803663&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>People are notoriously bad at identifying what actually led to their success. Career advice authors even more so.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="38803987"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803987" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803987&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>For a startup, focus on shipping faster. The only thing that matters in a startup is finding the product market fit.<p>If you don’t get to this point, the startup will die. So spending time optimizing the performance or arguing which code formatting standards to follow is just a waste of time and resources.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803277"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803771"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803771" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803771&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>At a startup phase, I'm not sure there is anything that is strictly speaking a "CTO" task, except the paperwork. And once you get big enough for it to matter, the same rule applies as for a CEO: the CxO you need for your first million is a different one you need for your 100 million and different yet again for your first billion.<p>There is of course a GitHub list for this: <a href="https://github.com/kuchin/awesome-cto">https://github.com/kuchin/awesome-cto</a> and perhaps the best way to find out what you need is to check things off of that list that don't actually have anything to do with what you're actually working on. Role names generally have very little meaning on their own, it's all about context.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803938"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803530"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803530" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803530&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>If this is the first time you'd to be responsible for budgets, working with the board, finance teams, HR, etc, then I'd recommend a general business management book like "The Personal MBA" to give you an introduction to the concepts and language that those teams will use.<p>The Personal MBA: A World-Class Business Education in a Single Volume <a href="https://amzn.eu/d/dTAp1GF" rel="nofollow">https://amzn.eu/d/dTAp1GF</a>
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803334"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803288"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803288" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803288&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>If it's just a "planning my first startup" stage and not an existing enterprise of some non-zero size, I'd suggest starting from the book "The Lean Startup" by Eric Ries and other general "startup mentality" information sources. For a tech-minded CTO, it's especially important to have that correct "startup mentality" to avoid big mistakes from the start.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803778"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803778" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803778&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>You need to book communication and/or good sales course. As CTO you’re into politics, not into tech. Ability to communicate clearly and steer the conversation is your skill number one. Tech background is nice to have, but not really useful. You will hire people for that.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803858"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803858" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803858&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The effective manager - how to manage people<p>The mom test - how to discover product</p><p>The EOS (Traction and Co) - how to manage the company and give direction to the vision of the company
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803723"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803723" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803723&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Technical founders are not CTOs. At least, not for a long time. A CTO role defines the strategic vision for the org. You'll have a vague idea of that as a founder but until you nail the product and where it fits in a market it won't really matter too much. Focus on executing and getting traction instead.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803560"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803328"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803797"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803416"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803416" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803416&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>As a CTO you'll work a lot with people, the best resource you can get is related to people.<p>Get a mentor, read books about dealing with people in the most optimal way for you and the business (closing deals, negotiation, psychology etc).</p><p>Also learn how to develop people. There are a few books on this, but nothing beats experience and being reflective about it. Every situation is specific and it's up to you to strategize how to develop people in your team, finding out what are the right buttons to push.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803719"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803280"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803574"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803574" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803574&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I would suggest reading 2-3 books from your tech domain, I mean the tech stack your startup will be using, and maybe 2-3 more about your niche (for example if you are in online advertising, read books about advertising in general and online in particular)</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803667"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803667" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803667&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>On a side note, when I had my startup and was the CTO, a lot of advice I got and also what I ended up realising was that my priority and goal was to build an amazing `Tech Team`.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803622"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803355"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803355" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803355&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Assumming you have worked as software engineer I recommend to talk with other CTOs, product people, and/or senior engineers (peer groups) and have concrete problems you would like to solve in mind.<p>What kind of startup you want to build and in what field? Knowing more details about the challenges you will face help to narrow the focus to specific knowledge and skills.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803850"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803738"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803566"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="38803884"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="38803314"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803489"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_38803489" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38803489&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38803092"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Given that you have provided no information about your industry, the size of your company or team, your background, or any relevant information that could be used to help, literally any book could be a good fit for you.<p>Your best bet is to see if your company is willing to pay for you to take some Dale Carnegie classes (Specifically the ones on Effective Communication). It will help you more than anything technical.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803573"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="38803305"><td></td></tr>
            </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[40% of US electricity is now emissions-free (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2023/12/40-of-us-electricity-is-now-emissions-free/</link>
            <guid>38802152</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 05:57:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2023/12/40-of-us-electricity-is-now-emissions-free/">https://arstechnica.com/science/2023/12/40-of-us-electricity-is-now-emissions-free/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38802152">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <h4>
      Decarbonizing, but slowly    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">Good news as natural gas, coal, and solar see the biggest changes.</h2>
                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/GettyImages-1414366794-800x533.jpg" alt="Image of electric power lines with a power plant cooling tower in the background.">
      <figcaption></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 353:single/related:5b9a036a34fed5756a2f33fdf9114d1c --><!-- empty -->
<p>Just before the holiday break, the US Energy Information Agency released data on the country's electrical generation. Because of delays in reporting, the monthly data runs through October, so it doesn't provide a complete picture of the changes we've seen in 2023. But some of the trends now seem locked in for the year: wind and solar are likely to be in a dead heat with coal, and all carbon-emissions-free sources combined will account for roughly 40 percent of US electricity production.</p>
<h2>Tracking trends</h2>
<p>Having data through October necessarily provides an incomplete picture of 2023. There are several factors that can cause the later months of the year to differ from the earlier ones. Some forms of generation are seasonal—notably solar, which has its highest production over the summer months. Weather can also play a role, as unusually high demand for heating in the winter months could potentially require that older fossil fuel plants be brought online. It also influences production from hydroelectric plants, creating lots of year-to-year variation.</p>
<p>Finally, everything's taking place against a backdrop of booming construction of solar and natural gas. So, it's entirely possible that we will have built enough new solar over the course of the year to offset the seasonal decline at the end of the year.</p>
<p>Let's look at the year-to-date data to get a sense of the trends and where things stand. We'll then check the monthly data for October to see if any of those trends show indications of reversing.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>The most important takeaway is that energy use is largely flat. Overall electricity production year-to-date is down by just over one percent from 2022, though demand was higher this October compared to last year. This is in keeping with a general trend of flat-to-declining electricity use as greater efficiency is offsetting factors like population growth and expanding electrification.</p>
<p>That's important because it means that any newly added capacity will displace the use of existing facilities. And, at the moment, that displacement is happening to coal.</p>
<h2>Can’t hide the decline</h2>
<p>At this point last year, coal had produced nearly 20 percent of the electricity in the US. This year, it's down to 16.2 percent, and only accounts for 15.5 percent of October's production. Wind and solar combined are presently at 16 percent of year-to-date production, meaning they're likely to be in a dead heat with coal this year and easily surpass it next year.</p>
<p>Year-to-date, wind is largely unchanged since 2022, accounting for about 10 percent of total generation, and it's up to over 11 percent in the October data, so that's unlikely to change much by the end of the year. Solar has seen a significant change, going from five to six percent of the total electricity production (this figure includes both utility-scale generation and the EIA's estimate of residential production). And it's largely unchanged in October alone, suggesting that new construction is offsetting some of the seasonal decline.</p>
<figure><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/2023-emissions.png" data-height="1536" data-width="2048" alt="Coal is being squeezed out by natural gas, with an assist from renewables."><img alt="Coal is being squeezed out by natural gas, with an assist from renewables." src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/2023-emissions-640x480.png" width="640" height="480" srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/2023-emissions-1280x960.png 2x"></a><figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/2023-emissions.png" data-height="1536" data-width="2048">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Coal is being squeezed out by natural gas, with an assist from renewables.</p><p>Eric Bangeman/Ars Technica</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>Hydroelectric production has dropped by about six percent since last year, causing it to slip from 6.1 percent to 5.8 percent of the total production. Depending on the next couple of months, that may allow solar to pass hydro on the list of renewables.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>Combined, the three major renewables account for about 22 percent of year-to-date electricity generation, up about 0.5 percent since last year. They're up by even more in the October data, placing them well ahead of both nuclear and coal.</p>
<p>Nuclear itself is largely unchanged, allowing it to pass coal thanks to the latter's decline. Its output has been boosted by a new, 1.1 Gigawatt reactor that come online this year (a second at the same site, Vogtle in Georgia, is set to start commercial production at any moment). But that's likely to be the end of new nuclear capacity for this decade; the challenge will be keeping existing plants open despite their age and high costs.</p>
<p>If we combine nuclear and renewables under the umbrella of carbon-free generation, then that's up by nearly 1 percent since 2022 and is likely to surpass 40 percent for the first time.</p>
<p>The only thing that's keeping carbon-free power from growing faster is natural gas, which is the fastest-growing source of generation at the moment, going from 40 percent of the year-to-date total in 2022 to 43.3 percent this year. (It's actually slightly below that level in the October data.) The explosive growth of natural gas in the US has been a big environmental win, since it creates the least particulate pollution of all the fossil fuels, as well as the lowest carbon emissions per unit of electricity. But its use is going to need to start dropping soon if the US is to meet its climate goals, so it will be critical to see whether its growth flat lines over the next few years.</p>
<p>Outside of natural gas, however, all the trends in US generation are good, especially considering that the rise of renewable production would have seemed like an impossibility a decade ago. Unfortunately, the pace is currently too slow for the US to have a net-zero electric grid by the end of the decade.</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ideal Monitor Rotation for Programmers (2021) (299 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sprocketfox.io/xssfox/2021/12/02/xrandr/</link>
            <guid>38802086</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 05:39:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sprocketfox.io/xssfox/2021/12/02/xrandr/">https://sprocketfox.io/xssfox/2021/12/02/xrandr/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38802086">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
      
  <figure>
    <img src="https://sprocketfox.io/xssfox/images/PXL_20211202_033906006.jpg" alt="Monitor in landscape mode">
    <figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>It all started with this toot from <a href="https://cloudisland.nz/web/accounts/1">Aurynn</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>do I just need to put one screen in portrait mode?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the past I had experimented with using portrait displays for reading and programming. The ability to display large amount of text is certainly appealing.</p>
<h3 id="boring">Boring</h3>
<figure>
    <img src="https://sprocketfox.io/xssfox/images/PXL_20211202_034116753.jpg" alt="Monitor in portrait mode">
    <figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>But is this the most optimal display for software development? Lets evaluate</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Rotation</th>
<th>Advantages</th>
<th>Disadvantages</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0°</td>
<td>Works with most applications. Video content is usually in wide format</td>
<td>Websites and documents usually end up with a lot of whitespace and padding around them</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>90°</td>
<td>Great for text documents - can read down like a book page</td>
<td>Movies don’t display well. Viewing angle problems</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Here you might think we might done. But there are soooooo many more angles we can try. This is a little tricky on macOS and Windows but on Linux we have all the freedom we need.</p>
<h3 id="odd-but-ok">Odd but ok.</h3>
<p>We have a little tool called <code>xrandr</code> (x resize and rotate). We can use it to rotate the screen around to any angle we want. In practice I couldn’t get this to work on my MacBook. My desktop on the otherhand it had no problems. So lets try a few out.</p>
<figure>
    <img src="https://sprocketfox.io/xssfox/images/PXL_20211202_034333303.jpg" alt="Monitor with a 1 degree rotation">
    <figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>
<blockquote>
<p>1° - notice the menu bar disappearing to the right</p>
</blockquote>
<figure>
    <img src="https://sprocketfox.io/xssfox/images/PXL_20211202_034744788.jpg" alt="Monitor with a 45 degree rotation">
    <figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>
<blockquote>
<p>45° - I run out of space</p>
</blockquote>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Rotation</th>
<th>Advantages</th>
<th>Disadvantages</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1°</td>
<td>Handy if your desk is on a slight slope</td>
<td>fonts render a little weird</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45°</td>
<td>Middle ground between vertical and horizontal</td>
<td>doesn’t fit well with non square aspect ratios</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>One neat thing about 45° is that it gives us pretty close to the diagonal. But not on my ultra wide. Due to maths, the amount we’d need to rotate is based on the angle of a triangle which match the aspect ration of the screen we are using. This ends up being about 22° for a 21:9 ratio.</p>
<h3 id="the-perfect-rotation">The perfect rotation</h3>
<figure>
    <img src="https://sprocketfox.io/xssfox/images/PXL_20211202_035205492.jpg" alt="Monitor with a 22 degree rotation">
    <figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>
<blockquote>
<p>22° - Perfect</p>
</blockquote>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Rotation</th>
<th>Advantages</th>
<th>Disadvantages</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>22°</td>
<td>Longest line length!</td>
<td>Webcam starts sliding away</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>So this here I think is the best monitor orientation for software development. It provides the longest line lengths and no longer need to worry about that pesky 80 column limit.</p>
<h3 id="how-do-i-do-this">How do I do this?</h3>
<p>First off, I could only get this to work in xorg - no wayland support yet. <code>xrandr --output HDMI-3 --transform lots of numbers here</code> takes a transformation matrix thats used to position the screen. We can use that to rotate the display.</p>
<p>The basic syntax that we need for rotating and shifting is this</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>cos(x),-sin(x),shift_left,sin(x),cos(x),shift_up,0,0,1
</code></pre><p>Some examples</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="sh"><span><span><span># these won't shift / center the display as I don't know the resolution</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>#-0.1</span>
</span></span><span><span>xrandr --output HDMI-3 --transform 0.999998476913288,0.00174532836589831,0,-0.00174532836589831,0.999998476913288,0,0,0,1
</span></span><span><span><span>#1</span>
</span></span><span><span>xrandr --output HDMI-3 --transform 0.999847695156391,-0.0174524064372835,0,0.0174524064372835,0.999847695156391,0,0,0,1
</span></span><span><span><span>#45</span>
</span></span><span><span>xrandr --output HDMI-3 --transform 0.707106781186548,-0.707106781186548,0,0.707106781186548,0.707106781186548,0,0,0,1
</span></span><span><span><span>#22</span>
</span></span><span><span>xrandr --output HDMI-3 --transform 0.927183854566787,-0.374606593415912,0,0.374606593415912,0.927183854566787,0,0,0,1
</span></span></code></pre></div><h4 id="calculator">Calculator</h4>
<p>This little javascript calculator should generate the xrandr command for given inputs</p>


<p>Enjoy.</p>




      
        
      
    </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[U.S. Government Database of Dad Jokes (272 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fatherhood.gov:443/for-dads/dad-jokes</link>
            <guid>38800458</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:31:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fatherhood.gov:443/for-dads/dad-jokes">https://fatherhood.gov:443/for-dads/dad-jokes</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38800458">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://fatherhood.gov:443/for-dads/dad-jokes: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vim users are encouraged to make a donation to ICCF (145 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vimhelp.org/uganda.txt.html</link>
            <guid>38799897</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 23:09:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vimhelp.org/uganda.txt.html">https://vimhelp.org/uganda.txt.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38799897">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="vh-content">
<pre><span id="uganda.txt">uganda.txt</span>    For <span>Vim version 9.0.</span>  Last change: 2022 Mar 02


		  <span>VIM REFERENCE MANUAL    by Bram Moolenaar</span>


			<span id="uganda">uganda</span> <span id="Uganda">Uganda</span> <span id="copying">copying</span> <span id="copyright">copyright</span> <span id="license">license</span>
<span>SUMMARY</span><span id="_summary"></span>
								<span id="iccf">iccf</span> <span id="ICCF">ICCF</span>
Vim <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> Charityware.  You can use and copy <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> much <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> you like, but you are
encouraged to make <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> donation for needy children in Uganda.  Please see <a href="#kcc">kcc</a>
below or visit the <a href="#ICCF">ICCF</a> web site, available <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> these URLs:

	<a href="https://iccf-holland.org/">https://iccf-holland.org/</a>
	<a href="https://www.vim.org/iccf/">https://www.vim.org/iccf/</a>
	<a href="https://www.iccf.nl/">https://www.iccf.nl/</a>

You can also <a href="https://vimhelp.org/sponsor.txt.html#sponsor">sponsor</a> the <a href="https://vimhelp.org/develop.txt.html#development">development</a> of Vim.  Vim sponsors can vote for
features.  See <a href="https://vimhelp.org/sponsor.txt.html#sponsor">sponsor</a><a href="https://vimhelp.org/repeat.txt.html#.">.</a>  The money goes to <a href="#Uganda">Uganda</a> anyway.

The Open Publication License applies to the Vim documentation, see
<a href="https://vimhelp.org/usr_01.txt.html#manual-copyright">manual-copyright</a><a href="https://vimhelp.org/repeat.txt.html#.">.</a>

<span>=== begin of license ===</span>

<span>VIM LICENSE</span><span id="_vim-license"></span>

I)  There are no restrictions on distributing unmodified copies of Vim except
    that they <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> include this <a href="#license">license</a> text.  You can also distribute
    unmodified parts of Vim, likewise unrestricted except that they <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a>
    include this <a href="#license">license</a> text.  You are also allowed to include executables
    that you made from the unmodified Vim sources, plus your own usage
    examples and Vim scripts.

II) It <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> allowed to distribute <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> modified (or extended) version of Vim,
    including executables and/or source code, when the following four
    conditions are met:
    1) This <a href="#license">license</a> text <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> be included unmodified.
    2) The modified Vim <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> be distributed in one of the following five ways:
       <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#a%29">a)</a> If you make changes to Vim yourself, you <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> clearly describe in
	  the <a href="https://vimhelp.org/intro.txt.html#distribution">distribution</a> how to contact you.  When the maintainer asks you
	  (in any way) for <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> copy of the modified Vim you distributed, you
	  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> make your changes, including source code, available to the
	  maintainer without fee.  The maintainer reserves the right to
	  include your changes in the official version of Vim.  What the
	  maintainer will <a href="https://vimhelp.org/diff.txt.html#do">do</a> with your changes and under what <a href="#license">license</a> they
	  will be distributed <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> negotiable.  If there has been no negotiation
	  then this license, or <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> later version, also applies to your changes.
	  The current maintainers are listed here: <a href="https://github.com/orgs/vim/people">https://github.com/orgs/vim/people</a>.
	  If this changes <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> will be announced in appropriate places (most likely
	  vim.sf.net, www.vim.org and/or comp.editors).  When <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> completely
	  impossible to contact the maintainer, the obligation to send him
	  your changes ceases.  Once the maintainer has confirmed that he has
	  received your changes they will not have to be sent again.
       b) If you have received <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> modified Vim that was distributed <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a>
	  mentioned under <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#a%29">a)</a> you are allowed to further distribute <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a>
	  unmodified, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> mentioned <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> I).  If you make additional changes the
	  text under <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#a%29">a)</a> applies to those changes.
       c) Provide all the changes, including source code, with every copy of
	  the modified Vim you distribute.  This may be done in the form of <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a>
	  context diff.  You can choose what <a href="#license">license</a> to use for new code you
	  add.  The changes and their <a href="#license">license</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> not restrict others from
	  making their own changes to the official version of Vim.
       d) When you have <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> modified Vim which includes changes <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> mentioned
	  under c), you can distribute <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> without the source code for the
	  changes if the following three conditions are met:
	  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> The <a href="#license">license</a> that applies to the changes permits you to distribute
	    the changes to the Vim maintainer without fee or restriction, and
	    permits the Vim maintainer to include the changes in the official
	    version of Vim without fee or restriction.
	  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> You keep the changes for <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> least three years after last
	    distributing the corresponding modified Vim.  When the maintainer
	    or someone who you distributed the modified Vim to asks you (in
	    any way) for the changes within this period, you <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> make them
	    available to him.
	  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> You clearly describe in the <a href="https://vimhelp.org/intro.txt.html#distribution">distribution</a> how to contact you.  This
	    contact information <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> remain valid for <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> least three years
	    after last distributing the corresponding modified Vim, or <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> long
	    <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> possible.
       e) When the GNU General Public License (GPL) applies to the changes,
	  you can distribute the modified Vim under the GNU GPL version 2 or
	  any later version.
    3) <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#A">A</a> message <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> be added, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> least in the output of the "<a href="https://vimhelp.org/various.txt.html#%3Aversion">:version</a>"
       command and in the <a href="https://vimhelp.org/intro.txt.html#intro">intro</a> screen, such that the user of the modified Vim
       <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> able to see that <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> was modified.  When distributing <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> mentioned
       under 2)e) adding the message <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> only required for <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> far <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> this does
       not conflict with the <a href="#license">license</a> used for the changes.
    4) The contact information <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> required under 2)a) and 2)d) <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> not be
       removed or changed, except that the person himself can make
       corrections.

III) If you distribute <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> modified version of Vim, you are encouraged to use
     the Vim <a href="#license">license</a> for your changes and make them available to the
     maintainer, including the source code.  The preferred way to <a href="https://vimhelp.org/diff.txt.html#do">do</a> this <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a>
     by e-mail or by uploading the files to <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> server and e-mailing the URL.
     If the number of changes <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> small (e.g., <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> modified Makefile) e-mailing <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a>
     context <a href="https://vimhelp.org/diff.txt.html#diff">diff</a> will do.  The e-mail address to be used <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a>
     &lt;maintainer@vim.org&gt;

IV)  It <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> not allowed to remove this <a href="#license">license</a> from the <a href="https://vimhelp.org/intro.txt.html#distribution">distribution</a> of the Vim
     sources, parts of <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> or from <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> modified version.  You may use this
     <a href="#license">license</a> for previous Vim releases instead of the <a href="#license">license</a> that they came
     with, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> your option.

<span>=== end of license ===</span>

<span id="_note"><span>Note:</span></span>

<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> If you are happy with Vim, please express that by reading the rest of this
  file and consider helping needy children in Uganda.

<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> If you want to support further Vim <a href="https://vimhelp.org/develop.txt.html#development">development</a> consider becoming <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a>
  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/sponsor.txt.html#sponsor">sponsor</a><a href="https://vimhelp.org/repeat.txt.html#.">.</a>  The money goes to <a href="#Uganda">Uganda</a> anyway.

<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> According to Richard Stallman the Vim <a href="#license">license</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> GNU GPL compatible.
  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#A">A</a> few minor changes have been made since he checked it, but that should not
  make <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> difference.

<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> If you link Vim with <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> library that goes under the GNU GPL, this <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vi_diff.txt.html#limits">limits</a>
  further <a href="https://vimhelp.org/intro.txt.html#distribution">distribution</a> to the GNU GPL.  Also when you didn't actually change
  anything in Vim.

<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> Once <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> change <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> included that goes under the GNU GPL, this forces all
  further changes to also be made under the GNU GPL or <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> compatible license.

<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#-">-</a> If you distribute <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> modified version of Vim, you can include your name and
  contact information with the "--with-modified-by" configure argument or the
  MODIFIED_BY define.

<span>==============================================================================</span>
<a href="#Kibaale">Kibaale</a> Children's Centre		<span id="kcc">kcc</span> <span id="Kibaale">Kibaale</span>  <span id="charity">charity</span>

<a href="#Kibaale">Kibaale</a> Children's Centre (KCC) <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> located in Kibaale, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> small town in the
south of Uganda, near Tanzania, in East Africa.  The area <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> known <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> Rakai
District.  The population <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> mostly farmers.  Although people are poor, there
usually <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> enough food.  But this district <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> suffering from AIDS more than
any other part of the world.  Some say that <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> started there.  Estimations are
that in the past 10 to 30% of the Ugandans are infected with HIV.  Because
parents die, there are many orphans.  In this district about 60,000 children
have lost one or both parents, out of <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> population of 350,000.  Although AIDS
<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> now mostly under control, the problems are still continuing.

The children need <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> lot of help.  The KCC <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> working hard to provide the needy
with food, medical care and education.  Food and medical care to keep them
healthy now, and education so that they can take care of themselves in the
future.  KCC works on <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> Christian base, but <a href="https://vimhelp.org/helphelp.txt.html#help">help</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> given to children of any
religion.

The key to solving the problems in this area <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> education.  This has been
neglected in the past years with president Idi Amin and the following civil
wars.  Now that the government <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> stable again, the children and parents have
to learn how to take care of themselves and how to avoid infections.  There <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a>
also <a href="https://vimhelp.org/helphelp.txt.html#help">help</a> for people who are ill and hungry, but the primary goal <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> to
prevent people from getting ill and to teach them how to grow healthy food.

Most of the orphans are living in an extended family.  An uncle or older
sister <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> taking care of them.  Because these families are big and the income
(if any) <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> low, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> child <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> lucky if <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> gets healthy food.  Clothes, medical
care and schooling <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> beyond its reach.  To <a href="https://vimhelp.org/helphelp.txt.html#help">help</a> these needy children, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a>
sponsorship program was <a href="https://vimhelp.org/change.txt.html#put">put</a> into place.  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#A">A</a> child can be financially adopted.
For <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> few dollars <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> month KCC sees to <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> that the child gets indispensable
items, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> healthy, goes to school and KCC takes care of anything else that
needs to be done for the child and the family that supports it.

Besides helping the child directly, the environment where the child grows up
needs to be improved.  KCC helps schools to improve their teaching methods.
There <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> demonstration school <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> the centre and teacher trainings are given.
Health workers are being trained, hygiene education <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> carried out and
households are stimulated to build <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> proper latrine.  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> helped setting up <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a>
production site for cement slabs.  These are used to build <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> good latrine.
They are sold below cost price.

There <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> clinic <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> the project, which provides children and their family
medical help.  Since 2020 <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> maternity ward was added and 24/7 service <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a>
available.  When needed, transport to <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> hospital <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> offered.  Immunization
programs are carried out and <a href="https://vimhelp.org/helphelp.txt.html#help">help</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> provided when an epidemic <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> breaking out
(measles and cholera have been <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> problem).
							<span id="donate">donate</span>
Summer 1994 to summer 1995 <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> spent <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> whole year <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> the centre, working <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a>
volunteer.  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> have helped to expand the centre and worked in the area of water
and sanitation.  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> learned that the <a href="https://vimhelp.org/helphelp.txt.html#help">help</a> that the KCC provides really helps.
When <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> came back to Holland, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> wanted to continue supporting KCC.  To <a href="https://vimhelp.org/diff.txt.html#do">do</a> this
I'm raising funds and organizing the sponsorship program.  Please consider one
of these possibilities:

1.  Sponsor <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> child in primary school: 17 <a href="https://vimhelp.org/digraph.txt.html#euro">euro</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> month (or more).
2.  Sponsor <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> child in secondary school: 25 <a href="https://vimhelp.org/digraph.txt.html#euro">euro</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> month (or more).
3.  Sponsor the clinic: Any amount <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> month or quarter
4.  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#A">A</a> one-time donation

Compared with other organizations that <a href="https://vimhelp.org/diff.txt.html#do">do</a> child sponsorship the amounts are
very low.  This <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> because the money goes directly to the centre.  Less than
5% <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> used for administration.  This <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> possible because this <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> small
organization that works with volunteers.  If you would like to <a href="https://vimhelp.org/sponsor.txt.html#sponsor">sponsor</a> <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a>
child, you should have the intention to <a href="https://vimhelp.org/diff.txt.html#do">do</a> this for <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> least one year.

How <a href="https://vimhelp.org/diff.txt.html#do">do</a> you know that the money will be spent right?  First of all you have my
personal guarantee <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#as">as</a> the <a href="https://vimhelp.org/intro.txt.html#author">author</a> of Vim.  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> trust the people that are working
<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#at">at</a> the centre, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> know them personally.  Furthermore, the centre has been
co-sponsored and inspected by World Vision, Save the Children Fund and <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> now
under the supervision of Pacific Academy Outreach Society.  The centre <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a>
visited about once <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> year to check the progress (at our own cost).  <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> have
visited the centre myself many times, <a href="https://vimhelp.org/starting.txt.html#starting">starting</a> in 1993.  The visit reports are
on the <a href="#ICCF">ICCF</a> web site.

If you have any further questions, send me e-mail: &lt;Bram@vim.org&gt;.

The address of the centre is:
			<a href="#Kibaale">Kibaale</a> Children's Centre
			p.o. box 1658
			Masaka, Uganda, East Africa

Sending money:						<span id="iccf-donations">iccf-donations</span>

Check the <a href="#ICCF">ICCF</a> web site for the latest information!  See <a href="#iccf">iccf</a> for the URL.


USA:		The methods mentioned below can be used.
		If you <a href="https://vimhelp.org/vim_faq.txt.html#must">must</a> send <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> check send <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#it">it</a> to our Canadian partner:
		<a href="https://www.kuwasha.net/">https://www.kuwasha.net/</a>

Canada:		Contact Kuwasha in Surrey, Canada.  They take care of the
		Canadian sponsors for the children in Kibaale.  Kuwasha
		forwards 100% of the money to the project in Uganda.  You can
		send them <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> one time donation directly.
		Please send me <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> <span>note</span> so that <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#I">I</a> know what has been donated
		because of Vim.  Look on their site for information about
		sponsorship: <a href="https://www.kuwasha.net/">https://www.kuwasha.net/</a>
		If you make <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> donation to Kuwasha you will receive <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> tax
		receipt which can be submitted with your tax return.

Holland:	Transfer to the account of "Stichting <a href="#ICCF">ICCF</a> Holland" in
		Amersfoort.  This will allow for tax deduction if you live in
		Holland.  ING bank, IBAN: NL95 INGB 0004 5487 74

Germany:	It <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a> possible to make donations that allow for <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> tax return.
		Check the <a href="#ICCF">ICCF</a> web site for the latest information:
			<a href="https://iccf-holland.org/germany.html">https://iccf-holland.org/germany.html</a>

Europe:		Use <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> bank transfer if possible.  See "Others" below for the
		swift code and IBAN number.
		Any other <a href="https://vimhelp.org/eval.txt.html#method">method</a> should work.  Ask for information about
		sponsorship.

Credit Card:	You can use PayPal to send money with <a href="https://vimhelp.org/insert.txt.html#a">a</a> Credit card.  This <a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#is">is</a>
		the most widely used Internet based payment system.  It's
		really simple to use.  Use this link to find more info:
		    <a href="https://www.paypal.com/en_US/mrb/pal=XAC62PML3GF8Q">https://www.paypal.com/en_US/mrb/pal=XAC62PML3GF8Q</a>
		The e-mail address for sending the money to is:
		    Bram@iccf-holland.org

Others:		Transfer to this account if possible:
		    ING bank:	IBAN: NL95 INGB 0004 5487 74
				Swift code: INGBNL2A
		    under the name "stichting <a href="#ICCF">ICCF</a> Holland"<a href="https://vimhelp.org/motion.txt.html#%2C">,</a> Amersfoort
		Checks are not accepted.


 vim:tw=78:ts=8:noet:ft=help:norl:


</pre>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Smallest Typeface (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://luc.devroye.org/fonts-51468.html</link>
            <guid>38799686</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 22:44:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://luc.devroye.org/fonts-51468.html">http://luc.devroye.org/fonts-51468.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38799686">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<td halign="RIGHT">
<p><span color="FF3097">Anders de Flon 
</span> 
<img src="http://luc.devroye.org/AndersDeFlon-3x3-2005.gif">
<br clear="all"></p><p>Creator of the <a href="http://luc.devroye.org/AndersDeFlon-3x3-2005.gif">world's smallest typeface</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3x3">3x3</a> (2005), which has appeared on several record sleeves; a slightly modified version appears on the cover of LFO's Sheath, designed by The Designers Republic. Anders de Flon (b. 1983, Stockholm, Sweden) is a Swedish creative advisor, graphic designer and industrial designer known for his minimalistic and experimental work. Founder of Deflon, a Creative&amp;Advising venture, based in Stockholm.
</p></td>
<td>
<div>
<p><span>EXTERNAL LINKS</span><br>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anders_de_Flon">Anders de Flon</a><br>
<a href="https://www.myfonts.com/search/+Anders%20de%20Flon">MyFonts search</a><br>
<a href="http://www.fonts.com/search/all-fonts?searchtext=Anders+de+Flon&amp;Searchin=all-fonts">Monotype search</a><br>
<a href="https://www.fontspring.com/search?q=Anders+de+Flon">Fontspring search</a><br>
<a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22%22+%22Anders%20de%20Flon%22&amp;btnG=Google+Search&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=">Google search</a></p><p><span>INTERNAL LINKS</span><br>
<a href="http://luc.devroye.org/sweden-index.html">Type design in Sweden</a> ⦿
<a href="http://luc.devroye.org/designers.html">Type designers</a> ⦿
<a href="http://luc.devroye.org/longdesigners-index.html">Type designers</a> ⦿
<a href="http://luc.devroye.org/pixel-index.html">Pixel/bitmap fonts</a> ⦿
</p></div></td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[BCHS software stack: BSD, C, httpd, SQLite (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://learnbchs.org/</link>
            <guid>38798383</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 20:47:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://learnbchs.org/">https://learnbchs.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38798383">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
		<section itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="http://schema.org/WebPage">
			<header id="tophead">
				
				<nav>
					<span><a href="https://learnbchs.org/tools.html">tools</a></span>
					<span><a href="https://learnbchs.org/easy.html">example</a></span>
					<span><a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/bchs"><i></i></a></span>
					<span><a href="https://learnbchs.org/report/index.html"><i></i></a></span>
				</nav>
			</header>
			<article id="top">
				<p><img itemprop="image" src="https://learnbchs.org/logo-white.png" alt="BCHS Logo">
				</p>
				<h2>BSD, C, httpd, SQLite.</h2>
				<p itemprop="description">
					BCHS is an <a href="https://www.openbsd.org/policy.html">open source</a> software stack for web
					applications.
					To prepare a BCHS environment, install <a href="https://www.openbsd.org/">OpenBSD</a>, start your editor
					of choice, and get to work.
				</p>
				<p>
					How does a BCHS system look?
					<a href="https://learnbchs.org/easy.html">See a trivial example</a>.
				</p>
			</article>
			<article id="start">
				<header>
					<h3>Stack components</h3>
					<p>why bchs? because the open internet is inhospitable.</p>
				</header>
				<section>
					<figure>
						<img src="https://learnbchs.org/puffy.png">
					</figure>
					
				</section>
				<section>
					<div>
						<h4>the C Programming Language</h4>
						<p>
							C is a straightforward, non-mustachioed language.
							It has full access to the kernel's system calls and a massive set of development tools
							and libraries.
						</p>
						<nav>
							Resources:
							<a href="https://www.amazon.com/The-Programming-Language-Brian-Kernighan/dp/0131103628">
								<i>The C Programming Language</i></a>,
							<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/OpenBSD-current/man1/clang.1">clang(1)</a>,
							<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/OpenBSD-current/man1/clang-local.1">clang-local(1)</a>.
						</nav>
					</div>
					<pre>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
   puts("<span>Hello, world!</span>");
   return 0;
}</pre>
				</section>
				<section>
					<pre>% curl -sD- -o/dev/null https://www.openbsd.org
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Connection: keep-alive
Content-Length: 5181
Content-Type: text/html
Date: Wed, 28 Mar 2018 03:15:19 GMT
Last-Modified: Sun, 25 Mar 2018 18:08:04 GMT
Server: <span>OpenBSD httpd</span></pre>
					
				</section>
				<section>
					
					<figure>
						<img src="https://learnbchs.org/sqlite.png">
					</figure>
				</section>
			</article>
			<article>
				<p>
					BCHS is a stable, developer-oriented platform.
				</p>
				<p>
					Get used to minimalism and security: componentised, privilege-separated binaries in file-system jails.
					Most of all, forget your instincts to search Google and StackExchange for every parameter and function
					call: man pages are your new best friend.
				</p>
			</article>
			<article id="news">
				<header>
					<h3>Articles, events, conference talks…</h3>
					<p>have more links?  <a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/bchs">let us know</a>.</p>
				</header>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<span>
							<a href="https://learnbchs.org/dates.html">Dates</a> in kcgi
						</span>
						<span>2020/05</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>
							<a href="https://learnbchs.org/portability.html">Portability and continuous integration</a>
						</span>
						<span>2020/04</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>
							<a href="https://kore.io/">kore</a>: 
							<a href="https://blog.kore.io/posts/automagic-x509s-via-acme.html">Automagic x509s via ACME</a>
						</span>
						<span>Joris Vink, 2019/11</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>
							<a href="https://learnbchs.org/sqlbox.html">sqlbox</a>: ksql re-imagined
						</span>
						<span>2019/11</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>
							<a href="https://learnbchs.org/typescript.html">TypeScript</a> integration and openradtool
						</span>
						<span>2019/07</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>
							<a href="https://learnbchs.org/translate.html">Translation</a> with openradtool
						</span>
						<span>2018/07</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>
							<a href="https://marc.info/?t=153019462600004&amp;r=1&amp;w=2">SQLite3 manpages</a> on
							OpenBSD
						</span>
						<span>2018/06</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span><a href="https://learnbchs.org/auditing.html">Role audits</a> with openradtool</span>
						<span>2018/03</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>
							<a href="https://kristaps.bsd.lv/absdcon2018/">RBAC in BCHS</a>
							(<a href="https://kristaps.bsd.lv/absdcon2018/paper.pdf">PDF</a>,
							 <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FzF9e4jrnJ4">video</a>)
						</span>
						<span>AsiaBSDCon, 2018/03</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span><a href="https://learnbchs.org/rbac.html">API provisioning</a> with openradtool</span>
						<span>2017/10</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<q><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KO1juo1KDFs">Should I use the BCHS web stack?</a></q>
						<span>EuroBSDCon short answer, 2017/09</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>Split-process <a href="https://learnbchs.org/ksql.html">ksql</a></span>
						<span>2017/07</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span><a href="https://learnbchs.org/kwebapp.html">Introduction</a> to RAD with openradtool</span>
						<span>2017/05</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span><a href="https://kristaps.bsd.lv//absdcon2017">Secure CGI</a></span>
						<span>AsiaBSDCon, 2017/03</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span>BCHS sandboxing with <a href="https://learnbchs.org/pledge.html">pledge</a></span>
						<span>2016/11</span>
					</li>
					<li>	
						<span>Using <a href="https://learnbchs.org/json.html">JSON</a> with BCHS</span>
						<span>2016/10</span>
					</li>
					<li>
						<span><a href="https://kristaps.bsd.lv/absdcon2016/">Secure CGI Applications in C on BSD</a></span>
						<span>AsiaBSDCon, 2016/03</span>
					</li>
				</ul>
			</article>
			<article>
				<header>
					<h3>FAQ</h3>
					<p>questions from the internet.</p>
				</header>
				<dl>
					<dt>Is BCHS a joke?</dt>
					<dd>
						Software development is full of jokes. 
						This is not one of them. 
					</dd>
					<dt>How do I pronounce <q>BCHS</q>?</dt>
					<dd>
						It's pronounced /biːtʃəz/, <i>beaches</i>.
						Or just Bee See Haich (or <q>Aich</q>) Ess.
					</dd>
					<dt>How can I hire BCHS developers?</dt>
					<dd>
						OpenBSD developers maintain an extensive list of <a href="https://www.openbsd.org/support.html">support</a> options, but these mostly relate
						to system administration.
						A better option is to contact your local <a href="https://www.openbsd.org/groups.html">user
							group</a>; or if an <a href="https://www.openbsd.org/events.html">event</a> is upcoming,
						attend and make enquiries in person.
						Falling through these options, polite enquiry on OpenBSD's <a href="https://www.openbsd.org/mail.html">misc</a> mailing list might get you pushed in
						the right direction.
					</dd>
					<dt>Wasn't this site once funnier?</dt>
					<dd>
						Yes.
						But some folks confused humour with levity.
					</dd>
				</dl>
			</article>
			
		</section>
	


</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You can't do that because I hate you (195 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bvisness.me/you-cant/</link>
            <guid>38797908</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 20:01:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bvisness.me/you-cant/">https://bvisness.me/you-cant/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38797908">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://bvisness.me/you-cant/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dark Visitors – A list of known AI agents on the internet (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://darkvisitors.com</link>
            <guid>38797487</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 19:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://darkvisitors.com">https://darkvisitors.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38797487">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>Insight into the hidden ecosystem of autonomous chatbots and data scrapers crawling across the web. Protect your website from unwanted AI agent access.</p><div id="submit-agent-container">
            <p><a href="https://forms.gle/RPjQGX5ojM3wmiKz8">Sign up</a> to get notified when new AI agents are added, so you can update your website's <a href="https://darkvisitors.com/robots-txt-builder">robots.txt</a>.</p>
            <p><a href="https://forms.gle/wiMhmaRPKHruFh687">Submit an AI Agent</a>
        </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hexcodle (215 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hexcodle.com/</link>
            <guid>38797472</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 19:29:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hexcodle.com/">https://hexcodle.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38797472">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Start by typing your guess above!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Custom firmware for MI fitness band (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/atc1441/ATCmiBand8fw</link>
            <guid>38797076</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 18:54:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/atc1441/ATCmiBand8fw">https://github.com/atc1441/ATCmiBand8fw</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38797076">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">ATC MiBand8 Fw</h2>
<p dir="auto">This is the most minimal demo of a custom firmware for the Xiaomi Mi Band 8</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Everything is really just bare minimum and not nice to read, but better i publish this now than never!</h3>
<p dir="auto">Here is a YouTube video that shows the general function
<a href="https://youtu.be/L2ugXV0ao3Q" rel="nofollow">https://youtu.be/L2ugXV0ao3Q</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L2ugXV0ao3Q" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/952c9179a589ffe46f0d2fa01ad584a35d060ee37aa9c6ec82bae043dc326231/68747470733a2f2f696d672e796f75747562652e636f6d2f76692f4c327567585630616f33512f302e6a7067" alt="YoutubeVideo" data-canonical-src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/L2ugXV0ao3Q/0.jpg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To build each example you need to enter the "gcc" folder of the choosen one and enter make, with an Segger flasher connected you can also use "flash.bat" and it will directly flash the firmware to the device. (Change the directy to the correct one in the file "jlink_auto_file.jlink" beforehand)</p>
<p dir="auto">In the folder "Custom_Firmware\boards\apollo4l_blue_evb\examples\peripherals\hello_world_lcd" you can find a Rickroll Gif example.</p>
<p dir="auto">In the folder "Custom_Firmware\boards\apollo4l_blue_evb\examples\peripherals\hello_world_uart" you can find an example of using the display, touchscreen and Light sensor, the Accl is started but not working right now( No idea when that will be finished :D )</p>
<p dir="auto">If you download the stock SDK from Ambiq.com you can also build working BLE examples.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://ambiq.com/apollo4-blue-lite/" rel="nofollow">https://ambiq.com/apollo4-blue-lite/</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://contentportal.ambiq.com/apollo4-blue-lite" rel="nofollow">https://contentportal.ambiq.com/apollo4-blue-lite</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Find the reversed pinout in the file "Pinout_MiBand8.ods" (OpenOffice)</p>
<p dir="auto">To flash a the Apollo 4 Blue Light SoC connect the SWD flasher to the pins: SWDIO and SWCLK, it is also best to connect to the Reset pin (small testpad) as the stock firmware disables the SWD interface after boot.</p>
<p dir="auto">The TXD Pin will output debug UART messages on 115200 baud</p>
<p dir="auto">See the pinout images for the further pins on the PCB</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/atc1441/ATCmiBand8fw/blob/main/PCB_test_pins_pinout.jpg"><img width="600" alt="PCB_test_pins_pinout" src="https://github.com/atc1441/ATCmiBand8fw/raw/main/PCB_test_pins_pinout.jpg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/atc1441/ATCmiBand8fw/blob/main/PCB_test_pins.jpg"><img width="600" alt="PCB_test_pins" src="https://github.com/atc1441/ATCmiBand8fw/raw/main/PCB_test_pins.jpg"></a></p>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Liero – Sling'n'shoot Worms Game (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.liero.be/</link>
            <guid>38796870</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 18:40:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.liero.be/">http://www.liero.be/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38796870">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="download">
			
			<div id="online">
							<p>
								We have four options for you. They are the same in terms of gameplay, but each one has its own special features. You may pick whichever one you like! All four are awesome!
							</p>
							
						</div>
			<div>
				<div>
					<h3>Liero 1.33</h3>
					<p>
						Conceived and created in 1998 Liero became a popular duel game in classrooms and homes alike. Between 1999 and 2005 the thriving Liero community created astounding maps, mods and editors to enhance the experience of this amazing game. This is final version of the original generation of Liero released in early 2000.
					</p>
					<div>
							<ul>
								<li><i></i> Maximum nostalgia</li>
								<li><i></i> Some bugs</li>
								<li><i></i> Requires Windows 98 or older</li>
								<li><i></i> No network play</li>
							</ul>
						</div>
					<p>
						<br><a href="https://www.liero.be/download/lierov133winxp.zip">
							<i></i> Download
						</a>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<h3>Liero 1.36</h3>
					<p>
						A true successor of the original game, this is a high fidelity clone based on the OpenLiero project from 2007. It is the official new version of Liero and the latest version was released in 2013. This version has fixed several annoying bugs and it has several several new modernising features - and of course it runs perfectly on modern computers.
					</p>
					<div>
						<div>
							<ul>
								<li><i></i> Perfect clone of 1.33</li>
								<li><i></i> Bugs fixed</li>
								<li><i></i> Works on almost any OS</li>
								<li><i></i> New AI opponent</li>
							</ul>
						</div>
						<div>
							<ul>
								<li><i></i> New game modes</li>
								<li><i></i> Record and watch replays</li>
								<li><i></i> Player profiles</li>
								<li><i></i> No network play</li>
							</ul>
						</div>
					</div>
					<p>
						<br><a href="https://www.liero.be/download/liero-1.36-bundle.zip">
							<i></i> Download
						</a>
						<a href="https://github.com/gliptic/liero">
							Source code
						</a>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div>
				<div>
					<h3>WebLiero <small>  RELEASED AUGUST 2019</small></h3>
					<p>
						After 20 years of intense anticipation from the Liero community it is astounding that the game finally reaches the clouds. WebLiero is an online multiplayer version of the Liero we all know and love which supports as many players as you wish from anywhere in the world. Create a room, invite your friends, drop the hammer and unleash that blood rain.
					</p>
					<div>
						<div>
							<ul>
								<li><i></i> True to original gameplay</li>
								<li><i></i> Works in the best browsers</li>
								<li><i></i> No splitscreen</li>
								<li><i></i> No offline mode</li>
							</ul>
						</div>
						<div>
							<ul>
								<li><i></i> Unlimited number of players</li>
								<li><i></i> Randomised map pools</li>
								<li><i></i> New game modes</li>
							</ul>
						</div>
					</div>
					<p>
						<br><a href="https://www.webliero.com/" target="_new">
							<i></i> Play now!
						</a>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<h3>lierolibre</h3>
					<p>
						This is a project to liberate Liero from all its proprietary components and to allow it to be distributed completely freely. “lierolibre” is a fork of Liero 1.35b, and features a new non-proprietary sound pack but is otherwise true to the game you were used to back in the nineties. Being completely re-engineered it is also easier to mod than the other games and does not use the original Liero files.
					</p>
					<div>
						<div>
							<ul>
								<li><i></i> True to original gameplay</li>
								<li><i></i> Different sound pack</li>
								<li><i></i> No proprietary content</li>
							</ul>
						</div>
						<div>
							<ul>
								<li><i></i> Works on almost any OS</li>
								<li><i></i> No network play</li>
							</ul>
						</div>
					</div>
					<p>
						<br><a target="_new" href="https://launchpad.net/lierolibre/+download">
							<i></i> Download
						</a>
						<a href="https://gitorious.org/lierolibre">
							Source code
						</a>
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<hr>
			
			<hr>
			<div id="about">
					<div>
						<h2>About the game</h2>
						<p>
							Liero is a simple game. Pick your five weapons, and unleash your inner fury. The game is always played one versus one on a map of your choice, and yes, you have to play with someone who is right next to you, unless you are enjoying the online multiplayer version!
						</p>
						<p>
							To shoot is of course easy enough to figure out, but if you want to step up your game, you need to figure out things like how to swing yourself to safety with the ninja rope, to use timed weapons for area denial, to hunt without being hunted, to ambush, hit and run, and control that darned guided missile.
						</p>
						<p>
							If you can do all these things, you may one day become a true champion, as the players in this video are trying to accomplish.
						</p>
					</div>
					<p>
							<iframe width="480" height="270" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BzvWW_SzZvk" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
						</p>
				</div>
			<hr>
			<div id="faq">
					<h2>Frequently asked questions</h2>
					<h5><i></i> How do I install Liero?</h5>
					<p>Unzip the game into a folder, and run it.</p>
					<h5><i></i> How do I install new levels?</h5>
					<p>Drop them in the same folder as the game.</p>
					<h5><i></i> Liero 1.33 doesnt run, why?</h5>
					<p>The game is old and your computer is new. Disable sounds by adding /n to the command line when starting the game.</p>
					<p><a>Click here for further instructions.</a></p>
					<div>
						<ol>
							<li>Right click Liero.exe and select "Create shortcut"</li>
							<li>Right click the created shortcut and select "Properties"</li>
							<li>Go to the tab titled Program and place the cursor at the end of the line</li>
							<li>Add /n at the end, after LIERO.EXE</li>
							<li>Press OK and run Liero via the shortcut</li>
						</ol>
					</div>
					<h5><i></i> Liero 1.36 doesn't run, why?</h5>
					<p>You need to run <em>OpenLiero.exe</em> instead of Liero.exe.</p>
					<h5><i></i> How do I change the game window size in Liero 1.36 and lierolibre?</h5>
					<p>Press F5 and F6 for full screen and 2x size, or use the menus.</p>
					<h5><i></i> How do I record replays?</h5>
					<p>In lierolibre, press F1 to access the "secret menu". Liero 1.36 has the options in the regular menus.</p>
					<h5><i></i> Which browsers support WebLiero?</h5>
					<p>Firefox, Chrome and Chromium.</p>
				</div>
			<hr>
			<div id="history">
						<h2>A brief history of Liero</h2>
						<p>Liero - originally envisioned to be a top-down-view game - eventually came out as a clone of MoleZ, a similar subterranean shooter game featuring moles instead of worms. The game was first published in 1998, in the Finnish "mbit" computer game magazine by Joosa Riekkinen. It quickly became a popular pastime in Finland and even won some “game of the week” awards. It soon began spreading on the internet, particularly interesting the owners of low-end computers.</p>
						<p>In 1999, Joosa became disillusioned with game development and decided to retire the game. Development stopped in January 2000 at the final version '1.33'. By this time a multitude of fan sites for Liero had already cropped up on the world wide web. The one which was to become the foundation of the community was "Wormhole - The Ultimate Liero Level Editor". The core of the site was the Liero editor <em>Wormhole</em> which let you convert BMP files into Liero levels, the <em>Liero Blood Increaser</em> which could set the blood spray all the way up to 32750%, and the <em>Liero Graphic Editor</em> which allowed users to create custom skins for the worms and projectiles. The community began to blossom on the Wormhole guestbook page.</p>
						<p>In the following years, the community moved off the guestbooks and message boards into the new heart of the community - The LieroNet Forum. Participation spiked and several new editors saw the light of day, with the most groundbreaking of them all, <em>LieroKit</em> and <em>LieroHacker</em> by Gliptic (Erik Lindroos). This new breed of editors could penetrate much deeper into the Liero game files and allowed editing weapons, changing the palettes, and altering of the physics of the game.</p>
						<p>Simultaneously - a somewhat separate community evolved in southern Poland with the prominent clan “Liga Liero”. The polish community quickly outgrew the international community, but due to the language barrier its strength never truly carried over into the wider world.</p>
						<h4>The next generation</h4>
						<p>The next step in the evolution of the game was the development of the first working clones. The most notable were <em>Wurmz!</em> by Patrys, <em>LOSP</em> by Gliptic, <em>LieroXtreme</em> by JasonB and <em>Gusanos</em> by Basro (Mario Carbajal), and let's not to forget <em>NiL</em> which was the very first clone of the all, and the first Liero for Linux, but was not widely played. All these projects took the game their own slightly divergent directions and with most of them being highly moddable, some with multiplayer features. It is also worth mentioning that innumerable clones projects were begun and abandoned by as many individuals, including 3D clones, Wii versions and anything you can think of.</p>
						<p>The most successful of the clones, <em>LOSP</em> was eventually developed into <em>OpenLiero</em>, which in 2007 was renamed “the official new version of Liero” when released as <em>Liero 1.34</em>. Unlike the other clones, OpenLiero was meant to be an exact simulation of the original Liero and still requires the original game files present in order to run. The idea behind it is to preserve the original game feeling but to allow the game to run properly on modern systems, and other platforms, and removing some notorious bugs. After some deliberation, new game options were added, such as the replay recording feature, new game modes, player profiles and eventually a restructuring of the game menu.</p>
						<p>In 2011 Joosa was approached by arand (Martin Erik Werner) with questions about licensing. It turned out he was making yet another clone based on the OpenLiero source code. The goal was to remove all proprietary content from the game so that it could be included in Linux packages. His version, aptly named <em>lierolibre</em> was released in 2012 and was adopted in 2013 as one of the promoted game versions on Liero.be, so as to give the avid Liero enthusiast complete freedom of choice.</p>
						<p>While the community has mostly vanished into the world, many old sites still survive the tooth of time. Most of the old community content created between 2000 and 2005 can still be found through way-back-machines, Google searches and not-yet-dead links on the Liero sites you may come across. The most important surviving sites are presented above in the resource section.</p>
						<h4>The Internet Age</h4>
						<p>One of the great talking points in the early era of clone-making was "network play". Many developers attempted to create online games, but only <em>LieroXtreme</em> really had any noteworthy success. But while it did have many fans it differed greatly from the original Liero and the purists remained restricted to the horrors of meeting people in real life in order to play a good game of Liero. This would however change abruptly in 2019 when long time Liero community member Basro (Mario Carbajal) combined the networking engine of his other game, the popular football game <em>"Haxball"</em> with the source code of Liero. Cowabunga! The wonderful world of Liero is now available for anyone to play with an unlimited number of friends, and an assurance of absolute mayhem!</p>
					</div>
			<div id="contact">
						<h3>Contact</h3>
						<p>If you have any questions about the Liero games you may leave some love on <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/liero">reddit.com/r/liero</a>, speak your mind on <a target="new" href="https://discord.gg/ZeNBxdh2wp">Discord</a>, or maybe squeek at us on <a target="_new" href="https://twitter.com/lieroofficial">Twitter</a>.</p>
						<p><strong>Have a great time playing Liero!</strong></p>
					</div>
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OsmAPP – A Universal OpenStreetMap App (170 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://osmapp.org</link>
            <guid>38795559</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 17:05:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://osmapp.org">https://osmapp.org</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38795559">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 256 256" width="130" height="130"><g fill-rule="evenodd"><path d="M32.578 33.691L80.11 45.27l42.412-11.943 43.51 11.822 44.12-13.041 13.162 47.166-14.382 42.29 11.7 41.804-10.846 44.241-44.607 11.822-43.51-12.797-34.125 10.847-51.31-6.094 10.97-46.556-11.335-45.704L47.69 78.663z" fill="#eb5757"></path><g fill="#fff" stroke="#fff"><path d="M118.927 125.615l-36.129 35.643c2.407 4.336 8.381 9.267 11.495 11.199l33.955-37.286" stroke-width="1.309"></path><path d="M175.92 107.559c0 17.48-13.968 31.65-31.198 31.65s-31.198-14.17-31.198-31.65c0-17.48 13.967-31.65 31.198-31.65 17.23 0 31.198 14.17 31.198 31.65z" stroke-width="2.945"></path></g></g></svg><h6>A universal OpenStreetMap app</h6></p><p>Start by typing your query into the searchbox.<br>Or click any item on the map.</p><p>eg.<!-- --> <a href="https://osmapp.org/way/34633854">Empire State Building</a> •<!-- --> <a href="https://osmapp.org/way/119016167">Statues of Charles bridge</a></p><p><img src="https://osmapp.org/osmapp-screenshot.png" alt="Screenshot of OsmAPP" width="300" height="226.03938730853392"></p><div><p><img src="https://osmapp.org/logo/logo-osm.svg" alt="OpenStreetMap logo" width="100" height="100"></p><p><span data-id="homepage.about_osm">All map data is from
      <a href="https://osm.org/">OpenStreetMap</a>, a map created by
      milions of contributors — similar to Wikipedia. You can find
      <em>Edit</em> button on each map feature.</span></p></div><h2>About OsmAPP</h2><p><span data-id="homepage.about_osmapp">This application should offer a convenient interface for everyday use of <i>OpenStreetMap</i>
     including editing options. <br>Currently it includes various map layers, POI editing and a basic search engine.
     Features such as navigation or favorite places are planned.</span></p><p> <span data-id="homepage.github_link">You may suggest new features on <a href="https://github.com/zbycz/osmapp" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Github</a>.</span></p><div><p><a tabindex="0" aria-disabled="false" href="https://osmapp.org/install"><span><span></span>Install app</span></a></p></div><h2>Special thanks to</h2><p><span data-id="homepage.special_thanks"><ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.mapillary.com/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Mapillary</a>,
              <a href="https://openstreetmap.cz/fody" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Fody</a>,
              <a href="https://www.wikipedia.org/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Wikipedia</a> – for images 🖼
        </li><li><a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">OpenStreetMap</a> – for the best world map 🌎
      </li></ul>
  </span></p><p><a href="https://www.maptiler.com/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><img src="https://osmapp.org/logo/maptiler.svg" alt="MapTiler logo" width="200" height="52"><br><span data-id="homepage.maptiler"><strong>MapTiler</strong> – for awesome vector maps <br>and for supporting this project  ❤️ </span></a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mozilla '23 Ann. Report: CEO pay skyrockets while Firefox Marketshare nosedives (348 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lunduke.locals.com/post/5053290/mozilla-2023-annual-report-ceo-pay-skyrockets-while-firefox-marketshare-nosedives</link>
            <guid>38795308</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 16:44:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lunduke.locals.com/post/5053290/mozilla-2023-annual-report-ceo-pay-skyrockets-while-firefox-marketshare-nosedives">https://lunduke.locals.com/post/5053290/mozilla-2023-annual-report-ceo-pay-skyrockets-while-firefox-marketshare-nosedives</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38795308">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>
        Mozilla 2023 Annual Report: CEO pay skyrockets, while Firefox Marketshare nosedives    </p><div>
        <p>The Mozilla Foundation has <a href="https://stateof.mozilla.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">released their latest annual report</a> -- covering the time up through December of 2022 (Mozilla's reporting always lags by one year) -- and something peculiar leaps out of the data:</p><ul><li>The <strong>compensation of the Mozilla CEO has skyrocketed</strong> (by millions)</li><li>While the <strong>Mozilla revenue drops</strong></li><li>And the <strong>Firefox Marketshare takes a nosedive</strong></li></ul><p>While, at first, this seems ridiculously lopsided... perhaps it actually makes sense.</p><p><em>Perhaps</em> the decreasing Firefox marketshare is a good thing, from the Mozilla point of view.</p><h3>Mozilla CEO gets a raise</h3><p>Let's start by looking at the pay of the Mozilla CEO.</p><figure><img src="https://media3.locals.com/images/posts/2023-12-27/102127/102127_dmnwn924regnp3j_custom.jpeg" alt=""><figcaption>Source: Mozilla Foundation 2022 IRS 990</figcaption></figure><p>That's right.&nbsp; Your eyes do not deceive you.&nbsp; The Mozilla CEO earned $6,903,089 in 2022.&nbsp; Just shy of $7 Million.</p><p>The year prior (2021), the CEO earned $5.6 Million.&nbsp; A <strong><em>raise</em></strong> of $1.3 Million dollars.&nbsp; Not a bad year-on-year increase!</p><p><img src="https://media3.locals.com/images/posts/2023-12-27/102127/102127_ok8f4fnipan7noi_custom.jpeg" alt="" width="353" height="218"></p><p>Now let's take a look at the core performance of Mozilla: The overall revenue, and the marketshare of their core product (Firefox) during that same period.</p><p>If a CEO gets a $1.3 Million dollar raise, surely those numbers will be excellent! &nbsp;... <em>Right?</em></p><p>Turns out... the revenue for Mozilla actually <em>dropped</em> between 2021 and 2022.</p><figure><img src="https://media3.locals.com/images/posts/2023-12-27/102127/102127_2irjcoofxpocsx6_custom.jpeg" alt="" width="610" height="348"><figcaption>Source: Mozilla Foundation 2022 IRS 990</figcaption></figure><p>To be fair, not a <em>huge</em> drop.&nbsp; Revenue went from $600 Million in 2021 to $593 Million in 2022.&nbsp; Roughly $7 Million lower.&nbsp; A small decrease, percentage wise... but a decrease just the same.</p><h3>The Firefox Nosedive</h3><p>Now let's look at the marketshare of Mozilla's primary product: Firefox.</p><p><img src="https://media3.locals.com/images/posts/2023-12-27/102127/102127_n8chdg6gk3if4gd_custom.jpeg" alt="" width="388" height="240">From the end of 2021 to the end of 2022 (the period during which the Mozilla CEO received a $1.3 Million Dollar raise), Firefox marketshare took a massive tumble.</p><p>Going from (an already declining) 3.79%... down to 3.04%.</p><p>It's almost as if there is an inverse relationship between Firefox Marketshare and Mozilla CEO compensation -- as marketshare goes down... CEO pay goes up by a similar percentage.</p><p><img src="https://media3.locals.com/images/posts/2023-12-27/102127/102127_n8vy8qci5obkq77_custom.jpeg" alt="" width="420" height="260"></p><p>Absolutely wild.</p><h3>Something doesn't add up... or does it?</h3><p>So.&nbsp; What can we learn from all of this?</p><p>Well, for starters, it is clear that Mozilla CEO compensation is <strong><em>not</em></strong> tied to either the success of the Firefox web browser (their current primary product) <strong><em>or</em></strong> to the overall revenue of Mozilla.</p><p>So what, <em>exactly</em>, could be the justification for that massive pay raise?</p><p>Turns out there are two big, measurable goals that Mozilla appears to have... and, at those goals, it is performing <em>exceptionally</em> well:</p><ol><li>Continued increases to overall corporate financial assets.</li><li>Transitioning Mozilla <em>away</em> from Firefox.</li></ol><p>That first goal is rather obvious.&nbsp; Let's be honest, what company doesn't want to have a massive pile of financial assets?</p><p>In 2022, the Mozilla war-chest (total assets) grew to a staggering <strong>$1.3 Billion Dollars</strong> -- up $157 Million from the year prior.&nbsp; A huge increase to their financial assets.</p><figure><img src="https://media3.locals.com/images/posts/2023-12-27/102127/102127_qnkwb8vtwgx6cf8_custom.jpeg" alt="" width="554" height="357"><figcaption>Source: Mozilla Foundation 2022 IRS 990</figcaption></figure><p>With over half a Billion Dollars in <em>cash</em> alone.&nbsp; That's a lot of cheddar.</p><p>But that's only part of the story.</p><h3>The De-Firefox-ification of Mozilla</h3><p>Let's take another look at the 2022 revenue breakdown.</p><p><img src="https://media3.locals.com/images/posts/2023-12-27/102127/102127_2lxxy1bxxwthsyp_custom.jpeg" alt="" width="571" height="326"></p><p><br>Note that revenue from "Royalties" is down substantially -- a decrease of $17 Million.&nbsp; Those "Royalties" are, in large part, made up of default search engine placement, within Firefox, for one single customer... Google.&nbsp; This decrease makes sense considering the signficant decline in Firefox marketshare.</p><p>But then look at the second row: <strong>"Subscription and advertising revenue"</strong>.</p><p>What is that, exactly? &nbsp;That line item includes some of the more recently launched subscription services -- "Pocket Premium" and "Mozilla VPN" (plus some advertising placement). &nbsp;And, you'll note, <em>that</em> revenue jumped from $56 Million to $75 Million in 2022.</p><p>While that may be a drop in the bucket of the overall Mozilla revenue and war-chest... it's a critical strategy for Mozilla to diversify their revenue stream <strong><em>away from Firefox</em></strong>.</p><p>As it turns out, moving away from Firefox is exactly Mozilla's plan.</p><p>Earlier this year, <a href="https://lunduke.locals.com/post/4671162/mozilla-downplaying-firefox-moving-into-a-i" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Mozilla laid out their vision for the future of their organization</a> -- and it did not include Firefox. &nbsp;The focus for the future of Mozilla -- <em>according to Mozilla</em> -- is primarily based around Artificial Intelligence services.</p><p>In fact, Mozilla leadership stated, quite plainly, that they intend to take Mozilla "in a&nbsp;different direction."</p><p>When you consider the goals of Mozilla... the decreasing Firefox marketshare is no longer much of a concern.&nbsp; In fact, moving revenue away from Firefox, while investing in A.I. systems (and other subscription services) becomes the primary goal.</p><p>And, at that, the Mozilla CEO is excelling.</p><h3>The future of Mozilla</h3><p>What does all of this mean for the future of Mozilla?&nbsp; What have we learned from Mozilla statements coupled with their financial reports?</p><ul><li>Mozilla rewards executives who oversee a decreasing success and reliance upon Firefox -- so we can expect more of that.</li><li>In turn, that likely means reduced investment in Firefox development and promotion over the coming years.</li><li>Mozilla intends to focus on A.I. -- so we can expect more A.I. investment, and possible A.I. services, in the year ahead.</li><li>If all of that holds true, we can likely expect the Mozilla CEO to receive additional raises in the next annual reports.</li></ul><p>If you are a fan of Firefox... none of that points to a particularly bright future.</p><p>That said... if you are the CEO at Mozilla... you might bring in enough income to buy your own island fortress pretty soon.&nbsp; And who doesn't want an island fortress?</p><hr><p>Want more truly independent Tech Journalism?&nbsp; Be sure to grab at least a free membership to&nbsp;<a href="https://lunduke.locals.com/Lunduke.Locals.com" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lunduke.Locals.com</a>.</p><p>Want to support this important work (and get some exclusive books, videos, and other goodies in the process)?&nbsp;&nbsp;<a href="https://lunduke.locals.com/support" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Grab a paid subscription</a>.</p><hr><p>Other articles you might be interested in:</p><ul><li><a href="https://lunduke.locals.com/post/5049241/linux-foundation-now-spends-only-2-of-their-revenue-on-linux" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Linux Foundation now spends only 2% of their revenue on Linux</a></li><li><a href="https://lunduke.locals.com/post/4408159/linux-foundation-decreased-linux-spending-to-3-2-in-2022" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Linux Foundation decreased Linux spending to 3.2% in 2022</a></li><li><a href="https://lunduke.locals.com/post/4458111/the-wiki-piggy-bank" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Wiki Piggy Bank</a></li><li><a href="https://lunduke.locals.com/post/3983662/major-open-source-projects-how-much-money-do-they-actually-make" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Major Open Source Projects: How much money do they actually make?</a></li></ul><div>
    <p><img src="https://media3.locals.com/images/avatars/102127/102127_pavt7hft2xvhhod_thumb.png" alt="community logo">
    </p>
    <p>
        Join the Lunduke Community
    </p>
    <p>
        To read more articles like this, sign up and join my community today
    </p>
    
</div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Details on Xiaomi EV (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.engadget.com/xiaomi-says-its-su7-ev-can-outperform-porsche-and-has-more-tech-than-tesla-095637762.html</link>
            <guid>38795290</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 16:43:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.engadget.com/xiaomi-says-its-su7-ev-can-outperform-porsche-and-has-more-tech-than-tesla-095637762.html">https://www.engadget.com/xiaomi-says-its-su7-ev-can-outperform-porsche-and-has-more-tech-than-tesla-095637762.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38795290">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main role="main"><div id="module-moreStories" data-wf-sticky-offset="130px   10px" data-wf-sticky-position="" data-wf-sticky-target="#adsStream" data-wf-trigger-percentage=""><ul><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/oujKNktiIKNeOC_rH0CKLg--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2022-03/de844380-a47d-11ec-b6be-9dd2ff775c4e" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="94f7e0a4-2c37-37fd-9879-739177ccbf4c" href="https://www.engadget.com/best-ipad-accessories-130018595.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:8;ct:story;g:94f7e0a4-2c37-37fd-9879-739177ccbf4c" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">The best iPad accessories for 2024</a></h4><p>Here are some of the best accessories you can buy for your new iPad, including stands, hubs, chargers and more, as reviewed by Engadget editors.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/MSD_9GCtabO.JkVdOnFtGw--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2023-02/5b28eef0-b3c2-11ed-b57f-9e3f777f5abe" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="8202648e-c2ce-4649-9f4b-98cd9b8af405" href="https://www.engadget.com/the-morning-after-the-best-games-of-2023-121548149.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:10;ct:story;g:8202648e-c2ce-4649-9f4b-98cd9b8af405" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">The Morning After: The best games of 2023</a></h4><p>The biggest news stories this morning:  The Apple Watch import ban is paused — for now, Swedish Researchers develop ‘electronic soil’, The Right to Repair movement won its biggest victories in 2023.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/HJxsKHuUuiGQ7r9EkcFr0w--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2023-09/b2cc3b00-57da-11ee-abdf-204593f65c5e" alt=""></p></div></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/PDVG0r28JlGWq347bXyrsQ--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2023-12/e5bba2d0-a4fb-11ee-af7d-0869508c9a34" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="5122336c-8711-4a89-a5d9-523d3548a9a4" href="https://www.engadget.com/the-first-ev-with-a-lithium-free-sodium-battery-hits-the-road-in-january-214828536.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:17;ct:story;g:5122336c-8711-4a89-a5d9-523d3548a9a4" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">The first EV with a lithium-free sodium battery hits the road in January</a></h4><p>JAC Motors, a Volkswagen-backed Chinese automaker, unveiled the first mass-produced EV with a sodium-ion battery through its new Yiwei brand. Although sodium-ion battery tech has a lower density than lithium-ion, its lower costs, simpler and more abundant supplies and superior cold-weather performance could help accelerate mass EV adoption.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/uju29m3F3a4eGsaIys9vGQ--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2023-12/9db494b0-a415-11ee-bfba-7079485ad539" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="323bb63c-c359-4f8c-a702-1347873f8cc8" href="https://www.engadget.com/apple-appeals-ban-on-watch-series-9-and-ultra-2-174046101.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:20;ct:story;g:323bb63c-c359-4f8c-a702-1347873f8cc8" data-hosted-type="HOSTED">Apple appeals ban on Watch Series 9 and Ultra 2</a></h4><p>Apple has filed an appeal to the International Trade Commision attempting to reverse a ban on US sales of the Apple Watch Series 9 and Ultra 2. The company’s also requesting an emergency stay on the ban until a decision is reached regarding proposed redesigns of both smartwatch models.</p></div></div></li></ul></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Anytype – local-first, P2P knowledge management (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://anytype.io/</link>
            <guid>38794733</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 16:00:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://anytype.io/">https://anytype.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38794733">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Particle Life (302 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life</link>
            <guid>38794625</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 15:52:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life">https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38794625">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/65893b444b686267ca39d78e23a1266b55a06293669f81efac2c370afb327ae4/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f7265706f2d73697a652f68756e6172343332312f6c6966655f636f6465"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/65893b444b686267ca39d78e23a1266b55a06293669f81efac2c370afb327ae4/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f7265706f2d73697a652f68756e6172343332312f6c6966655f636f6465" alt="GitHub repo size" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/repo-size/hunar4321/life_code"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/c2b61dab1da9fe2b6d1615f7f70e4bbbb0faf13c82eb7e3652c23dbd3ca6d9eb/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6c6963656e73652f68756e6172343332312f6c6966655f636f6465"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/c2b61dab1da9fe2b6d1615f7f70e4bbbb0faf13c82eb7e3652c23dbd3ca6d9eb/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6c6963656e73652f68756e6172343332312f6c6966655f636f6465" alt="GitHub" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/license/hunar4321/life_code"></a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Particle Life Simulation</h2>
<p dir="auto">A simple program to simulate primitive Artificial Life using simple rules of attraction or repulsion among atom-like particles, producing complex self-organzing life-like patterns. Excluding the GUI elements, the code is less than a page. The video tutorial and walkthrough are available below.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Learn More Here (YouTube video tutorial):</h2>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://youtu.be/0Kx4Y9TVMGg" rel="nofollow">https://youtu.be/0Kx4Y9TVMGg</a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Online Demo (JavaScript version):</h2>
<p dir="auto">Click here for a live demo (JavaScript):</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>2d - <a href="https://hunar4321.github.io/particle-life/particle_life.html" rel="nofollow">https://hunar4321.github.io/particle-life/particle_life.html</a></li>
<li>3d - <a href="https://hunar4321.github.io/particle-life/particle_life_3d.html" rel="nofollow">https://hunar4321.github.io/particle-life/particle_life_3d.html</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Interface (C++ version)</h2>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life/blob/main/images/interface.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life/raw/main/images/interface.jpg" alt=""></a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Example Results</h2>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life/blob/main/images/big_pic.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life/raw/main/images/big_pic.jpg" alt=""></a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Some Interesting Patterns to Reproduce:</h2>
<p dir="auto">You do not need to be exact with the parameters to reproduce these patterns. The best way to get interesting patterns is to first try random parameter explorations, once you find an interesting pattern, try fine-tuning it gradually. To avoid becoming stuck at a local maximum, you can make some occasional big parameter jumps. In this way interesting and different patterns shall keep poping up.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life/blob/main/images/some_patterns.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/hunar4321/particle-life/raw/main/images/some_patterns.jpg" alt=""></a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">To use:</h2>
<p dir="auto">Download this repo. unzip the file then go to /particle_life/bin/ folder and click on particle_life.exe</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Code:</h2>
<p dir="auto">The source code is available in C++, JavaScript, and Python.
Watch this YouTube video for a walkthrough tutorial: <a href="https://youtu.be/0Kx4Y9TVMGg" rel="nofollow">https://youtu.be/0Kx4Y9TVMGg</a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you would like to contribute to the C++ program, the core algorithm is the first 100 lines of code at:  "/particle_life/src/ofApp.cpp". The rest are GUI components and rendering controls which are provided by the openFrameworks library an opensource and easy-to-use image rendering library.</p>
<p dir="auto">To start, download this repository then download openFrameworks library from here: <a href="https://openframeworks.cc/" rel="nofollow">https://openframeworks.cc/</a>. Use openFramework's projectGenerator and import /particle_life/ folder to the project.</p>
<p dir="auto">Alternatively, generate a new openFramework project and add ofxGui. Once the project files are generated replace the /src/ folder with the one provided here.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can now compile the C++ code on your machine.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Other Ports:</h2>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/NiclasEriksen/game-of-leif">Godot</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ChevyRay/smarticles">Rust</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sikora507/go-artificial-life">Go-1</a>, <a href="https://github.com/fglo/particles-rules-of-attraction">Go-2</a>, <a href="https://github.com/youssefboulmalf/Particle-Life-Go">Go-3</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/gianfa/pyrticleslife">Python</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ravener/love-life">Lua</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/a740g/Particle-Life">QB64-PE</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/CapsAdmin/webgl-particles">Webgl</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/helloimalemur/ParticleSimulation">Java</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/BlinkSun/ParticleLifeSimulation">C# Winforms</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.freebasic.net/forum/viewtopic.php?p=294331#p294331" rel="nofollow">FreeBasic</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The JavaScript code is as simple as this:</h2>
<p dir="auto">Also, look at the particle_life.html file for a more optimized version - thanks to those who have contributed.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="<canvas id=&quot;life&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;500&quot;></canvas>
<script>
  //Hunar Ahmad @ brainxyz
  m = document.getElementById(&quot;life&quot;).getContext(&quot;2d&quot;);
  draw = (x, y, c, s) => {
    m.fillStyle = c;
    m.fillRect(x, y, s, s);
  };
  atoms = [];
  atom = (x, y, c) => {
    return { x: x, y: y, vx: 0, vy: 0, color: c };
  };
  random = () => {
    return Math.random() * 400 + 50;
  };
  create = (number, color) => {
    group = [];
    for (let i = 0; i < number; i++) {
      group.push(atom(random(), random(), color));
      atoms.push(group[i]);
    }
    return group;
  };
  rule = (atoms1, atoms2, g) => {
    for (let i = 0; i < atoms1.length; i++) {
      fx = 0;
      fy = 0;
      for (let j = 0; j < atoms2.length; j++) {
        a = atoms1[i];
        b = atoms2[j];
        dx = a.x - b.x;
        dy = a.y - b.y;
        d = Math.sqrt(dx * dx + dy * dy);
        if (d > 0 &amp;&amp; d < 80) {
          F = (g * 1) / d;
          fx += F * dx;
          fy += F * dy;
        }
      }
      a.vx = (a.vx + fx) * 0.5;
      a.vy = (a.vy + fy) * 0.5;
      a.x += a.vx;
      a.y += a.vy;
      if (a.x <= 0 || a.x >= 500) { a.vx *= -1; }
      if (a.y <= 0 || a.y >= 500) { a.vy *= -1; }
    }
  };
  yellow = create(200, &quot;yellow&quot;);
  red = create(200, &quot;red&quot;);
  green = create(200, &quot;green&quot;);
  update = () => {
    rule(green, green, -0.32);
    rule(green, red, -0.17);
    rule(green, yellow, 0.34);
    rule(red, red, -0.1);
    rule(red, green, -0.34);
    rule(yellow, yellow, 0.15);
    rule(yellow, green, -0.2);
    m.clearRect(0, 0, 500, 500);
    draw(0, 0, &quot;black&quot;, 500);
    for (i = 0; i < atoms.length; i++) {
      draw(atoms[i].x, atoms[i].y, atoms[i].color, 5);
    }
    requestAnimationFrame(update);
  };
  update();
</script>"><pre><span>&lt;</span><span>canvas</span> <span>id</span>="<span>life</span>" <span>width</span>="<span>500</span>" <span>height</span>="<span>500</span>"<span>&gt;</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>canvas</span><span>&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span>
  <span>//Hunar Ahmad @ brainxyz</span>
  <span>m</span> <span>=</span> <span>document</span><span>.</span><span>getElementById</span><span>(</span><span>"life"</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>getContext</span><span>(</span><span>"2d"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
  <span>draw</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>x</span><span>,</span> <span>y</span><span>,</span> <span>c</span><span>,</span> <span>s</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>m</span><span>.</span><span>fillStyle</span> <span>=</span> <span>c</span><span>;</span>
    <span>m</span><span>.</span><span>fillRect</span><span>(</span><span>x</span><span>,</span> <span>y</span><span>,</span> <span>s</span><span>,</span> <span>s</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span><span>;</span>
  <span>atoms</span> <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>]</span><span>;</span>
  <span>atom</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>x</span><span>,</span> <span>y</span><span>,</span> <span>c</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>{</span> <span>x</span>: <span>x</span><span>,</span> <span>y</span>: <span>y</span><span>,</span> <span>vx</span>: <span>0</span><span>,</span> <span>vy</span>: <span>0</span><span>,</span> <span>color</span>: <span>c</span> <span>}</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span><span>;</span>
  <span>random</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>Math</span><span>.</span><span>random</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>*</span> <span>400</span> <span>+</span> <span>50</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span><span>;</span>
  <span>create</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>number</span><span>,</span> <span>color</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>group</span> <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>]</span><span>;</span>
    <span>for</span> <span>(</span><span>let</span> <span>i</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span> <span>&lt;</span> <span>number</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span><span>++</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
      <span>group</span><span>.</span><span>push</span><span>(</span><span>atom</span><span>(</span><span>random</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>,</span> <span>random</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>,</span> <span>color</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
      <span>atoms</span><span>.</span><span>push</span><span>(</span><span>group</span><span>[</span><span>i</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>}</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>group</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span><span>;</span>
  <span>rule</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>atoms1</span><span>,</span> <span>atoms2</span><span>,</span> <span>g</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>for</span> <span>(</span><span>let</span> <span>i</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span> <span>&lt;</span> <span>atoms1</span><span>.</span><span>length</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span><span>++</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
      <span>fx</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span>
      <span>fy</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span>
      <span>for</span> <span>(</span><span>let</span> <span>j</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span> <span>j</span> <span>&lt;</span> <span>atoms2</span><span>.</span><span>length</span><span>;</span> <span>j</span><span>++</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
        <span>a</span> <span>=</span> <span>atoms1</span><span>[</span><span>i</span><span>]</span><span>;</span>
        <span>b</span> <span>=</span> <span>atoms2</span><span>[</span><span>j</span><span>]</span><span>;</span>
        <span>dx</span> <span>=</span> <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>x</span> <span>-</span> <span>b</span><span>.</span><span>x</span><span>;</span>
        <span>dy</span> <span>=</span> <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>y</span> <span>-</span> <span>b</span><span>.</span><span>y</span><span>;</span>
        <span>d</span> <span>=</span> <span>Math</span><span>.</span><span>sqrt</span><span>(</span><span>dx</span> <span>*</span> <span>dx</span> <span>+</span> <span>dy</span> <span>*</span> <span>dy</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
        <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>d</span> <span>&gt;</span> <span>0</span> <span>&amp;&amp;</span> <span>d</span> <span>&lt;</span> <span>80</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
          <span>F</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>g</span> <span>*</span> <span>1</span><span>)</span> <span>/</span> <span>d</span><span>;</span>
          <span>fx</span> <span>+=</span> <span>F</span> <span>*</span> <span>dx</span><span>;</span>
          <span>fy</span> <span>+=</span> <span>F</span> <span>*</span> <span>dy</span><span>;</span>
        <span>}</span>
      <span>}</span>
      <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>vx</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>vx</span> <span>+</span> <span>fx</span><span>)</span> <span>*</span> <span>0.5</span><span>;</span>
      <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>vy</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>vy</span> <span>+</span> <span>fy</span><span>)</span> <span>*</span> <span>0.5</span><span>;</span>
      <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>x</span> <span>+=</span> <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>vx</span><span>;</span>
      <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>y</span> <span>+=</span> <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>vy</span><span>;</span>
      <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>x</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>0</span> <span>||</span> <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>x</span> <span>&gt;=</span> <span>500</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span> <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>vx</span> <span>*=</span> <span>-</span><span>1</span><span>;</span> <span>}</span>
      <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>a</span><span>.</span><span>y</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>0</span> <span>||</span> <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>y</span> <span>&gt;=</span> <span>500</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span> <span>a</span><span>.</span><span>vy</span> <span>*=</span> <span>-</span><span>1</span><span>;</span> <span>}</span>
    <span>}</span>
  <span>}</span><span>;</span>
  <span>yellow</span> <span>=</span> <span>create</span><span>(</span><span>200</span><span>,</span> <span>"yellow"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
  <span>red</span> <span>=</span> <span>create</span><span>(</span><span>200</span><span>,</span> <span>"red"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
  <span>green</span> <span>=</span> <span>create</span><span>(</span><span>200</span><span>,</span> <span>"green"</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
  <span>update</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>rule</span><span>(</span><span>green</span><span>,</span> <span>green</span><span>,</span> <span>-</span><span>0.32</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>rule</span><span>(</span><span>green</span><span>,</span> <span>red</span><span>,</span> <span>-</span><span>0.17</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>rule</span><span>(</span><span>green</span><span>,</span> <span>yellow</span><span>,</span> <span>0.34</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>rule</span><span>(</span><span>red</span><span>,</span> <span>red</span><span>,</span> <span>-</span><span>0.1</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>rule</span><span>(</span><span>red</span><span>,</span> <span>green</span><span>,</span> <span>-</span><span>0.34</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>rule</span><span>(</span><span>yellow</span><span>,</span> <span>yellow</span><span>,</span> <span>0.15</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>rule</span><span>(</span><span>yellow</span><span>,</span> <span>green</span><span>,</span> <span>-</span><span>0.2</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>m</span><span>.</span><span>clearRect</span><span>(</span><span>0</span><span>,</span> <span>0</span><span>,</span> <span>500</span><span>,</span> <span>500</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>draw</span><span>(</span><span>0</span><span>,</span> <span>0</span><span>,</span> <span>"black"</span><span>,</span> <span>500</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>for</span> <span>(</span><span>i</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span> <span>&lt;</span> <span>atoms</span><span>.</span><span>length</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span><span>++</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
      <span>draw</span><span>(</span><span>atoms</span><span>[</span><span>i</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>x</span><span>,</span> <span>atoms</span><span>[</span><span>i</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>y</span><span>,</span> <span>atoms</span><span>[</span><span>i</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>color</span><span>,</span> <span>5</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
    <span>}</span>
    <span>requestAnimationFrame</span><span>(</span><span>update</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span><span>;</span>
  <span>update</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>&lt;/</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></pre></div>

<p dir="auto">Related topics:
Particle Life Simulation,
Primordial Soup - Evolution,
Conway's game of life,
Cellular automata,
Self organzing patterns,</p>
<p dir="auto">This project was inspired by: Jeffery Ventrella's Clusters <a href="http://www.ventrella.com/Clusters/" rel="nofollow">http://www.ventrella.com/Clusters/</a>. I do not have access to Ventrella's code but I guess the main difference of this project from the other particle life projects is that I did not implement collision detection and this made simulating thousands of particles possible in real-time. Also, I added GUI controls to change the parameters in real-time allowing easy fine-tuning and exploration, hence, I was able to find some never-seen-before patterns emerge form some extremely simple models of relations.
The code here is probably an order of magnitude simpler than any other Artificial Life codes out there because I started this code solely as an educational material for non-programmers and general audience to prove the point that complexity can arise from simplicity.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Todos:</h2>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Adding the ability to save and load parameters (so that people can easily share the interesting models they find)</li>
<li>Ability to add more particle types (currently it is fixed to four particle types)</li>
<li>Currently, the biggest bottleneck is the nested for-loops (which calculate the pairwise distance among all particles) making the computational complexity quadratic. It would be amazing if we could find a way around.</li>
<li>Alternative to point 3, computing the pairwise distances are embarrassingly parallel so it can be computed on GPU.</li>
<li>Adding the ability to resize the screen and improving boundary-checking as many fast moving particles can escape the screen bounds.</li>
<li>Adding a more intuitive UI so that it gives the ability for a finer control over the parameters.</li>
<li>Adding a randomize button or, even better, having a simple meta rule to mutate the initial rule continously and recursively. This way the patterns will never get stuck on a local maximum and will keep changing!</li>
<li>A better way to fine-tune is to use an evolutionary algorithm to select and optimize the parameters but one needs to write a fitness function for that. I currently don't know what fitness function corresponds to in the realm of this program. In our world the fitness function is competition and survival of the fittest. However, here we fine-tune and select the parameters that produce interesting patterns for us but the word "interesting" is easier to say than to define!</li>
</ol>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon receives FDA warning letter for supplements with undeclared ingredients (481 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fda.gov/inspections-compliance-enforcement-and-criminal-investigations/warning-letters/amazoncom-inc-662503-12202023</link>
            <guid>38794068</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 15:07:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.fda.gov/inspections-compliance-enforcement-and-criminal-investigations/warning-letters/amazoncom-inc-662503-12202023">https://www.fda.gov/inspections-compliance-enforcement-and-criminal-investigations/warning-letters/amazoncom-inc-662503-12202023</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38794068">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

                                 <article id="main-content" role="article">
          
                                                                <header role="heading" aria-level="1">
                         <div id="block-entityviewcontent-8" data-block-plugin-id="entity_view:node">

        <p>WARNING LETTER</p>
      <h2>Amazon.com, Inc.
            
      <span>
                  MARCS-CMS 662503 —           <time datetime="2023-12-20T00:00:00Z">December 20, 2023</time>
</span></h2>


    

 
</div>






                      </header>
                              
                                                                           <div role="main">

                            
                            
                            
                            
                                              
  
 

                 

  <hr>
 

<div>
  <dl>

              <dt>Delivery Method:</dt> 
        <dd>Via Email
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                              </dd>
      
      
              <dt>Product:</dt> 
        <dd>Drugs<br>Food &amp; Beverages                          
            
            
            
            
            
            
            
             
            
            
            
              
            
            
            </dd>
      
          </dl>
  </div>            


<hr>

<div>
    <dl>
          
          <dt>Issuing Office:</dt>
        
         
          <dd>Center for Drug Evaluation and Research | CDER</dd>
        
         
          <dd><p translate="no"><span>United States</span></p></dd>
        
        
        
        
        
    </dl>
    <dl> 
      
  <div>
    <p>Secondary Issuing Offices</p>
          
              </div>
      </dl></div>  
      
</div>

 

 

<hr>

<p><strong>WARNING LETTER</strong></p>

<p>December 20, 2023</p>

<p><strong>RE: 662503</strong></p>

<p>Dear Mr. Jassy:</p>

<p>This letter concerns your firm’s distribution of products that violate the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (the “FD&amp;C Act”). The United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) purchased on your website, www.amazon.com, products that are labeled as energy enhancing supplements or food, but laboratory analyses confirmed that they contained undeclared and potentially harmful active pharmaceutical ingredients. As discussed further below, your firm is responsible for introducing or delivering for introduction into interstate commerce products that are unapproved new drugs under section 505(a) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 355(a). Furthermore, the products are misbranded drugs under section 502 of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 352. As explained further below, introducing or delivering these products for introduction into interstate commerce is prohibited under sections 301(a), 301(d), and 505(a) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 331(a), 331(d), and 355(a). Your firm is also responsible for introducing or delivering for introduction into interstate commerce a food that is prohibited under section 301(ll) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 331(ll).</p>

<p>FDA purchased “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement,” and “X Max Triple Shot Energy Honey” through your website, www.amazon.com. All of these products were introduced or delivered for introduction into interstate commerce by Amazon via your Fulfillment by Amazon service.<sup><em><strong>1</strong></em></sup> FDA confirmed through laboratory analyses that the “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “Genergy,” and “X Max Triple Shot Energy Honey” products, purchased on www.amazon.com, contained the active pharmaceutical ingredient (API) tadalafil; and the “WeFun,”<sup><em><strong>2</strong></em></sup> “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” products, also purchased on www.amazon.com, contained the API sildenafil. These ingredients are not declared on the products’ labeling.<sup><em><strong>3</strong></em></sup> Sildenafil and tadalafil are phosphodiesterase type-5 (PDE-5) inhibitors and the active ingredients in the FDA-approved prescription drugs Viagra and Cialis, respectively, used to treat erectile dysfunction (ED). These undeclared ingredients may interact with nitrates found in some prescription drugs, such as nitroglycerin, and may lower blood pressure to dangerous levels.</p>

<p>Information on the labels and/or labeling of “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” demonstrates that these products are marketed as dietary supplements<sup><em><strong>4</strong></em></sup>. However, these products do not meet the definition of “dietary supplement” under section 201(ff) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 321(ff). Under section 201(ff)(3)(B)(i) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 321(ff)(3)(B)(i), a product is not a dietary supplement if it includes an article that is approved as a new drug under section 505 of the FD&amp;C Act, unless that article was marketed as a dietary supplement or food before its approval as a drug. Sildenafil and tadalafil were not marketed as dietary supplements or as foods before Viagra and Cialis were FDA-approved. FDA approved Viagra (containing sildenafil as the active ingredient) as a new drug on March 27, 1998. FDA approved Cialis (containing tadalafil as the active ingredient) as a new drug on November 21, 2003. Given that sildenafil and tadalafil were not marketed as dietary supplements or as foods before Viagra and Cialis were FDA-approved, “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement,” which contain sildenafil or tadalafil, are excluded from the definition of “dietary supplement” under section 201(ff)(3)(B)(i) of the FD&amp;C Act.</p>

<p>The remaining product, “X Max Triple Shot Energy Honey,” is a food<sup><em><strong>5</strong></em></sup> that was confirmed by laboratory analysis to contain tadalafil.</p>

<p><u><strong>Unapproved New Drugs</strong></u></p>

<p>The “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” products that are marketed as dietary supplements are drugs as defined by section 201(g)(1) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 321(g)(1), because they are intended for use in the diagnosis, cure, mitigation, treatment, or prevention of disease and/or intended to affect the structure or any function of the body. Examples of claims observed on the labeling, including the outer packaging, that establish the intended use of these products as drugs include, but may not be limited to, the following:</p>

<p><strong>“MANNERS Energy Boost”</strong><br>
From the product label:</p>

<ul><li>“Energy Boost”</li>
</ul><p><strong>“Round 2”</strong><br>
From the product label:</p>

<ul><li>“THE POWER TO GO AGAIN! STRENGTH * ENERGY * ENDURANCE”</li>
</ul><p><strong>“WeFun”</strong><br>
From the product label:</p>

<ul><li>“Energy[,] Performance”</li>
</ul><p><strong>“Genergy”</strong><br>
From the product label:</p>

<ul><li>“ENERGY FOR MEN”</li>
</ul><p><strong>“Big Guys Male Energy Supplement”</strong><br>
From the product label:</p>

<ul><li>From the product name: “Male Energy Supplement”</li>
	<li>“Extreme Power”</li>
	<li>“Focus . . . Energy . . . Mood”</li>
	<li>“500 MG POWER BOOST”</li>
</ul><p><strong>“Mens Maximum Energy Supplement”</strong><br>
From the product label:</p>

<ul><li>The product name: “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement”</li>
	<li>“NEVER ENDING ENERGY!”</li>
	<li>“STRENGTH[,] ENERGY[,] ENDURANCE”</li>
</ul><p>“MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” are not generally recognized as safe and effective for their above referenced uses and, therefore, are “new drugs” under section 201(p) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 321(p). With certain exceptions not applicable here, new drugs may not be legally introduced or delivered for introduction into interstate commerce without prior approval from the FDA, as described in sections 301(d) and 505(a) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 331(d) and 355(a). There are no FDA-approved applications in effect for “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement.” Introduction or delivery of these products into interstate commerce without approved applications violates sections 301(d) and 505(a) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 331(d) and 355(a).</p>

<p><strong>Misbranded Drugs</strong></p>

<p>Additionally, “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” are misbranded under section 502(a) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 352(a). Under section 502(a) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 352(a), a drug is misbranded if its labeling is false or misleading in any particular. Section 201(n) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 321(n), provides that, in determining whether an article’s labeling or advertising “is misleading there shall be taken into account . . . not only representations made or suggested . . . but also the extent to which the labeling or advertising fails to reveal facts material in light of such representations.” The labeling for these products does not declare that they contain PDE-5 inhibitors. The use of PDE-5 inhibitors can be associated with significant safety issues and the risk of serious adverse events. The undeclared PDE-5 inhibitors in these products may pose serious health risks because consumers with underlying medical issues may take the products without knowing that they can cause serious harm or interact in dangerous ways with other drugs they may be taking. For example, PDE-5 inhibitors may interact with nitrates found in some prescription drugs (such as nitroglycerin) and can lower blood pressure to dangerous levels. Consumers with diabetes, high blood pressure, or heart disease often take nitrates. The failure to disclose these ingredients in the products’ labeling renders them misbranded under section 502(a) of the FD&amp;C Act.</p>

<p>“MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” are also misbranded under section 502(f)(1) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 352(f)(1), in that their labeling fails to bear adequate directions for their intended uses. “Adequate directions for use” means directions under which a layman can use a drug safely and for the purposes for which it is intended (see 21 CFR 201.5). Prescription drugs, as defined in section 503(b)(1) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 353(b)(1), include those that, because of their toxicity or other potentiality for harmful effect, and/or the method of their use, and/or the collateral measures necessary for their use, are not safe for use except under supervision of a practitioner licensed by law to administer them. All PDE-5 inhibitors which have been approved for marketing by FDA are limited by an approved new drug application to use under the supervision of a practitioner licensed by law to administer such drugs. “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement,” which contain undeclared sildenafil or tadalafil, are also prescription drugs as defined in section 503(b)(1)(A) of the FD&amp;C Act, and as such, can be used safely only at the direction and under the supervision of a licensed practitioner. Therefore, it is impossible to write “adequate directions for use” for “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” such that a layperson can use these drugs safely for their intended uses. These products are not exempt from the requirements that their labeling bear adequate directions for use by a layperson, 21 CFR 201.100(c)(2) and 201.115, because there are no FDA-approved applications in effect for these products. For these reasons, “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” are misbranded under section 502(f)(1) of the FD&amp;C Act.</p>

<p>The undeclared sildenafil or tadalafil in “MANNERS Energy Boost,” “Round 2,” “WeFun,” “Genergy,” “Big Guys Male Energy Supplement,” and “Mens Maximum Energy Supplement” also causes the products to be misbranded under section 502(f)(2) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 352(f)(2), because their labeling lacks adequate warnings against unsafe dosage or methods or duration of administration or application, in such manner and form, as are necessary for the protection of users. As previously noted, there is a potential for serious health risks associated with these products, particularly since anyone who takes these products would be unaware of the presence of the undeclared drug ingredients and placed at risk for the associated adverse events.</p>

<p>The introduction or delivery for introduction into interstate commerce of these misbranded drug products is a prohibited act under section 301(a) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 331(a).</p>

<p><strong>Prohibited Act under Section 301(ll)</strong></p>

<p>It is a prohibited act under section 301(ll) of the FD&amp;C Act, 21 U.S.C. 331(ll), to introduce or deliver for introduction into interstate commerce any food to which has been added a drug approved under section 505 of the FD&amp;C Act or for which substantial clinical investigations have been instituted and for which the existence of such investigations has been made public. As noted above, FDA purchased “X Max Triple Shot Energy Honey” from www.amazon.com and confirmed through laboratory testing that the product contained undeclared tadalafil. Based on available evidence, FDA has determined that the prohibition in section 301(ll) applies to tadalafil.<sup><em><strong>6</strong></em></sup> The introduction or delivery for introduction into interstate commerce of “X Max Triple Shot Energy Honey” is therefore prohibited under section 301(ll) of the FD&amp;C Act.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>The violations cited in this letter are not intended to be an all-inclusive statement of past or present violations that may exist in connection with the products you distribute. You are responsible for investigating and determining the causes of any violations and for preventing their recurrence or the occurrence of other violations. It is your responsibility to ensure that your firm complies with all requirements of federal law, including FDA regulations.</p>

<p>This letter notifies you of our concerns and provides you an opportunity to address them. Failure to adequately address this matter may result in legal action including, without limitation, seizure and/or injunction. Please submit a written response to this letter within fifteen working days from the date of receipt, explaining the specific steps you have taken to address any violations. Include an explanation of each step being taken to prevent the recurrence of violations, including steps you will take to ensure that Amazon will no longer introduce or deliver for introduction into interstate commerce unapproved new drugs and/or misbranded products with undeclared drug ingredients, as well as copies of related documentation. If you believe that the products you distribute are not in violation of the FD&amp;C Act, include your reasoning and any supporting information for our consideration within fifteen working days from the date of receipt of this letter.</p>

<p>Your response should be sent to U.S. Food and Drug Administration, CDER/OC/Office of Unapproved Drugs and Labeling Compliance by email to FDAAdvisory@fda.hhs.gov.</p>

<p>Sincerely,<br>
/S/</p>

<p>Jill Furman<br>
Director<br>
Office of Compliance<br>
Center for Drug Evaluation and Research<br>
Food and Drug Administration</p>

<p>/S/</p>

<p>Ann M. Oxenham, J.D.<br>
Director<br>
Office of Compliance<br>
Center for Food Safety and Applied Nutrition<br>
Food and Drug Administration</p>

<p>____________________________</p>

<p><em><strong>1</strong></em> Amazon distributed each of the products directly to individual U.S. consumers on behalf of third parties. Each of the products was “fulfilled” by Amazon; your website states, “<em>Fulfillment by Amazon (FBA) is a service that allows you to outsource order fulfillment to Amazon. Sign up for Amazon FBA to send products to Amazon’s global network of fulfillment centers and offer customers free, two-day shipping through Prime. When a customer makes a purchase, Amazon fulfillment specialists can pick, pack, and ship the order. We can also provide customer service and process returns for those orders</em>.” (See https://sell.amazon.com/fulfillment-by-amazon).</p>

<p><em><strong>2</strong></em> On August 25, 2023, Hua Da Trading Inc., dba WeFun Inc., issued a voluntary nationwide recall of WeFun Capsules due to the presence of undeclared sildenafil (see https://www.fda.gov/safety/recalls-market-withdrawals-safety-alerts/hua-da-trading-inc-dba-wefun-inc-issues-voluntary-nationwide-recall-wefun-capsules-due-presence).</p>

<p><em><strong>3</strong></em> U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration, Public Notification: MANNERS Energy Boost contains hidden drug ingredient (February 2, 2023), https://www.fda.gov/drugs/medication-health-fraud/public-notification-manners-energy-boost-contains-hidden-drug-ingredient;<br>
U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration, Public Notification: Round 2 contains hidden drug ingredient (August 22, 2023),https://www.fda.gov/drugs/medication-health-fraud/round-2-contains-hidden-drug-ingredient;<br>
U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration, Public Notification: Genergy contains hidden drug ingredient (August 23, 2023), https://www.fda.gov/drugs/medication-health-fraud/genergy-contains-hidden-drug-ingredient;<br>
U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration, Public Notification: X Max Triple Shot Energy Honey contains hidden drug ingredient (August 23, 2023), https://www.fda.gov/drugs/medication-health-fraud/x-max-triple-shot-energy-honey-contains-hidden-drug-ingredient;<br>
U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration, Public Notification: WeFun contains hidden drug ingredient (August 23, 2023) https://www.fda.gov/drugs/medication-health-fraud/wefun-contains-hidden-drug-ingredient;<br>
U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration, Public Notification: Big Guys Male Energy Supplement contains hidden drug ingredient (August 23, 2023), https://www.fda.gov/drugs/medication-health-fraud/big-guys-male-energy-supplement-contains-hidden-drug-ingredient;<br>
U.S. Food &amp; Drug Administration, Public Notification: Mens Maximum Energy Supplement contains hidden drug ingredient (August 23, 2023), https://www.fda.gov/drugs/medication-health-fraud/mens-maximum-energy-supplement-contains-hidden-drug-ingredient.</p>

<p><em><strong>4</strong></em> The labeling for each of these products includes a Supplement Facts panel.</p>

<p><em><strong>5</strong></em> The labeling for this product includes a Nutritional Information panel.</p>

<p><em><strong>6</strong></em> There is an exception if the substance was marketed in food before the drug was approved or before the substantial clinical investigations involving the drug had been instituted. However, based on available evidence, FDA has concluded that this is not the case for tadalafil.</p>


<!--BEGIN QUALTRICS WEBSITE FEEDBACK SNIPPET-->


<!--END WEBSITE FEEDBACK SNIPPET-->

<!--BEGIN QUALTRICS WEBSITE FEEDBACK SNIPPET-->



              
                                            
              
            </article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New U.S. immigration rules spur more visa approvals for STEM workers (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.science.org/content/article/new-u-s-immigration-rules-spur-more-visa-approvals-stem-workers</link>
            <guid>38793735</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 14:24:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/new-u-s-immigration-rules-spur-more-visa-approvals-stem-workers">https://www.science.org/content/article/new-u-s-immigration-rules-spur-more-visa-approvals-stem-workers</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38793735">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.science.org/content/article/new-u-s-immigration-rules-spur-more-visa-approvals-stem-workers: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>