(ignoring known css parsing error)
(ignoring known css parsing error)
(ignoring known css parsing error)
(ignoring known css parsing error)
(ignoring known css parsing error)
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 19:30:09 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU court rules nuclear energy is clean energy (221 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.weplanet.org/post/eu-court-rules-nuclear-energy-is-clean-energy</link>
            <guid>45224967</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 18:18:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.weplanet.org/post/eu-court-rules-nuclear-energy-is-clean-energy">https://www.weplanet.org/post/eu-court-rules-nuclear-energy-is-clean-energy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45224967">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="ltr" data-id="content-viewer" data-rce-version="10.141.4" data-hook="post-description"><div id="viewer-ua0iq295" data-breakout="normal"><figure data-hook="figure-IMAGE"><div id="ua0iq295" data-hook="image-viewer"><wow-image id="dccfdc_1744e9223bae4f338ddd5d15499c1763~mv2.jpg" data-image-info="{&quot;containerId&quot;:&quot;ua0iq295&quot;,&quot;displayMode&quot;:&quot;fill&quot;,&quot;isLQIP&quot;:true,&quot;isSEOBot&quot;:false,&quot;lqipTransition&quot;:&quot;blur&quot;,&quot;encoding&quot;:&quot;AVIF&quot;,&quot;imageData&quot;:{&quot;width&quot;:9504,&quot;height&quot;:6336,&quot;uri&quot;:&quot;dccfdc_1744e9223bae4f338ddd5d15499c1763~mv2.jpg&quot;,&quot;name&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;displayMode&quot;:&quot;fill&quot;}}" data-motion-part="BG_IMG" data-bg-effect-name="" data-has-ssr-src="true" data-animate-blur=""><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/dccfdc_1744e9223bae4f338ddd5d15499c1763~mv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_147,h_98,al_c,q_80,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01,blur_2,enc_avif,quality_auto/dccfdc_1744e9223bae4f338ddd5d15499c1763~mv2.jpg" alt="Youth climate activists sit with a sign reading Dear Greenpeace You can't power the future with hope." data-pin-url="https://www.weplanet.org/post/eu-court-rules-nuclear-energy-is-clean-energy" data-pin-media="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/dccfdc_1744e9223bae4f338ddd5d15499c1763~mv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_5000,h_3333,al_c,q_90,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01/dccfdc_1744e9223bae4f338ddd5d15499c1763~mv2.jpg" draggable="false"></wow-image></div><div id="viewer-c161e298"><p><figcaption><span>Launching Dear Greenpeace back in 2023</span></figcaption></p></div></figure></div><p dir="auto" id="viewer-n7zk6396"><span><span>When I launched </span><a target="_blank" href="https://www.weplanet.org/deargreenpeace" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-hook="web-link"><span><u><span>Dear Greenpeace</span></u></span></a><span> with my fellow youth climate activists alongside WePlanet two years ago, I had no idea just how quickly the anti-nuclear dominoes would fall across Europe. </span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-88h61415"><span><span>In 2023, and what seems like a lifetime ago, Austria launched their legal action against the European Commission for the inclusion of nuclear energy in the EU Sustainable Finance Taxonomy. At the time they were supported by a bulwark of EU countries and environmental NGOs that opposed nuclear energy. Honestly, it looked like they might win.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-ryc0x156"><span><span>But today, that whole landscape has changed.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-bw9py159"><span><span>Germany, long a symbol of anti-nuclear politics, is beginning to shift. The nuclear phase-outs or bans in the Netherlands, Belgium, Switzerland, Denmark, and Italy are now history. Even Fridays for Future has quietened its opposition, and in some places, embraced nuclear power.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-9x3x3163"><span><span>This moment matters.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-b4w0x166"><span><span>It shows what’s possible when we stick to the science. The evidence only gets clearer by the day that nuclear energy has an extremely low environmental impact across its lifecycle, and strong regulations and safety culture ensure that it remains one of the safest forms of energy available to humanity. </span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-2amni169"><span><span>The European Court of Justice has now fully dismissed Austria’s lawsuit. That ruling doesn’t just uphold nuclear energy’s place in EU green finance rules. It also signals a near-certain defeat for the ongoing Greenpeace case – the very lawsuit that inspired me to launch Dear Greenpeace in the first place.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-s1mp7538"><span><span>But instead of learning from this, Greenpeace is doubling down. Martin Kaiser, Executive Director of Greenpeace Germany, called the court decision “a dark day for the climate”.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-hnk62579"><span><span>Let that sink in. The highest court in the EU just reaffirmed that nuclear energy meets the scientific and environmental standards to be included in sustainable finance, and Greenpeace still refuses to budge.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-kjw4h560"><span><span>Meanwhile, the climate crisis gets worse. Global emissions are not falling fast enough. Billions of people still lack access to clean, reliable electricity. And we are forced to spend time defending proven solutions instead of scaling them.</span></span></p><div id="viewer-3ae5f638" data-breakout="normal"><figure data-hook="figure-IMAGE"><div id="3ae5f638" data-hook="image-viewer"><wow-image id="5caaac_7a93e55d745a4c13a57e7cf2c6f3fb8a~mv2.jpg" data-image-info="{&quot;containerId&quot;:&quot;3ae5f638&quot;,&quot;displayMode&quot;:&quot;fill&quot;,&quot;isLQIP&quot;:true,&quot;isSEOBot&quot;:false,&quot;lqipTransition&quot;:&quot;blur&quot;,&quot;encoding&quot;:&quot;AVIF&quot;,&quot;imageData&quot;:{&quot;width&quot;:4521,&quot;height&quot;:3442,&quot;uri&quot;:&quot;5caaac_7a93e55d745a4c13a57e7cf2c6f3fb8a~mv2.jpg&quot;,&quot;name&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;displayMode&quot;:&quot;fill&quot;}}" data-motion-part="BG_IMG" data-bg-effect-name="" data-has-ssr-src="true" data-animate-blur=""><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/5caaac_7a93e55d745a4c13a57e7cf2c6f3fb8a~mv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_147,h_112,al_c,q_80,usm_0.66_1.00_0.01,blur_2,enc_avif,quality_auto/5caaac_7a93e55d745a4c13a57e7cf2c6f3fb8a~mv2.jpg" alt="Youth Climate Activists stand with a sign saying Fight Fossils Not Nuclear." data-pin-url="https://www.weplanet.org/post/eu-court-rules-nuclear-energy-is-clean-energy" data-pin-media="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/5caaac_7a93e55d745a4c13a57e7cf2c6f3fb8a~mv2.jpg/v1/fill/w_4521,h_3442,al_c,q_90/5caaac_7a93e55d745a4c13a57e7cf2c6f3fb8a~mv2.jpg" draggable="false"></wow-image></div><div id="viewer-xdow6652"><p><figcaption><span>Announcing our inclusion in the case between Greenpeace and the EU Commission</span></figcaption></p></div></figure></div><p dir="auto" id="viewer-depjh684"><span><span>It’s now up to the court whether we will get our time in court to outline the evidence in support of nuclear energy and the important role it can play in the global clean energy transition. Whether in court, on the streets, or in the halls of parliaments across the globe, we will be there to defend the science and ensure that nuclear power can spread the advantages of the modern world across the planet in a sustainable, reliable and dignified way.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-szxti181"><span><span>Austria stands increasingly isolated among a handful of countries that still cling to their opposition to nuclear energy. Their defeat in this vital high stakes topic is a success not just for the nuclear movement, but for the global transition as a whole. </span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-tvkcu260"><span><span>We have made real progress. Together, we’ve helped defend nuclear power in the EU, overturned outdated policies at the World Bank, and secured more technology-neutral language at the UN. These wins are not abstract. They open the door to real investment, real projects, and real emissions cuts.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-5dxe6243"><span><span>But the work is not done.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-a2l0l226"><span><span>We still need to overturn national nuclear bans, unlock more funding, and push democratic countries to support clean energy development abroad: especially where it is most needed to compete with Russia’s growing influence.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-u71i5190"><span><span>The fight will not be done until every single country in the world can boast a clean, reliable energy grid, ready to maintain a modern dignified standard of living, for everyone, everywhere.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-ifug7193"><span><span>This is a great success for the movement and it would not have been possible without the financial support, time and energy given by people like you.</span></span></p><p dir="auto" id="viewer-mcpu5961"><span><span>In Solidarity,</span><span>
</span><span>Ia Aanstoot</span></span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Epistemic Collapse at the WSJ (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=15206</link>
            <guid>45224649</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 17:46:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=15206">https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=15206</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45224649">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-15206">
					

					<!-- .entry-meta -->

					<div>
						<p>For a long time now fundamental theoretical physics has been suffering not just from a slowdown in progress, but from a sort of intellectual collapse (I wrote about this <a href="https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=14999">here</a> a while back in the context of “epistemic collapse”: the collapse of a shared reality, caused by the loss of reliable sources for distinguishing what is true from what is false.). The Wall Street Journal has a new article entitled <a href="https://www.wsj.com/science/physics/the-rise-of-conspiracy-physics-dd79fe36">The Rise of ‘Conspiracy Physics’</a> with summary:</p>
<blockquote><p>Streamers are building huge audiences by attacking academic physics as just another corrupt establishment. Scientists are starting to worry about the consequences.</p></blockquote>
<p>If you replaced “Streamers” by “Sabine Hossenfelder” this would be reasonably accurate, and a serious discussion of this would have been interesting and worthwhile.  Instead, the article is an excellent example of the sort of epistemic collapse we’re now living in.  There’s zero intelligent content about the underlying scientific issues (is fundamental theoretical physics in trouble?), just a random collection of material about podcasts, written by someone who clearly knows nothing about the topic he’s writing about.  The epistemic collapse is total when traditional high-quality information sources like the Wall Street Journal are turned over to uninformed writers getting their information from Joe Rogan podcasts. Any hope of figuring out what is true and what is false is now completely gone.</p>
<p>I was planning on writing something explaining what exactly the WSJ story gets wrong, but now realize this is hopeless (and I’m trying to improve my mental health this week, not make it worse).  Sorting through a pile of misinformation, trying to rebuild something true out of a collapsed mess of some truth buried in a mixture of nonsense and misunderstandings is a losing battle.</p>
<p>Maybe some day our information environment will become healthy again, but for now I’m not sure what to do about this.   Be aware that if you’re trying to understand the state of fundamental theoretical physics, watching Joe Rogan, Piers Morgan, Professor Dave, etc. podcasts is just going to fill your mind with crap. Reading articles about these podcasts is worse. If a podcaster (e.g. Sabine Hossenfelder) has a book, read the book (Lost in Math is pretty good) rather than watching the podcasts.  In general, reading books is a good idea (I can also recommend <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0465092756">this one</a>). </p>
<p><strong>Update:</strong>  John Baez comments <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@johncarlosbaez/115187879181381057">here</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>This quagmire is getting bigger.  It’s another part of what William Gibson recently called the Singularity of Stupid.</p></blockquote>
											</div><!-- .entry-content -->

		
						<div><p>
							This entry was posted in <a href="https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?cat=1" rel="category">Uncategorized</a>. Bookmark the <a href="https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=15206" title="Permalink to Epistemic Collapse at the WSJ" rel="bookmark">permalink</a>.													</p></div><!-- .entry-utility -->
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Corporations are trying, and now failing, to hide job openings from US citizens (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thehill.com/opinion/finance/5498346-corporate-america-has-been-trying-to-hide-job-openings-now-it-is-failing/</link>
            <guid>45223719</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 16:13:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/finance/5498346-corporate-america-has-been-trying-to-hide-job-openings-now-it-is-failing/">https://thehill.com/opinion/finance/5498346-corporate-america-has-been-trying-to-hide-job-openings-now-it-is-failing/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45223719">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://thehill.com/opinion/finance/5498346-corporate-america-has-been-trying-to-hide-job-openings-now-it-is-failing/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A beginner's guide to extending Emacs (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.tjll.net/a-beginners-guide-to-extending-emacs/</link>
            <guid>45223239</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 15:32:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.tjll.net/a-beginners-guide-to-extending-emacs/">https://blog.tjll.net/a-beginners-guide-to-extending-emacs/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45223239">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
<hgroup>
  <h3>
    
    <a href="https://blog.tjll.net/blog-architecture-redux/">«</a>
    
    A Beginner's Guide to Extending Emacs
    
    <a href="https://blog.tjll.net/human-resources-misalignment/">»</a>
    
  </h3>
  <div>
    <ul id="post-details">
      <li> 4 February, 2025</li>
      <li>3,983 words</li>
      <li>17 minute read time</li>
    </ul>
  </div>
</hgroup>


        <section id="content">
	  
<p>
This post isn’t about the virtues of some editors versus others: <a href="https://www.murilopereira.com/the-values-of-emacs-the-neovim-revolution-and-the-vscode-gorilla/">that's already been written by somebody else</a> (and it’s really good) – if you want to know <i>why</i> I use emacs, I suggest reading that instead.
</p>

<p>
<i>This</i> post will help you understand why "extensibility" and "introspectability" are such prominent emacs features even without an emacs lisp background.
Bridging the gap from <a href="https://www.spacemacs.org/">spacemacs</a> or <a href="https://github.com/doomemacs/doomemacs">doom emacs</a> to a bespoke configuration wasn't easy for me because I didn’t know <i>how</i> to learn emacs, so I'm going to stumble through one of my own use cases to demonstrate how this process goes if you're peeking in from outside the emacs ecosystem, <del>horrified</del> curious about how this all works.
</p>

<p>
Let's talk about reStructuredText.
</p>

<div id="table-of-contents" role="doc-toc">
<h4>Table of Contents</h4>
<div id="text-table-of-contents" role="doc-toc">
<ul>
<li><a href="#restructuredtext">reStructuredText</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#a-parentheses-prelude">A Parentheses Prelude</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#extensible-macros">Extensible MACroS</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#completions-abound">Completions Abound</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#gathering-completions">Gathering Completions</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#regexes">Regexes</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#gathering-completions-continued">Gathering Completions: Continued</a></li>
<li><a href="#completing-the-completion-backend">Completing the Completion Backend</a></li>
<li><a href="#dressing-up-the-bones">Dressing Up the Bones</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#mode-hooks">Mode Hooks</a></li>
<li><a href="#other-files">Other Files</a></li>
<li><a href="#fancy-completion">Fancy Completion</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="#summary">Summary</a></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-restructuredtext">
<h4 id="restructuredtext">reStructuredText</h4>
<div id="text-restructuredtext">
<p>
At my day job I write <a href="https://docs.bowtie.works/">our user documentation</a> using <a href="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/master/">Sphinx</a>.
It expects my stilted prose in <code>.rst</code> format, which is kind of like Markdown if you squint.
</p>

<p>
I do an awful lot of cross-referencing between <i>references</i> (or <code>refs</code>) to link concepts across the documentation.
You define a reference like this:
</p>

<p><span><span>ReST</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used for directives and roles.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used for all other defining constructs.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>.. _code_example:</span></code>
<code></code>
<code><span>.. code::</span></code>
<code>   echo "HELP I'M TRAPPED IN A CODE EXAMPLE"</code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
…and then link to it later like this:
</p>

<p><span><span>ReST</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used for field names and interpreted text.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used for directives and roles.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code>This <span>:ref:</span><span>`doesn't look like anything to me &lt;code_example&gt;`</span>.</code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
…or like this (if the <code>ref</code> is associated with a title of some sort):
</p>

<p><span><span>ReST</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used for field names and interpreted text.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used for directives and roles.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code>Don't say <span>:ref:</span><span>`code_example`</span>.</code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
My problem is that I have an <i>assload</i> of references across the all of the documentation and my brain cannot recall them on the spot.
What I really need is the ability to call up the list of references to easily discover and select from that list – this is basically auto-completion but for documentation headers (or titles).
</p>

<p>
I am ready to write some shitty elisp <a href="http://landoflisp.com/">with the help of aliens</a>.
</p>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-a-parentheses-prelude">
<h5 id="a-parentheses-prelude">A Parentheses Prelude</h5>
<p>
Before we dig into emacs' guts, here are some principles that I learned after my first elisp experiments that might help somebody digging into this ecosystem for the first time:
</p>
<div id="outline-container-1-emacs-wants-you-to-extend-it">
<h6 id="1-emacs-wants-you-to-extend-it">1. Emacs <i>Wants</i> You to Extend It</h6>
<div>
<p>
I haven't written plugins for other editors extensively, but I <i>can</i> tell you this: emacs doesn't just make deep customization available, but it actively <i>encourages</i> you to make an absolute customization <del>messes</del> masterpieces.
Core editor functions aren't just documented, but often include tidbits about "you probably want to see this other variable" or "here's how you should use this".
</p>

<p>
Not only that, but emacs happily hands you functions shaped like nuclear warheads like <code><span>advice-add</span></code> (that let you override any function) that can absolutely obliterate your editor if you hold it the wrong way.
Of course, this also grants you <b>unlimited power</b>.
</p>

<p>
Remember that emacs is designed to be torn apart and rearranged.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-2-geriatric-software">
<h6 id="2-geriatric-software">2. Geriatric Software</h6>
<div>
<p>
The first public release of GNU emacs happened in 1985.
Literally <i>40 years</i> of development sits inside of emacs and its developers are <b>still</b> adding non-trivial features (native language server support landed in version 29 in 2023).
</p>

<p>
The ecosystem is vast and the language has evolved for a long time.
There's nearly always something useful if you need a particular piece of functionality, so even moreso than with other ecosystems: remember to do your homework first.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-3-lisp-for-for-the-un-lisped">
<h6 id="3-lisp-for-for-the-un-lisped">3. Lisp for for the un-Lisped</h6>
<div>
<p>
The syntax is polarizing, I know.
Gurus will wince when I get this wrong, but:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Writing lisp is like writing any other code, just with the parentheses wrapping <i>everything</i> instead of just <i>arguments</i>. <code><span>print</span><span>(</span><span>"Macrodata Refinement"</span><span>)</span></code> becomes <code><span>(</span><span>print</span> <span>"Macrodata Refinement"</span><span>)</span></code></li>
<li>Sometimes you don't get functions, you get macros that behave special ways.
For example, <code><span>let</span></code> sets variables for an inner block of code.
Like this: <code><span>(</span><span>let</span> <span>(</span>name <span>"Mark S."</span><span>)</span> <span>(</span><span>print</span> name<span>)</span><span>)</span></code></li>
<li>Lispers say "this is actually data and not calling code" by doing this with single quotes: <code><span>'</span><span>(</span><span>"list"</span> <span>"of"</span> <span>"strings"</span><span>)</span></code></li>
</ul>

<p>
I'm out of my depth in lisp, but if you're a novice, those notes might help.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-extensible-macros">
<h4 id="extensible-macros">Extensible MACroS</h4>
<div id="text-extensible-macros">
<p>
With that prelude out of the way, let's begin.
</p>

<p>
Inside of emacs you can call up a list of potential <i>completions</i> by using the keyboard shortcut <kbd>M-.</kbd> (that’s "hit the meta key along with period", where "meta" is the <kbd>Alt</kbd> key for me).
This applies in a wide variety of scenarios, like when completing class names or variables.
If we want to ask emacs to hand us a list of potential references, then the system we want to hook into is this <i>completions</i> system.
</p>

<p>
(This is the only time I'll assume we know where to go without crawling through documentation. You could discover it yourself looking for "<code>completion</code>" or similar string in emacs docs).
</p>

<p>
To start our hero’s journey, we figure out what the hell <kbd>M-.</kbd> actually <i>does</i>.
We can ask emacs this by calling the function <code><span>describe-key</span></code>, which is bound to <kbd>C-h k</kbd>.
Hitting <kbd>Ctrl-h</kbd>, then <kbd>k</kbd>, then <kbd>M-.</kbd> drops us into a help buffer that looks like this:
</p>

<pre id="org6bbb9dc"><code>M-. runs the command completion-at-point (found in</code>
<code>evil-insert-state-map), which is an interactive native-compiled Lisp</code>
<code>function in ‘minibuffer.el’.</code>
<code></code>
<code>It is bound to M-..</code>
<code></code>
<code>(completion-at-point)</code>
<code></code>
<code>Perform completion on the text around point.</code>
<code>The completion method is determined by ‘completion-at-point-functions’.</code>
<code></code>
<code>  Probably introduced at or before Emacs version 23.2.</code>
</pre>

<p>
We have the next breadcrumb to follow, which is the variable <code><span>completion-at-point-functions</span></code>.
Running <code><span>completion-at-point</span></code> by hitting <kbd>M-.</kbd> consults that variable to hand us completion candidates, so we <code><span>describe-variable</span></code> it with <kbd>C-h v</kbd> and then choose <code><span>completion-at-point-functions</span></code> from the list of variables:
</p>

<pre id="org56c73d2"><code>completion-at-point-functions is a variable defined in ‘minibuffer.el’.</code>
<code></code>
<code>Its value is (cape-dict cape-file tags-completion-at-point-function)</code>
<code></code>
<code>Special hook to find the completion table for the entity at point.</code>
<code>Each function on this hook is called in turn without any argument and</code>
<code>should return either nil, meaning it is not applicable at point,</code>
<code>or a function of no arguments to perform completion (discouraged),</code>
<code>or a list of the form (START END COLLECTION . PROPS)</code>
</pre>

<p>
…and it goes on from there.
You can see some existing completion functions in there: I use a package called <a href="https://github.com/minad/cape">cape</a> to offer helpful suggestions like file paths if I start typing in something like <code>./filename</code>.
</p>

<p>
The description for this variable instructs us about how to add our own functions (scary!)
You’ll note that emacs calls this a "hook", which is most often just a term used to describe a variable that is a list of functions that get called at a specific time (hooks show up everywhere).
</p>

<p>
I elided the full description for <code><span>completion-at-point-functions</span></code> – which is lengthy! – but if you parse it all out, you learn the following:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Your completion at point function should return either <code>nil</code> (the elisp "null") – which means your completion function doesn’t apply right now – or another function (which emacs discourages), or a list, which is what we’ll do because it sounds like the most-correct thing to do.</li>
<li>The list we return is <code><span>(</span>START END COLLECTION . PROPS<span>)</span></code>:
<ul>
<li><code>START</code> and <code>END</code> should be positions in the buffer between which emacs will replace the completed symbol with our candidate.
That is, if your cursor is calling a method on a Python object like <code>file.ope|</code> (where the bar is your cursor), emacs will replace just <code>ope</code> when you select <code>open</code> from a list of completions and not the entire <code>file.ope</code> string.</li>
<li><code>COLLECTION</code> is the juicy bit. The documentation calls it a completion "table", and there’s probably hidden meaning there, but you can just return a list of candidates and move on with your day, which is what I'll do.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<p>
Okay, so we need to write something to find the bounds of a string to replace and a function that returns that list.
</p>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-completions-abound">
<h5 id="completions-abound">Completions Abound</h5>
<div id="text-completions-abound">
<p>
I fooled around with some regular expressions for a while until I did the <i>right</i> thing and examined how other completion backends do it.
If you have the package installed, the aforementioned <code><span>cape-file</span></code> function gives us a hint: hit <kbd>M-x</kbd>, then choose <code><span>find-function</span></code>, select <code><span>cape-file</span></code>, and poke around. You’ll find the use of a function called <code><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span></code>.
Describing it with <kbd>C-h f</kbd> <code><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span></code> gives us:
</p>

<pre id="orgdb3711b"><code>Determine the start and end buffer locations for the THING at point.</code>
<code>THING should be a symbol specifying a type of syntactic entity.</code>
<code>Possibilities include ‘symbol’, ‘list’, ‘sexp’, ‘defun’, ‘number’,</code>
<code>‘filename’, ‘url’, ‘email’, ‘uuid’, ‘word’, ‘sentence’, ‘whitespace’,</code>
<code>‘line’, and ‘page’.</code>
</pre>

<p>
And <i>that</i> is useful for our <code>START</code> and <code>END</code> needs.
You can take it for a test drive at any time with <kbd>M-:</kbd> <code><span>(</span><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span> <span>'</span><span>word</span><span>)</span></code> to see where emacs thinks the <i>word</i> at your cursor starts and ends.
This is a common theme when developing elisp: try out functions all the time within the editor since they’re near at hand.
</p>

<p>
The argument to <code><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span></code> is a symbol for a literal <i>thing</i> that is predefined by the function <code><span>define-thing-chars</span></code>.
We pass <code><span>define-thing-chars</span></code> a name for our "thing" and a regex, and we can call <code><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span></code> with it from that point on.
The function documentation in <code>thingatpt.el</code> that emacs refers you to explains more if you’re interested.
</p>

<p>
<code><span>define-thing-chars</span></code> expects a string with characters to put into a regex character class (like <code>[...]</code>) - just any valid character.
This is a pretty standard character class and we can start with something super simple.
I can’t be bothered to look up whatever the reStructedText spec is for references, but let’s start with "word characters, dashes, and underscores".
That expressed as a "thing" looks like this:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight keywords.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>define-thing-chars</span> rst-ref <span>"[:alpha:]_-"</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Now we have a <i>thing</i> called <code>rst-ref</code> we can use with <code><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span></code>.
In typical emacs fashion, we can run elisp ad-hoc in our editor just to tinker, so let’s do that now.
</p>

<p>
Remember: we’re trying to write a function to give us the <code>start</code> and <code>end</code> of whatever piece of text we intend for a completion to replace.
Let’s try it out: in any sort of buffer, put a piece of fake <code>.rst</code> text with a reference, like this:
</p>

<p><span><span>ReST</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used for field names and interpreted text.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used for directives and roles.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code>This is a <span>:ref:</span><span>`other-reference`</span>.</code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Place your point somewhere within "<code>other-reference</code>" and try out your <code>thing</code>:
</p>

<p>
<kbd>M-:</kbd> <code><span>(</span><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span> <span>'</span><span>rst-ref</span><span>)</span></code>
</p>

<p>
You’ll see something like <code><span>(</span>number . number<span>)</span></code> in the echo area (the little minibuffer at the bottom of the emacs window frame).
Congratulations!
We’ve got the first part of the problem solved.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-gathering-completions">
<h4 id="gathering-completions">Gathering Completions</h4>
<div id="text-gathering-completions">
<p>
Recall the structure of what our "completion backend" needs to return to emacs:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span>START END COLLECTION . PROPS<span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
We can construct <code>START</code> and <code>END</code> with <code><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span></code>, now we just need <code>COLLECTION</code>, which is a list of potential candidates.
</p>

<p>
Conceptually the task isn’t hard: we should find all instances of strings of the form:
</p>

<p><span><span>ReST</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used for all other defining constructs.</span></li></ul></div>

<p>
in our document and capture <code>my-reference</code>.
Where do we start?
</p>

<p>
Once again you can rely on discovery mechanisms like searching for functions that <i>sound</i> related (by browsing <code><span>describe-function</span></code>) or look at existing code.
Personally, I found this:
</p>

<pre id="orge9859ee"><code>(re-search-forward REGEXP &amp;optional BOUND NOERROR COUNT)</code>
<code></code>
<code>Search forward from point for regular expression REGEXP.</code>
</pre>

<p>
The documentation refers you to some other related functions, like this one:
</p>

<pre id="org335f041"><code>(match-beginning SUBEXP)</code>
<code></code>
<code>Return position of start of text matched by last search.</code>
<code>SUBEXP, a number, specifies which parenthesized expression in the last</code>
<code>regexp.</code>
</pre>

<p>
So we can <code><span>(</span><span>re-search-forward</span><span>)</span></code> for something then invoke <code><span>(</span><span>match-beginning</span> 1<span>)</span></code>, for example, if we used a regex capture group to grab the reference’s label.
Cool: we can start there.
</p>

<p>
As you get deeper into elisp you’ll find that regular expressions are <i>everywhere</i>, and this case is no different.
We need a solid regex to search through a reStructuredText buffer (and honor any quirks in emacs’ regular expression engine), so we’ll use this opportunity to kick the tires on <i>interactively</i> developing regular expressions in emacs.
</p>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-regexes">
<h5 id="regexes">Regexes</h5>
<div id="text-regexes">
<p>
Geriatric millennial software engineers like myself grew up on <a href="https://regexr.com/">https://regexr.com/</a> when it was still a Flash application.
Unless you’re a masochist that lives and breathes regular expressions, it’s kind of hard to develop a good regex without live feedback, which sites like <a href="https://regexr.com/">https://regexr.com/</a> provide.
</p>

<p>
Little did I know that emacs comes with its own live regular expression builder and it's goooood.
</p>

<p>
Within any emacs buffer, run <kbd>M-x</kbd> <code><span>re-builder</span></code> to open the regex builder window split alongside the current buffer.
If I then enter the string <code><span>"re-</span><span><span>\\</span></span><span><span>(</span></span><span>builder</span><span><span>\\</span></span><span><span>)</span></span><span>"</span></code> into that buffer, that string a) gets highlighted in my original buffer and b) the capture group gets highlighted in its own unique group color.
</p>

<p>
You can do this all day long to fine-tune a regular expression, but there’s yet <i>another</i> trick when writing regular expressions, which is to use the <code><span>rx</span></code> macro.
</p>

<p>
My previous example regular expression <code><span>"re-</span><span><span>\\</span></span><span><span>(</span></span><span>builder</span><span><span>\\</span></span><span><span>)</span></span><span>"</span></code> works, but the quirks when writing emacs regular expressions pile up quickly: escaping characters is one example but there are more, too.
</p>

<p>
Instead, the <code><span>rx</span></code> macro will let you define a regular expression in lisp-y form and evaluate it into a typical string-based regular expression you can use normally, so it works any place emacs expects a string-based regular expression.
For example, if you evaluate this with <kbd>M-:</kbd>:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight keywords.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>rx</span> <span>"re-"</span> <span>(</span>group <span>"builder"</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
This is what emacs returns:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font for backslashes in Lisp regexp grouping constructs.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li></ul></div>

<p>
Identical!
The <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/elisp/Rx-Constructs.html"><code>rx</code> documentation</a> explains all the constructs available to you.
</p>

<p>
Jumping back to <code><span>re-builder</span></code>, with the <code><span>re-builder</span></code> window active, invoke <kbd>M-x</kbd> <code>reb-change-syntax</code> and choose <code><span>rx</span></code>.
Now you can interactively build regular expressions with the <code><span>rx</span></code> macro!
In the <code><span>re-builder</span></code> window, you’ve got to enter a weird syntax to get it to take <code><span>rx</span></code> constructs (I’m… not sure why this is), but you end up with the same outcome:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>'</span><span>(</span><span>:</span> <span>"re-"</span> <span>(</span>group <span>"builder"</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Watch the regex get highlighted live just as it was in the string-based regex mode.
</p>

<p>
To bring this full circle, hop into a buffer with an example <code>.rst</code> document like this one:
</p>

<p><span><span>ReST</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used for all other defining constructs.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used for the adornment of a section header.</span></li>
<li><span>Default font for section title text at level 1.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>A Heading</span></code>
<code><span>=========</span></code>
<code></code>
<code><span>.. _my-reference:</span></code>
<code></code>
<code>Link to me!</code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Using our newfound <code><span>re-builder</span></code> knowledge, let’s build a regex interactively to make short work of it:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Invoke <kbd>M-x</kbd> <code><span>re-builder</span></code></li>
<li>Change the engine to something easier with <kbd>M-x</kbd> <code>reb-change-syntax</code> and choose <code><span>rx</span></code></li>
<li>Start trying out solutions</li>
</ul>

<p>
I’ll refer here to the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/elisp/Rx-Constructs.html">rx constructs documentation</a> which lists out all the possibilities that you can plug into the <code><span>rx</span></code> macro.
Here’s a recorded example of what developing it looks like from start to finish, ending up with a functional <code><span>rx</span></code> construct:
</p>



<p>
Live-highlighting regex development.
Nice.
If you add more groups, more colors show up.
In this example the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/elisp/Rx-Constructs.html">rx constructs</a> I’m using are:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Any strings end up as literal matches</li>
<li>Special symbols <code>bol</code> and <code>eol</code> for "beginning of line" and "end of line", respectively</li>
<li>Symbols like <code>+</code> behave like their regex counterparts ("at least one")</li>
<li>Some symbols like <code>not</code> are nice little shortcuts (in this case, to negate the next form)</li>
</ul>

<p>
Because <code><span>rx</span></code> is a macro, we don’t ever actually <i>need</i> to compile its regular expressions to use elsewhere - we can always just use <code><span>rx</span></code> when we need a regex.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-gathering-completions-continued">
<h4 id="gathering-completions-continued">Gathering Completions: Continued</h4>
<div id="text-gathering-completions-continued">
<p>
Okay, we've cut our teeth on emacs regular expressions.
Let's use 'em.
(Not our teeth. Regexes.)
</p>

<p>
To start, let's save our reStructuredText regular expression to find a <code>ref</code> so we can easily grab it later.
I'll save the one I came up with to the name <code>tmp/re</code> (this name is arbitrary, I drop temporary variables into <code>tmp/&lt;name&gt;</code> out of habit)
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight built-in function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight keywords.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>setq</span> tmp/re <span>(</span><span>rx</span> bol <span>".."</span> <span>(</span><span>+</span> blank<span>)</span> <span>"_"</span> <span>(</span>group <span>(</span><span>+</span> <span>(</span><span>not</span> <span>":"</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>":"</span> eol<span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Now we can reference it easily.
I mentioned before that <code><span>re-search-forward</span></code> accepts a regex, so let's hop into a reStructuredText rev up the regex.
</p>

<p>
Here's my sample text that I'll work with:
</p>

<p><span><span>ReST</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used for directives and roles.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used for all other defining constructs.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used for the adornment of a section header.</span></li>
<li><span>Default font for section title text at level 1.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>A Title</span></code>
<code><span>=======</span></code>
<code></code>
<code>Beware the Jabberwock, my son.</code>
<code></code>
<code><span>.. _my-reference:</span></code>
<code></code>
<code>You are like a little baby. Watch this.</code>
<code></code>
<code><span>.. _code-sample:</span></code>
<code></code>
<code><span>.. code::</span> python</code>
<code></code>
<code>   print("emacs needs telemetry")</code>
<code></code>
<code>The end?</code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
The <code><span>re-search-forward</span></code> documentation indicates that it starts at the <code>point</code>'s current position, so head to the start of the buffer, hit <kbd>M-:</kbd> to enter the elisp <code>Eval</code> prompt, and try:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight built-in function names.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>re-search-forward</span> tmp/re<span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
This is anticlimactic because you'll just see the point move to the end of one of the references.
BUT.
This means that the search succeeded.
So… what now?
</p>

<p>
More reading in the <code><span>re-search-forward</span></code> documentation will educate you about emacs <i>global match data</i>.
In non-functional-programming style, functions like <code><span>match-beginning</span></code> and <code><span>match-end</span></code> serve to interrogate a global state that functions like <code><span>re-search-forward</span></code> will modify.
In concise terms, our regular expression defines one match group and we can grab it with <code><span>(</span><span>match-string-no-properties</span> 1<span>)</span></code> to get the first group match (<code><span>match-string</span></code> will return a string with "properties", which is a bunch of data like font styling that we don't want).
</p>

<p>
Within our example buffer, executing this after the regex search should return our match:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight function names.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>match-string-no-properties</span> 1<span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
I see <code>"my-reference"</code> from this command.
Now we're cooking like it's 1985, baby.
You can enter the minibuffer again with <kbd>M-:</kbd>, press <kbd>↑</kbd> to find the <code><span>re-search-forward</span></code> command again, and repeat this process again to watch the point move to the next match, after which you can see the matched string with <code><span>match-string-no-properties</span></code>.
</p>

<p>
Note that running this a few times will eventually error out after no matches exist past your point.
We'll address this.
</p>

<p>
If you're a human (or Claude) at this point, you can see the path ahead – we need to write some elisp that will:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Move the point to the beginning of the buffer (important, remember that <code><span>re-search-forward</span></code> relies upon the current position of your point)</li>
<li>Iteratively execute an <code><span>re-search-forward</span></code> command to aggregate reference targets</li>
<li>Conclude when there aren't any more matches</li>
</ul>

<p>
I'll start with the code and then explain which demons the parentheses are summoning afterward:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight special form names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight built-in function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight keywords.</span></li>
<li></li>
<li></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>;; </span><span>This function will save the current position of the cursor and then</span></code>
<code><span>;; </span><span>return it to this position once the code that it wraps has finished</span></code>
<code><span>;; </span><span>executing, which lets us hop around the buffer without driving the</span></code>
<code><span>;; </span><span>programmer insane. Important for any functions that move the point</span></code>
<code><span>;; </span><span>around.</span></code>
<code><span>(</span><span>save-excursion</span></code>
<code>  <span>;; </span><span>progn is a simple function that just executes each lisp form</span></code>
<code>  <span>;; </span><span>step-by-step.</span></code>
<code>  <span>(</span><span>progn</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>Step one: go to the beginning of the buffer.</span></code>
<code>    <span>(</span><span>goto-char</span> <span>(</span><span>point-min</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>Step two: loop</span></code>
<code>    <span>;;</span><span></span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>cl-loop is a macro with a long and venerable heritage stemming</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>from the common lisp family of macros, which it mimics the</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>behavior of. You could spend hours honing your ability to wield</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>the common lisp `loop` macro, but we'll just explain the parts</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>we're using:</span></code>
<code>    <span>;;</span><span></span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>`while` runs the loop until its argument evalutates to a falsy</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>value. We can overload our use of `re-search-forward` here: we</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>can use it to step our loop forward each time and also rely</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>upon it returning `nil` once it stops matching substrings in</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>the buffer and we should finish up.</span></code>
<code>    <span>(</span><span>cl-loop</span> <span>while</span> <span>(</span><span>re-search-forward</span></code>
<code>                    <span>(</span><span>rx</span> bol <span>".."</span> <span>(</span><span>+</span> blank<span>)</span> <span>"_"</span> <span>(</span>group <span>(</span><span>+</span> <span>(</span><span>not</span> <span>":"</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>":"</span> eol<span>)</span></code>
<code>                    <span>;; </span><span>The aforementioned `while` termination case</span></code>
<code>                    <span>;; </span><span>relies upon this `t` parameter, which says</span></code>
<code>                    <span>;; </span><span>"don't error out with no matches, just return</span></code>
<code>                    <span>;; </span><span>nil". Once no more matches are found, the loop</span></code>
<code>                    <span>;; </span><span>exits.</span></code>
<code>                    nil <span>t</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>             <span>;; </span><span>The `collect` keyword instructs `cl-loop` how to form</span></code>
<code>             <span>;; </span><span>its return value. We can helpfully summarize the regex</span></code>
<code>             <span>;; </span><span>match item by pulling out the global match data.</span></code>
<code>             collect <span>(</span><span>match-string-no-properties</span> 1<span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
The code is less intimidating without comments:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight special form names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight built-in function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight keywords.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>save-excursion</span></code>
<code>  <span>(</span><span>progn</span></code>
<code>    <span>(</span><span>goto-char</span> <span>(</span><span>point-min</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>    <span>(</span><span>cl-loop</span> <span>while</span> <span>(</span><span>re-search-forward</span></code>
<code>                    <span>(</span><span>rx</span> bol <span>".."</span> <span>(</span><span>+</span> blank<span>)</span> <span>"_"</span> <span>(</span>group <span>(</span><span>+</span> <span>(</span><span>not</span> <span>":"</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>":"</span> eol<span>)</span></code>
<code>                    nil <span>t</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>             collect <span>(</span><span>match-string-no-properties</span> 1<span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Without belaboring the point, you can – like I did – discover most of these functions by skimming existing elisp code and using it as a launch pad.
Many of these functions are bog standard and show up all over the place in emacs packages (<code><span>save-excursion</span></code>, <code><span>progn</span></code>, <code><span>goto-char</span></code>…)
</p>

<p>
Here's the result when I run this code against our example <code>.rst</code> file:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>"my-reference"</span> <span>"code-sample"</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Looks good!
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-completing-the-completion-backend">
<h4 id="completing-the-completion-backend">Completing the Completion Backend</h4>
<div id="text-completing-the-completion-backend">
<p>
We're now armed with the ability to:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Identify the bounds of the string we want to replace, and</li>
<li>Collect a list of targets for completion candidates</li>
</ul>

<p>
We are <i>so close</i>.
Recall the description of the variable we need to modify:
</p>

<pre id="orgb0e2210"><code>completion-at-point-functions is a variable defined in ‘minibuffer.el’.</code>
<code></code>
<code>Its value is (cape-dict cape-file tags-completion-at-point-function)</code>
<code></code>
<code>Special hook to find the completion table for the entity at point.</code>
<code>Each function on this hook is called in turn without any argument and</code>
<code>should return either nil, meaning it is not applicable at point,</code>
<code>or a function of no arguments to perform completion (discouraged),</code>
<code>or a list of the form (START END COLLECTION . PROPS)</code>
</pre>

<p>
To return the list that <code><span>completion-at-point-functions</span></code> expects, we already have the ability to identify the bounds of a <code>thing</code> and sweep up a list of candidates in our buffer.
Note the comment about returning <code>nil</code>: we probably don't <i>always</i> want to run our backend, so we should short-circuit our function to eagerly return nil to avoid tying up emacs with a regex loop we don't need.
</p>

<p>
With all that said, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Nye">consider the following</a>:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight special form names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font to highlight quoted Lisp symbols.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight built-in function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight documentation embedded in program code.
It is typically used for special documentation comments or strings.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight strings.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight keywords.</span></li>
<li></li>
<li></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>;; </span><span>Our reStructuredText reference "thing"</span></code>
<code><span>(</span><span>define-thing-chars</span> rst-ref <span>"[:alpha:]_-"</span><span>)</span></code>
<code></code>
<code><span>(</span><span>defun</span> <span>my/rst-internal-reference-capf</span> <span>()</span></code>
<code>  <span>"Completion backend for buffer reStructuredText references"</span></code>
<code>  <span>;; </span><span>Only applies when we're within a reference - outside of a</span></code>
<code>  <span>;; </span><span>reference, we bail out with nil.</span></code>
<code>  <span>(</span><span>when</span> <span>(</span><span>looking-back</span> <span>(</span><span>rx</span> <span>":ref:`"</span> <span>(</span><span>*</span> <span>(</span><span>not</span> <span>"`"</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>(</span><span>point-at-bol</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>    <span>;; </span><span>Get potential bounds for the string to replace</span></code>
<code>    <span>(</span><span>let*</span> <span>(</span><span>(</span>bounds <span>(</span><span>or</span> <span>(</span><span>bounds-of-thing-at-point</span> <span>'</span><span>rst-ref</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>                       <span>;; </span><span>Fallback to the current position</span></code>
<code>                       <span>(</span><span>cons</span> <span>(</span><span>point</span><span>)</span> <span>(</span><span>point</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>           <span>(</span>start <span>(</span><span>car</span> bounds<span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>           <span>(</span>end <span>(</span><span>cdr</span> bounds<span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>           <span>;; </span><span>Collect all reference candidates</span></code>
<code>           <span>(</span>candidates</code>
<code>            <span>;; </span><span>Our previously-noted reference collector</span></code>
<code>            <span>(</span><span>save-excursion</span></code>
<code>              <span>(</span><span>progn</span></code>
<code>                <span>(</span><span>goto-char</span> <span>(</span><span>point-min</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>                <span>(</span><span>cl-loop</span> <span>while</span> <span>(</span><span>re-search-forward</span></code>
<code>                                <span>(</span><span>rx</span> bol <span>".."</span> <span>(</span><span>+</span> blank<span>)</span> <span>"_"</span> <span>(</span>group <span>(</span><span>+</span> <span>(</span><span>not</span> <span>":"</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>":"</span> eol<span>)</span></code>
<code>                                nil <span>t</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>                         collect <span>(</span><span>match-string-no-properties</span> 1<span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
<code>      <span>;; </span><span>Return value suitable for `completion-at-point-functions`</span></code>
<code>      <span>(</span><span>list</span> start end candidates<span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<ul>
<li>We're following some naming conventions by calling this a "<code>capf</code>" (a "completion-at-point function) and prefixing with <code>my/</code> (a habit to namespace your own functions)</li>
<li>Our short-circuit takes the form of using <code><span>looking-back</span></code> to ask, "are we inside of a reStructuredText reference"?
Note the use of <code><span>rx</span></code> here again to clean up our lisp.</li>
<li>We use our <code>rst-ref</code> <code>thing</code> to easily snag the <code>start</code> and <code>end</code> of the string to replace – note our fallback to <i>just</i> the immediate point if we can't find the bounds of our <code>thing</code>.</li>
</ul>

<p>
We wrap it all up with <code>list</code>.
Personally, even as somebody relatively new to writing Lisps, I find the code pleasant to read and self-evident.
We did a lot in 17 lines of code!
</p>

<p>
Inside of our test <code>.rst</code> buffer, we can test drive this function.
First, invoke <kbd>M-x</kbd> <code><span>eval-defun</span></code> with your cursor somewhere in the function to evaluate it, which makes <code>my/rst-internal-reference-capf</code> available.
Then run:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font to highlight quoted Lisp symbols.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight variable names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight function names.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>add-hook</span> <span>'</span><span>completion-at-point-functions</span> <span>'</span><span>my/rst-internal-reference-capf</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
Huzzah!
Our function is now live in emacs' completion framework.
You can trigger the completion by calling <code>completion-at-point</code> at a relevant spot in a buffer.
Many batteries-included emacs distributions like spacemacs or doom emacs slap nice-looking porcelain on top of the completion framework; here's an example that uses the <a href="https://github.com/minad/corfu">corfu</a> package:
</p>



<p>
Congratulations, you've extended emacs for the first time!
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-dressing-up-the-bones">
<h4 id="dressing-up-the-bones">Dressing Up the Bones</h4>
<p>
Okay, this is a pretty basic setup.
You could improve it in <i>many</i> ways, but here are a few ideas about potential directions:
</p>
<div id="outline-container-mode-hooks">
<h5 id="mode-hooks">Mode Hooks</h5>
<div id="text-mode-hooks">
<p>
Manually adding your custom completion function to the <code><span>completion-at-point-functions</span></code> hook is tedious, but there's a way to automate it.
Recall that in emacs parlance, a "hook" is usually a <i>variable</i> that holds a <i>list of functions</i> that get called at a <i>specific time</i>.
</p>

<p>
If you use <a href="https://docutils.sourceforge.io/docs/user/emacs.html">rst-mode</a>, then opening an <code>.rst</code> file will drop you into <code><span>rst-mode</span></code> and implicitly call the <code><span>rst-mode-hook</span></code> functions.
That means that this line is sufficient to integrate our completion function:
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font to highlight quoted Lisp symbols.</span></li>
<li><span>Font to highlight Lisp quotes.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight keywords.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight variable names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight function names.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>add-hook</span> <span>'</span><span>rst-mode-hook</span> <span>(</span><span>lambda</span> <span>()</span> </code>
<code>    <span>(</span><span>add-hook</span> <span>'</span><span>completion-at-point-functions</span>  <span>#'</span><span>my/rst-internal-reference-capf</span> 0 <span>t</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>

<p>
This says: "when I open an <code>.rst</code> file, run this lambda that modifies <code><span>completion-at-point-functions</span></code> <i>only</i> for this buffer by adding my internal reference completion function".
It's a little nested which makes it less obvious with the two <code>add-hook</code> calls.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-other-files">
<h5 id="other-files">Other Files</h5>
<div id="text-other-files">
<p>
Okay, our example works for references in the <i>same buffer</i> but this is sort of pointless for uses <i>across</i> files.
</p>

<p>
You can solve this too, although my post is already too long so we won't solve this step-by-step.
However, here's how <i>I</i> solved it:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Turn my <code>capf</code> into a minor mode that manages the completion variables</li>
<li>Doesn't search the buffer every time but instead does so once and then rebuilds it with a hook in <code><span>after-change-functions</span></code>, saving it to a hash cache</li>
<li>Walk all <code>.rst</code> files in the current project and run the reference collection function for each, storing the results into a hash cache for all files that don't have live buffers</li>
<li>When it comes time to call the completion function, combine the hash for completions for files without buffers along with each <code>.rst</code> buffer's cached list of references</li>
</ul>

<p>
It sounds complicated, but it works!
Functions like <code><span>with-temp-buffer</span></code> make this pretty easy by aggregating reference targets for files using the exact same function we do for live buffers.
</p>

<p><span><span>ELisp</span></span></p><div><ul><li><span>Font used to highlight built-in function names.</span></li>
<li><span>Font used to highlight keywords.</span></li></ul></div><div>
<pre><code><span>(</span><span>with-temp-buffer</span></code>
<code>  <span>(</span><span>insert-file-contents</span> file<span>)</span></code>
<code>  <span>(</span>my/rst-internal-references<span>)</span><span>)</span></code>
</pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-fancy-completion">
<h5 id="fancy-completion">Fancy Completion</h5>
<div id="text-fancy-completion">
<p>
Emacs' long history includes <a href="https://company-mode.github.io/">company-mode</a>, which is a third-party completion framework that integrates with the <code><span>completion-at-point</span></code> set of functions.
Some <code><span>company-mode</span></code> features include additional metadata about completion candidates, and I found two that were useful: <code>company-kind</code> and <code>company-doc-buffer</code>.
</p>

<ul>
<li><code>company-kind</code> is a simple key that just tells the completion caller what the completion cadidate <i>is</i>.
In our case we can add some eye candy by indicating it's <code><span>'</span><span>text</span></code>.</li>
<li><code>company-doc-buffer</code> lets us add additional context to a completion candidate.
I leveraged this to include a couple of lines following the reference line to help me figure out what exactly the link refers to.
It's easier to show what this looks like rather than tell:</li>
</ul>



<p>
Notes:
</p>

<ul>
<li>I'm using GUI emacs here for the nicer completion popup with <a href="https://github.com/minad/corfu">corfu</a> which displays a transparent, floating frame</li>
<li>My completion candidate "context" is a real excerpt from the text around the reference, complete with styling, etc.</li>
<li>The small icon to the left of each candidate comes from the <code>company-kind</code> attribute.</li>
<li>The <code>~</code> syntax is part of <a href="https://github.com/oantolin/orderless">orderless</a></li>
</ul>

<p>
Completion candidate context is an extra frill but very helpful.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-summary">
<h4 id="summary">Summary</h4>
<p>
My experience extending a core emacs function was an instructive and interesting exercise.
I don't know what the future of emacs looks like in an increasingly LLM-crazed world, but I hope that future includes an open and powerful way to extend and customize the tools we use to write software.
</p>
</div>


<hr>



<hr>







        </section>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Crates.io phishing attempt (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fasterthanli.me/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt</link>
            <guid>45222772</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 14:50:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fasterthanli.me/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt">https://fasterthanli.me/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45222772">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

  
    
    

    
    

    

    

    
    

    
    
     
     

    
        
<p id="sponsor-list">
    Thanks to my sponsors:
    <span id="visible-sponsors">
    
    Lena Schönburg, Kevin Nguyen, Aiden Scandella, Brian L. Troutwine, Yufan Lou, Dirkjan Ochtman, Santiago Lema, Geoffrey Thomas, Radu Matei, Samit Basu, Justy, Tanner Muro, Seth, Geoff Cant, Simon Menke, psentee, Bob Ippolito, Philipp Gniewosz, Enrico Zschemisch, Andrew Henshaw
        and <a href="#" id="show-all-sponsors"><span id="more-sponsors-count">279</span> more</a>
    
    </span>
    

    
</p>



     

    

    
    



    

    

    

    <p data-bo="160">Earlier this week, an <a href="https://fasterthanli.me/articles/color-npm-package-compromised">npm supply chain attack</a>.</p>

<p data-bo="251">It’s turn for <a href="https://crates.io/">crates.io</a>, the main public repository for <a href="https://rust-lang.org/">Rust</a>
crates (packages).</p>

<p data-bo="378">The phishing e-mail looks like this:</p>

<figure data-bo="416"><picture><source type="image/jxl" media="(max-width: 400px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~13b1cc912a064403.w400.jxl 1x"><source type="image/jxl" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~052f360399d29116.jxl 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~052f360399d29116.jxl 2x"><source type="image/avif" media="(max-width: 400px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~0965dc15bd5795cf.w400.avif 1x"><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~4adc3538b38cd5d0.avif 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~4adc3538b38cd5d0.avif 2x"><source type="image/webp" media="(max-width: 400px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~569c8ebc7740ee8f.w400.webp 1x"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~f5f81e8409287a73.webp 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~f5f81e8409287a73.webp 2x"><img src="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email~052f360399d29116.jxl" loading="lazy" width="708" height="653" data-kind="media" data-input-path="/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/phishing-email.jxl" title="" alt="A phishing e-mail: Important: Breach notification regarding crates.io  Hi, BurntSushi! We recently discovered that an unauthorized actor had compromised the crates.io infrastructure and accessed a limited amount of user information. The attacker's access was revoked, and we are currently reviewing our security posture. We are currently drafting a blog post to outline the timeline and the steps we took to mitigate this. In the meantime, we strongly suggest you to rotate your login info by signing in here to our internal SSO, which is a temporary fix to ensure that the attacker cannot modify any packages published by you. "></picture><figcaption><cite><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/burntsushi.net/post/3lynehptw6c2n">Andrew Gallant on BlueSky
</a></cite></figcaption>
</figure><p data-bo="1262">And it leads to a GitHub login page that looks like this:</p>

<figure data-bo="1321"><picture><source type="image/jxl" media="(max-width: 400px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~f39542ca9ae9f0c3.w400.jxl 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~5429425a2625794b.w800.jxl 2x"><source type="image/jxl" media="(max-width: 900px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~ff6053b5d2562aeb.w900.jxl 1x"><source type="image/jxl" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~e78524d35ede5efb.jxl 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~e78524d35ede5efb.jxl 2x"><source type="image/avif" media="(max-width: 400px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~de116d2a77f034de.w400.avif 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~e4d40b2fbaa0c23e.w800.avif 2x"><source type="image/avif" media="(max-width: 900px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~5f55c6d615078899.w900.avif 1x"><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~f28292ec85f76009.avif 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~f28292ec85f76009.avif 2x"><source type="image/webp" media="(max-width: 400px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~21a0077b4369fdc4.w400.webp 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~34797abd3fa323ca.w800.webp 2x"><source type="image/webp" media="(max-width: 900px)" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~324abfa3a52194e8.w900.webp 1x"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~bf34180d4a8419bd.webp 1x,https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~bf34180d4a8419bd.webp 2x"><img src="https://cdn.fasterthanli.me/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish~e78524d35ede5efb.jxl" loading="lazy" width="1322" height="1378" data-kind="media" data-input-path="/content/articles/crates-io-phishing-attempt/github-phish.jxl" title="" alt="A fake GitHub sign-in page. "></picture><figcaption><cite><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/crates.io/discussions/11889#discussion-8886064">Barre on GitHub
</a></cite></figcaption>
</figure><p data-bo="1548">Several maintainers received it — the issue is being discussed <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/crates.io/discussions/11889">on GitHub</a>.</p>

<p data-bo="1685">The <a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/governance/teams/dev-tools#team-crates-io">crates.io team</a> has acknowledged
the attack and said they’d see if they can do something about it.</p>

<p data-bo="1859">No compromised packages have been identified as of yet (Sep 12, 14:10 UTC).</p>

<p data-bo="1936">Important links:</p>

<ul><li><a href="https://blog.rust-lang.org/2025/09/12/crates-io-phishing-campaign/">Rust Security Response WG blog post</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/crates.io/discussions/11889">GitHub discussion about the attack</a></li>
</ul>


    

    

    

    
    
    

    
        <p>
            (JavaScript is required to see this. Or maybe my stuff broke)
        </p>
     

    



    
  
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Many hard LeetCode problems are easy constraint problems (290 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://buttondown.com/hillelwayne/archive/many-hard-leetcode-problems-are-easy-constraint/</link>
            <guid>45222695</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 14:44:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://buttondown.com/hillelwayne/archive/many-hard-leetcode-problems-are-easy-constraint/">https://buttondown.com/hillelwayne/archive/many-hard-leetcode-problems-are-easy-constraint/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45222695">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            
            <date>
                
                
                September 10, 2025
                
                
            </date>
            

            

            
            <h2>
                Use the right tool for the job.
            </h2>
            

            

            
            
            <p>In my first interview out of college I was asked the change counter problem:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Given a set of coin denominations, find the minimum number of coins required to make change for a given number. IE for USA coinage and 37 cents, the minimum number is four (quarter, dime, 2 pennies).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I implemented the simple greedy algorithm and immediately fell into the trap of the question: the greedy algorithm only works for "well-behaved" denominations. If the coin values were <code>[10, 9, 1]</code>, then making 37 cents would take 10 coins in the greedy algorithm but only 4 coins optimally (<code>10+9+9+9</code>). The "smart" answer is to use a dynamic programming algorithm, which I didn't know how to do. So I failed the interview.</p>
<p>But you only need dynamic programming if you're writing your own algorithm. It's really easy if you throw it into a constraint solver like <a href="https://www.minizinc.org/" target="_blank">MiniZinc</a> and call it a day. </p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>int: total;
array[int] of int: values = [10, 9, 1];
array[index_set(values)] of var 0..: coins;

constraint sum (c in index_set(coins)) (coins[c] * values[c]) == total;
solve minimize sum(coins);
</code></pre></div>
<p>You can try this online <a href="https://play.minizinc.dev/" target="_blank">here</a>. It'll give you a prompt to put in <code>total</code> and then give you successively-better solutions:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>coins = [0, 0, 37];
----------
coins = [0, 1, 28];
----------
coins = [0, 2, 19];
----------
coins = [0, 3, 10];
----------
coins = [0, 4, 1];
----------
coins = [1, 3, 0];
----------
</code></pre></div>

<p>Lots of similar interview questions are this kind of mathematical optimization problem, where we have to find the maximum or minimum of a function corresponding to constraints. They're hard in programming languages because programming languages are too low-level. They are also exactly the problems that constraint solvers were designed to solve. Hard leetcode problems are easy constraint problems.<sup id="fnref:leetcode"><a href="#fn:leetcode">1</a></sup> Here I'm using MiniZinc, but you could just as easily use Z3 or OR-Tools or whatever your favorite generalized solver is.</p>
<h3>More examples</h3>

<p>This was a question in a different interview (which I thankfully passed):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Given a list of stock prices through the day, find maximum profit you can get by buying one stock and selling one stock later.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It's easy to do in O(n^2) time, or if you are clever, you can do it in O(n). Or you could be not clever at all and just write it as a constraint problem:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>array[int] of int: prices = [3, 1, 4, 1, 5, 9, 2, 6, 5, 3, 5, 8];
var int: buy;
var int: sell;
var int: profit = prices[sell] - prices[buy];

constraint sell &gt; buy;
constraint profit &gt; 0;
solve maximize profit;
</code></pre></div>
<p>Reminder, link to trying it online <a href="https://play.minizinc.dev/" target="_blank">here</a>. While working at that job, one interview question we tested out was:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Given a list, determine if three numbers in that list can be added or subtracted to give 0? </p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a satisfaction problem, not a constraint problem: we don't need the "best answer", any answer will do. We eventually decided against it for being too tricky for the engineers we were targeting. But it's not tricky in a solver; </p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>include "globals.mzn";
array[int] of int: numbers = [3, 1, 4, 1, 5, 9, 2, 6, 5, 3, 5, 8];
array[index_set(numbers)] of var {0, -1, 1}: choices;

constraint sum(n in index_set(numbers)) (numbers[n] * choices[n]) = 0;
constraint count(choices, -1) + count(choices, 1) = 3;
solve satisfy;
</code></pre></div>
<p>Okay, one last one, a problem I saw last year at <a href="https://chicagopython.github.io/algosig/" target="_blank">Chipy AlgoSIG</a>. Basically they pick some leetcode problems and we all do them. I failed to solve <a href="https://leetcode.com/problems/largest-rectangle-in-histogram/description/" target="_blank">this one</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Given an array of integers heights representing the histogram's bar height where the width of each bar is 1, return the area of the largest rectangle in the histogram.</p>
<p><img alt="example from leetcode link" src="https://assets.buttondown.email/images/63337f78-7138-4b21-87a0-917c0c5b1706.jpg?w=960&amp;fit=max"></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The "proper" solution is a tricky thing involving tracking lots of bookkeeping states, which you can completely bypass by expressing it as constraints:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>array[int] of int: numbers = [2,1,5,6,2,3];

var 1..length(numbers): x; 
var 1..length(numbers): dx;
var 1..: y;

constraint x + dx &lt;= length(numbers);
constraint forall (i in x..(x+dx)) (y &lt;= numbers[i]);

var int: area = (dx+1)*y;
solve maximize area;

output ["(\(x)-&gt;\(x+dx))*\(y) = \(area)"]
</code></pre></div>
<p>There's even a way to <a href="https://docs.minizinc.dev/en/2.9.3/visualisation.html" target="_blank">automatically visualize the solution</a> (using <code>vis_geost_2d</code>), but I didn't feel like figuring it out in time for the newsletter.</p>
<h3>Is this better?</h3>
<p>Now if I actually brought these questions to an interview the interviewee could ruin my day by asking "what's the runtime complexity?" Constraint solvers runtimes are unpredictable and almost always than an ideal bespoke algorithm because they are more expressive, in what I refer to as the <a href="https://buttondown.com/hillelwayne/archive/the-capability-tractability-tradeoff/" target="_blank">capability/tractability tradeoff</a>. But even so, they'll do way better than a <em>bad</em> bespoke algorithm, and I'm not experienced enough in handwriting algorithms to consistently beat a solver.</p>
<p>The real advantage of solvers, though, is how well they handle new constraints. Take the stock picking problem above. I can write an O(n²) algorithm in a few minutes and the O(n) algorithm if you give me some time to think. Now change the problem to</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Maximize the profit by buying and selling up to <code>max_sales</code> stocks, but you can only buy or sell one stock at a given time and you can only hold up to <code>max_hold</code> stocks at a time?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That's a way harder problem to write even an inefficient algorithm for! While the constraint problem is only a tiny bit more complicated:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>include "globals.mzn";
int: max_sales = 3;
int: max_hold = 2;
array[int] of int: prices = [3, 1, 4, 1, 5, 9, 2, 6, 5, 3, 5, 8];
array [1..max_sales] of var int: buy;
array [1..max_sales] of var int: sell;
array [index_set(prices)] of var 0..max_hold: stocks_held;
var int: profit = sum(s in 1..max_sales) (prices[sell[s]] - prices[buy[s]]);

constraint forall (s in 1..max_sales) (sell[s] &gt; buy[s]);
constraint profit &gt; 0;

constraint forall(i in index_set(prices)) (stocks_held[i] = (count(s in 1..max_sales) (buy[s] &lt;= i) - count(s in 1..max_sales) (sell[s] &lt;= i)));
constraint alldifferent(buy ++ sell);
solve maximize profit;

output ["buy at \(buy)\n", "sell at \(sell)\n", "for \(profit)"];
</code></pre></div>

<p>Most constraint solving examples online are puzzles, like <a href="https://docs.minizinc.dev/en/stable/modelling2.html#ex-sudoku" target="_blank">Sudoku</a> or "<a href="https://docs.minizinc.dev/en/stable/modelling2.html#ex-smm" target="_blank">SEND + MORE = MONEY</a>". Solving leetcode problems would be a more interesting demonstration. And you get more interesting opportunities to teach optimizations, like symmetry breaking.</p>

            
            

            
            
            <p><em>If you're reading this on the web, you can subscribe <a href="https://buttondown.com/hillelwayne" target="_blank">here</a>. Updates are once a week. My main website is <a href="https://www.hillelwayne.com/" target="_blank">here</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>My new book, </em>Logic for Programmers<em>, is now in early access! Get it <a href="https://leanpub.com/logic/" target="_blank">here</a>.</em></p>
            
            

            





        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[3D modeling with paper (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.arvinpoddar.com/blog/3d-modeling-with-paper</link>
            <guid>45222369</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 14:12:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.arvinpoddar.com/blog/3d-modeling-with-paper">https://www.arvinpoddar.com/blog/3d-modeling-with-paper</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45222369">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.arvinpoddar.com/blog/3d-modeling-with-paper: Error: unsuitable certificate purpose]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Over 100 ships have sailed with fake insurance from the Norwegian Ro Marine (189 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nrk.no/vestland/xl/over-100-ships-have-sailed-without-legitimate-insurance-from-the-norwegian-company-ro-marine-1.17565216</link>
            <guid>45221996</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 13:36:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nrk.no/vestland/xl/over-100-ships-have-sailed-without-legitimate-insurance-from-the-norwegian-company-ro-marine-1.17565216">https://www.nrk.no/vestland/xl/over-100-ships-have-sailed-without-legitimate-insurance-from-the-norwegian-company-ro-marine-1.17565216</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45221996">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-main-content="" data-ec-list="article_body" data-ec-name="brødtekst">
<p>All large ships must have insurance, and Ro Marine has provided this in a big way.</p>
<p>The Norwegian company did not have permission to sell insurance but did it anyway — to clients worldwide.</p>
<p>In March, we reported how select ships used false papers to <a href="https://www.nrk.no/vestland/xl/falske-dokument-fra-norsk-selskap-brukt-til-a-lure-nato-land-i-skyggeflate-kontroller-1.17354948" ec-id="pp:1.17354948" ec-name="deceive inspectors in NATO countries">deceive inspectors in NATO countries</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Now, NRK and <span data-content="<p>Dossier Center is a non-commercial project by Mikhail Khodorkovsky, an opponent&amp;nbsp;of Vladimir Putin.<br /> The internationally recognized Dossier Center consists of journalists, including Russians in exile, that investigate Russia&amp;#39;s leaders.</p> " data-term="Dossier Center">Dossier Center</span> can reveal how extensive and global the fraud was: over 100 ships have sailed with illegitimate insurance documents from Ro Marine.</strong></p>
<p>“It's very serious and unusual that such a serious fraud happens with the help of a Norwegian company. At worst, it could undermine the trust in the Norwegian maritime industry,” says Thomas Angell Bergh from the Norwegian Maritime Authority.</p>
<div id="1.17568300.8c70d55b"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17568300&amp;size=18&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=CENTER&amp;parentSize=18 -->
    <!-- prettier-ignore-attribute --><persongalleri-v1 data-name="persongalleri"><div><ul><li><div><figure data-name="Thomas Angell Bergh"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_wq8rUs1eFkbYJbZ61EPOBGQ.webp 450w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_wnoTgudfdDwgJbZ61EPOBGQ.webp 768w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_w8jePSXb30yAJbZ61EPOBGQ.webp 1080w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_wuNp7Qu8ZmcYJbZ61EPOBGQ.webp 1280w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_wn_o6CoW11WYJbZ61EPOBGQ.webp 1600w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_wLKWFt68BNHoJbZ61EPOBGQ.webp 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 540px) 320px, 100vw"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_w342IbWVNHKenVEhkjqGLsQ.jpg 450w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_wztEmgUJr222nVEhkjqGLsQ.jpg 768w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_w9rfWMZYJdzinVEhkjqGLsQ.jpg 1080w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_w882KLzBeIRunVEhkjqGLsQ.jpg 1280w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_wPMBdYPZ_3manVEhkjqGLsQ.jpg 1600w,https://gfx.nrk.no/ihn93lPDHrcBSgfFUis9_wMg-LIRMKR8inVEhkjqGLsQ.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 540px) 320px, 100vw"></picture></figure><h4>Thomas Angell Bergh</h4></div></li></ul></div></persongalleri-v1>
  </div>
<p>Most of the fake insurance papers were for ships transporting goods out of Russia, mainly oil.</p>
<p>NRK has contacted dozens of Ro Marine’s clients. Only a few were willing to speak with us.</p>
<p>One of the customers says he was scammed by Ro Marine because he believed the insurance policies he purchased were valid.</p>
<p>Another says that "everyone" knows Ro Marine is fake, but that the ships need Western insurance documents. Such documents can make it easier to sail freely, without Western countries interfering in the transport.</p>
<p>This signature appears time and again on documents issued by Ro Marine.</p>
<div id="1.17568169.8cb74ae0"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17568169&amp;size=12&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=LEFT&amp;type=image&amp;aspect=F11&amp;parentSize=18 --><!-- START: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
<figure>
<p><img sizes="(min-width:1180px) 767px, (min-width:720px) 67vw, 100vw" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLgp8oq42yqzJv_bmGApN12mA.jpg 80w, https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLgI4VxDh-eYuP_bmGApN12mA.jpg 160w, https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLgCK_seUg0Z13_bmGApN12mA.jpg 350w, https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLgkb3wyP2Zz5z_bmGApN12mA.jpg 450w, https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLgN7_-8CwimW3_bmGApN12mA.jpg 650w, https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLgOiGR5qF_50r_bmGApN12mA.jpg 1000w, https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLgU29NNNUV-yn_bmGApN12mA.jpg 1200w, https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLg-ayV4U5l8p3_bmGApN12mA.jpg 1600w, https://gfx.nrk.no/MCbDTN4tmgaQov7qKXpaLgjuoSny5RoK7_bmGApN12mA.jpg 2000w" loading="eager" alt="Ro Marine's logo and a signature on an insurance document" title=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- END: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
</div>
<p>The search for the owner of the signature led us to a Russian website, where you can download many different signatures. The one used by Ro Marine belongs to a "doctor," says the website.</p>

<p><strong>Behind the global hoax is this man.</strong></p>
<div id="1.17568185.8c9b1bde"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17568185&amp;size=12&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=LEFT&amp;type=image&amp;aspect=F11&amp;parentSize=18 --><!-- START: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
<figure>
<p><img sizes="(min-width:1180px) 767px, (min-width:720px) 67vw, 100vw" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfwZStez9nvcswaCR3DbYoUfw.png 80w, https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfw6OtUNMSZ_tIaCR3DbYoUfw.png 160w, https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfw2BOD_pdfbXgaCR3DbYoUfw.png 350w, https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfwXKNX0QHbnGUaCR3DbYoUfw.png 450w, https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfwH1dPZu-OvFAaCR3DbYoUfw.png 650w, https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfwUVQFAgSRKukaCR3DbYoUfw.png 1000w, https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfwFxu00I7874IaCR3DbYoUfw.png 1200w, https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfwFBLMM5pHi5MaCR3DbYoUfw.png 1600w, https://gfx.nrk.no/IvSO6V-9BL7p6VxthXRYfw20KeFacs-zQaCR3DbYoUfw.png 2000w" loading="eager" alt="Images taken from Andrey Mochalin's passport" title=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- END: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
</div>
<p>His name is Andrey Mochalin, a Russian citizen and resident of St. Petersburg. Mochalin has experience working for a reputable Norwegian insurance company.</p>
<p>In March, he, two Norwegians and a Bulgarian were charged with forging documents and operating an insurance business without a permit. Mochalin is also being investigated for violating international sanctions.</p>
<p><em>Through an attorney, the Norwegians say they do not understand the charges (see their full response in the fact box later in the article). The Bulgarian tells NRK he is innocent.</em></p>
<p>For several months, NRK and Dossier Center have tried unsuccessfully to get in touch with Mochalin. At the same time, we investigated Ro Marine's operations. What we found surprised experts.</p>
<h2>“Among the worst of the worst”</h2>
<p>Sanctions expert David Tannenbaum is shocked by the the scale of it. He knows how far Russia is willing to go to protect its oil exports, which are crucial for funding Putin’s illegal war in Ukraine.</p>
<p>Sanctions against Russia can make it difficult for tankers carrying Russian oil to obtain insurance that is approved in the West. But they are finding ways around it.</p>
<p>This is where Ro Marine enters the picture.</p>
<p>“Seems like Ro Marine is popular with sanctions evaders. You don't have this roster by accident,” says David Tannenbaum from Deep Blue Intelligence. The American company specializes in detecting sanctions evasion.</p>
<div id="1.17509059.48b308e2"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17509059&amp;size=12&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=LEFT&amp;type=image&amp;aspect=F169&amp;parentSize=18 --><!-- START: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
<figure>
<p><img sizes="(min-width:1180px) 767px, (min-width:720px) 67vw, 100vw" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQg7rXPWF7Mz3IlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 80w, https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQ8jYT6MYPiGPIlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 160w, https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQf_1pSlZEGQDIlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 350w, https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQxa5lBDeruP_IlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 450w, https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQdeoe2MHnLabIlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 650w, https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQJCobIBIWEFnIlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 1000w, https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQG4VFENiSFL7IlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 1200w, https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQDL9Zv-pLhpzIlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 1600w, https://gfx.nrk.no/FmLZNY4daRMBV4kNL7XzJQyBwvDFOI7P3IlyPp8Xb8RA.jpg 2000w" loading="eager" alt="David Tannenbaum. " title=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- END: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
</div>
<p>For Tannenbaum, it appears that Ro Marine primarily serves the <span data-content="<p>The shadow fleet consists of ships suspected of circumventing Western sanctions. This term is loosely defined as ships having the following characteristics:</p> <ul> <li>Older than 15 years and without Western insurance</li> <li>Changing flags often</li> <li>Difficult to trace real ownership</li> <li>Owned or operated by companies registered in countries that have not joined the economic sanctions imposed after Russia&amp;#39;s full-scale invasion of Ukraine in 2022</li> <li>Often deactivating&amp;nbsp;their AIS, a system that permits tracking their movements and calls at Russian ports</li> </ul> <p>Insurance companies have been given a central role in enforcing sanctions against Russia.</p> <p>The Norwegian&amp;nbsp;companies Gard and Skuld are among the twelve in the International Group, which provides insurance for about 90 percent&amp;nbsp;of the world&amp;#39;s shipping. These twelve go to great lengths to comply with Western sanctions.</p> <p>This means that ships that violate sanctions rules must find other insurance providers in order to pass inspections and avoid Western countries interfering in the transport.</p> <p>A standard insurance policy provides coverage in the event of an oil spill, ship accident or crew accident. A fake insurance policy, such as the one offered by Ro Marine, is unlikely to provide any coverage at all.</p> " data-term="shadow fleet">shadow fleet</span> or ships engaged in illegal activities or sanctions evasion.</p>
<p>“Is Ro Marine the worst of the worst? I think they're definitely in contention,” he both asks and answers.</p>
<p>Our documentation shows, for example, that Gatik, known as one of the largest players in the Russian shadow fleet, appears to have placed almost all of their ships with Ro Marine.</p>
<p>In addition, six ships linked to the Russian gas giant Novatek have had fake insurance from the Norwegian company. All six have sailed along the Norwegian coast towards the gas facility Arctic LNG2 in Russia, which is sanctioned by the USA. The ships are sanctioned by the EU.</p>
<p>Ships linked to the sanctioned Iranian oil industry and Iranian military have also been customers of Ro Marine.</p>

<h2>Dangerous cargo from Russia</h2>
<p>Among the cargo ships that have purchased invalid insurance from Ro Marine, we found "<span data-content="<p>The ship with IMO number&amp;nbsp;9125097 was previously called&amp;nbsp;&amp;quot;Lily-B&amp;quot;.</p> " data-term="Agattu">Agattu</span>". Here, the vessel is sailing between Denmark and Sweden with explosives in the cargo, bound for Algeria.</p>
<div id="1.17568437.c344473f"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17568437&amp;size=18&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=CENTER&amp;parentSize=18 -->
    <!-- prettier-ignore-attribute --><levende-stillbilde-v2 data-self-id="1.17568437" data-name="levende-stillbilde"><dh-lvs-basis-levende-stillbilde data-state="ACTIVE" data-viewport-position="OUT-OF-VIEWPORT" data-view="WIDE"><figure><div role="img" aria-label=""><p><img src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_360.jpg" alt=""></p><video preload="none" muted="" poster="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_360.jpg"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_360.mp4"></video></div><div role="img" aria-label=""><p><img src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_720.jpg" alt=""></p><video preload="none" muted="" poster="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_720.jpg"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_720.mp4"></video></div><div role="img" aria-label=""><p><img src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_1080.jpg" alt=""></p><video preload="none" muted="" poster="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_1080.jpg"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_1080.mp4"></video></div><div role="img" aria-label=""><p><img src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_360.jpg" alt=""></p><video preload="none" muted="" poster="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_360.jpg"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_360.mp4"></video></div><div role="img" aria-label=""><p><img src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_720.jpg" alt=""></p><video preload="none" muted="" poster="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_720.jpg"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_720.mp4"></video></div><div role="img" aria-label=""><p><img src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_1080.jpg" alt=""></p><video preload="none" muted="" poster="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_1080.jpg"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://mediaorigin.nrk.no/movingstill/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93/20250801133521/e150da16-836e-4b6d-90da-16836eab6d93_1080.mp4"></video></div><figcaption data-caption="true"><small>Drone footage: Ole Jakobsen</small></figcaption></figure></dh-lvs-basis-levende-stillbilde></levende-stillbilde-v2>
  </div>
<p>Three tonnes of missile weapons were transported from St. Petersburg in Russia, according to Russian port records.</p>
<p>The ship joins the ranks of Ro Marine customers who have contributed to Russia's export revenues by transporting goods from Russian ports. This does not apply to all customers, but the vast majority, according to research by NRK and Dossier Center.</p>
<h2>Provoked a NATO country</h2>
<p>Not long ago, it was difficult to imagine that ordinary shipping in Europe could lead to military confrontation. Today, the situation is different. European countries may intervene in oil shipments that violate Western sanctions, which are intended to oppose Putin's bloody war in Ukraine. Russia has its countermeasures.</p>
<p>An illustrative example happened to a Ro Marine customer in mid-May: The oil tanker "<span data-content="<p>The ship has previously been called&amp;nbsp;&amp;quot;Argent&amp;quot;&amp;nbsp;and &amp;quot;Jaguar&amp;quot;. Its IMO number is&amp;nbsp;9293002.</p> " data-term="Blint">Blint</span>".</p>
<p>The Estonian navy suspected the ship was sailing without a flag—a clear violation of international regulations. The navy radioed the vessel, but according to Estonian authorities, the captain refused to cooperate.</p>
<p>Suddenly, a Russian fighter jet came whizzing over them, violating the NATO country’s airspace. Instead of stopping, the sanctioned tanker sailed on to the Russian oil port of Primorsk.</p>
<p>This video of the incident is filmed from inside the ship.</p>

<p>Like many other tankers transporting Russian oil, "Blint" has had fake insurance from Ro Marine, NRK can document.</p>
<p>In this way, Ro Marine has acted in line with the interests of the Russian authorities.</p>
<p>Russia's president, October 2023:</p>
<p>“Thanks to the actions of companies and authorities, the tanker fleet has grown, new mechanisms for payment, <strong>insurance</strong> and reinsurance of our cargo have been created.”</p>
<div id="1.17568325.b8ced581"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17568325&amp;size=18&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=CENTER&amp;parentSize=18 -->
    <!-- prettier-ignore-attribute --><persongalleri-v1 data-name="persongalleri"><div><ul><li><div><figure data-name="Vladimir Putin"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgjdLnXidFSzWNtdzvw0I5SQ.webp 450w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtg2X6K4mxagNmNtdzvw0I5SQ.webp 768w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgdiBctd-DXGmNtdzvw0I5SQ.webp 1080w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgAauL-2gJdkONtdzvw0I5SQ.webp 1280w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgnpDqvosoTr2Ntdzvw0I5SQ.webp 1600w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtg4ToaQV0IyBmNtdzvw0I5SQ.webp 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 540px) 320px, 100vw"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgnSKHvm-_AYw6qzzfOVZgkg.jpg 450w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgw8aQ0IrhwSg6qzzfOVZgkg.jpg 768w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgPh8n5bx9lAk6qzzfOVZgkg.jpg 1080w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgTx-woK-idXE6qzzfOVZgkg.jpg 1280w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgg4BvyddrE0E6qzzfOVZgkg.jpg 1600w,https://gfx.nrk.no/f8cUeJaJIba4_outEVaKtgZJrArYan2q06qzzfOVZgkg.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 540px) 320px, 100vw"></picture></figure><h4>Vladimir Putin</h4></div></li></ul></div></persongalleri-v1>
  </div>
<p>Researcher Åse Gilje Østensen at the Norwegian Naval Academy tells that “sometimes, entities act in the Russian interest on their own initiative. Sometimes, Putin or other central figures around him have signaled that certain initiatives are welcome. In such cases, actors will often seek to please the regime.”</p>
<div id="1.17568330.b798d06b"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17568330&amp;size=18&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=CENTER&amp;parentSize=18 -->
    <!-- prettier-ignore-attribute --><persongalleri-v1 data-name="persongalleri"><div><ul><li><div><figure data-name="Åse Gilje Østensen"><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwL03NoKrzsHuhO8_k8SR0YA.webp 450w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwlYg4JfxfvY6hO8_k8SR0YA.webp 768w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwNTnevp86prehO8_k8SR0YA.webp 1080w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwfXk6cKydPWShO8_k8SR0YA.webp 1280w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwjSbHz-dPlhuhO8_k8SR0YA.webp 1600w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdw_zfdNqp22ZChO8_k8SR0YA.webp 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 540px) 320px, 100vw"><source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwm6zm5bhyUs3z5eJ2lc2aMg.jpg 450w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwHmXqoLRp6XPz5eJ2lc2aMg.jpg 768w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwjNVGsgZGvSjz5eJ2lc2aMg.jpg 1080w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwZYozY_cabQPz5eJ2lc2aMg.jpg 1280w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdw1vnBHxHKY1Tz5eJ2lc2aMg.jpg 1600w,https://gfx.nrk.no/btfWzaJhXs-uhS0CSRzzdwKQngojQkR1Pz5eJ2lc2aMg.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 540px) 320px, 100vw"></picture></figure><h4>Åse Gilje Østensen</h4></div></li></ul></div></persongalleri-v1>
  </div>
<div><p>“Russia is an authoritarian regime that can force civilian actors to assist the regime. Other times, state bodies may be more directly involved. What is the case regarding Ro Marine is difficult to know.”</p><p>  The Russian Embassy in Norway does not answer NRK's questions about Ro Marine's operations because the company is Norwegian and refers us to the Norwegian authorities. They also do not respond to whether Ro Marine has acted in accordance with the interests of Russian authorities, or any other statements and findings in this case.</p></div>
<p>The embassy does however choose to point out that the sanctions against the "shadow fleet" are contrary to international law.</p>

<h2>Approved by the largest flag state</h2>
<p>For several years, the Norwegian company operated without permission and with fake documents without any authorities noticing — neither in Norway nor abroad.</p>
<p>The earliest objectionable activity was in 2021, according to NRK’s investigation.</p>
<p>At that time, Ro Marine applied to be recognized as an insurance company by the world's largest <span data-content="<p>The flag states are responsible for ensuring&amp;nbsp;that&amp;nbsp;ships comply with international regulations regarding safety, environment, and working conditions. The flag state&amp;#39;s responsibilities&amp;nbsp;also include ensuring that a ship has legitimate&amp;nbsp;insurance.<br /> <br /> All ships must be registered with&amp;nbsp;a flag state.</p> " data-term="flag state">flag state</span>, Panama, despite missing the necessary approval from Norwegian authorities.</p>
<div id="1.17568160.8ca9335f"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17568160&amp;size=12&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=LEFT&amp;caption=NRK+has+found+that+most+ships+among+Ro+Marine%27s+clients+are+registered+in+Panama.&amp;type=image&amp;aspect=F169&amp;parentSize=18 --><!-- START: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
<figure>
<p><img sizes="(min-width:1180px) 767px, (min-width:720px) 67vw, 100vw" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gjF8n58S82ElaOHzh4YKbOw.png 80w, https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gzY_3_sKFywpaOHzh4YKbOw.png 160w, https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gS8bjQpaI-v1aOHzh4YKbOw.png 350w, https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gUpRNoS7C0VZaOHzh4YKbOw.png 450w, https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gTf5EpK_c7LhaOHzh4YKbOw.png 650w, https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gV7bjpwwxi8laOHzh4YKbOw.png 1000w, https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gAfr5SZl42f1aOHzh4YKbOw.png 1200w, https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gx40rQ0uqGwVaOHzh4YKbOw.png 1600w, https://gfx.nrk.no/9VDLCagvklNb21yExnoq0gtIhetBUrdHtaOHzh4YKbOw.png 2000w" loading="eager" alt="Office of the flag state of Panama in Panama City." title=""></p>
<figcaption>
<p>NRK has found that most ships among Ro Marine's clients are registered in Panama.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<!-- END: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
</div>
<p>Ro Marine sent the flag state a forged reference, which was originally given to a completely different company, sources tell NRK. With this reference, Ro Marine was recognized by the flag state of Panama in December 2021.</p>

<p>In the time that followed, <a href="https://www.nrk.no/vestland/flaggstater-verden-rundt-stanser-skip-og-palegger-tiltak-etter-avsloring-fra-nrk-og-danwatch-1.17363840" ec-id="pp:1.17363840" ec-name="several flag states were fooled by Ro Marine">several flag states were fooled by Ro Marine</a>, including by forged documents that looked like they were from the Norwegian Financial Supervisory Authority.</p>
<p><strong>The illegal activity continued unencumbered until NRK alerted the flag states. </strong></p>
<h2>Russian owner worked many years for a Norwegian company</h2>
<p>The Russian owner of Ro Marine, Andrey Mochalin, has gone underground. Mochalin has not responded to any of the numerous inquiries from NRK and Dossier Center.</p>
<p>For over ten years, he worked for a legitimate Norwegian insurance company. Most of the time, he worked from St. Petersburg.</p>
<p>Occasionally, he visited his employer's office in Oslo. Here he is pictured with his former colleagues.</p>

<p>At this time, two of his Norwegian managers also owned another company that offered insurance. This company later became Ro Marine.</p>
<p>A few weeks after Russia's war against Ukraine began in 2022, Ro Marine passed from Norwegian to Russian ownership.</p>
<p>This is when Mochalin bought Ro Marine from the company of the two Norwegians for almost two million NOK.</p>
<p>These two Norwegians, along with Andrey Mochalin and a Bulgarian citizen, are charged with forging documents and conducting illegal insurance business.</p>
<p>Out of respect for the ongoing investigation, the Norwegians did not want to be interviewed by NRK, according to their lawyer.</p>
<div id="1.17568145.8cc56261"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17568145&amp;size=12&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=LEFT&amp;caption=Ro+Marine+claimed+its+address+was+here+at+the+Norwegian+Shipowners%27+Association+building+in+Oslo%2C+but+according+to+the+association%2C+that+was+not+correct.&amp;type=image&amp;aspect=F169&amp;parentSize=18 --><!-- START: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
<figure>
<p><img sizes="(min-width:1180px) 767px, (min-width:720px) 67vw, 100vw" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZgFBPT1ejROqIXnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 80w, https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZgYCy9dNFmrS0Xnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 160w, https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZgNZsHNwrviTIXnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 350w, https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZgua7FhvP8m7wXnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 450w, https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZgXRyug-pa4HAXnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 650w, https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZg7G6NsOXIEowXnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 1000w, https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZgU9IAQXJ-Yp4Xnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 1200w, https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZgbXkYw-cExFAXnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 1600w, https://gfx.nrk.no/7fLLtyITpHkwWHDGgIEyZgdlUqMBbUKdQXnh7mSkYdfg.jpg 2000w" loading="eager" alt="Norwegian Shipowners' Association building in Oslo" title=""></p>
<figcaption>
<p>Ro Marine claimed its address was here at the Norwegian Shipowners' Association building in Oslo, but according to the association, that was not correct.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<!-- END: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
</div>
<h2>Money trail in Russia</h2>
<p>Alongside the Norwegian company Ro Marine, Andrey Mochalin runs a company in St. Petersburg with direct links to Ro Marine.</p>
<p>NRK and Dossier Center have obtained access to bank documents for <span data-content="<p>The company is called&amp;nbsp;Khaydor St Petersburg,&amp;nbsp;OGRN: 1167847332960.</p> <p>NRK and Dossier Center have verified the information against publicly available reports.</p> " data-term="his Russian company">his Russian company</span>.</p>
<p>The money transfers are many, and some stand out.</p>
<p><strong>Last year, there were 36 payments totaling approximately five million NOK that we can connect to Ro Marine. </strong></p>
<p>The bank transfers were marked with the name of the ship and the policy number.</p>

<p>The number corresponds to insurance documents issued by Ro Marine.</p>

<p>The company’s account also shows salary payments to Mochalin.</p>
<h2>Those charged</h2>
<div id="1.17567355.eb00a411"><!-- include: /serum/render?id=1.17567355&amp;size=12&amp;perspective=RICH&amp;alignment=LEFT&amp;type=image&amp;aspect=ORIGINAL&amp;parentSize=18 --><!-- START: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
<figure>
<p><img sizes="(min-width:1180px) 767px, (min-width:720px) 67vw, 100vw" srcset="https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQ6gL5eurodHOkNt7LQbu8kA.png 80w, https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQVxCczaQQnPKkNt7LQbu8kA.png 160w, https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQdb0IUbjwWpSkNt7LQbu8kA.png 350w, https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQgZSA5lWZhfGkNt7LQbu8kA.png 450w, https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQrLxg9Ko8IFikNt7LQbu8kA.png 650w, https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQ5TzBib8k9YykNt7LQbu8kA.png 1000w, https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQg0_ce_iOgYWkNt7LQbu8kA.png 1200w, https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQfTHJhVrKe5OkNt7LQbu8kA.png 1600w, https://gfx.nrk.no/nv-P8YTALYMJuOM4Mb-kRQCQ52fP3rsfukNt7LQbu8kA.png 2000w" loading="eager" alt="A graphical representation showing the geographical connections of Andrey Mochalin and the three others who have held official roles in Ro Marine." title=""></p>
</figure>
<!-- END: /templates/image/image-rich.jsp -->
</div>
<p>Here’s what we can share about the Russian Andrey Mochalin and the others charged in the case (in parentheses is the time period they had official roles in Ro Marine):</p>
<p><strong>A. Mochalin (2022-2025): </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Sole owner of Ro Marine during the period when the company's illegal insurance activities were most widespread, according to our documentation.</li>
<li>Majority owner of the Russian company that received payments worth millions of NOK last year marked for Ro Marine.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Norwegian 1 (2016-2023): </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Registered as co-owner in the Russian company that last year received payments worth millions of NOK marked for Ro Marine.</li>
<li>Owner and board chairman in 2021 when someone sent a forged reference on behalf of Ro Marine to Panama. At the time the company lacked a permit to sell insurance.</li>
<li>In 2024, a year after he left the board, contributed to ensuring Ro Marine’s continued operations by securing a new board member: the charged Bulgarian.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Norwegian 2 (2017-2023): </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Owner and managing director in 2021 when someone sent a forged reference on behalf of Ro Marine to Panama. At the time the company lacked a permit to sell insurance.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Bulgarian (2024-2025): </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Car mechanic without any experience in marine insurance.</li>
<li>Tenant of Norwegian 1 for years.</li>
<li>Board member in Ro Marine for over half a year, up to March 2025.</li>
</ul>
<p>After the Norwegians left the board in 2023, the Norwegian company had a problem. With a Russian as the only board member, the company was in violation of the Companies Act of Norway, which requires at least one board member to be from an EEA country. Since Bulgaria is a member of the EEA, the Bulgarian could solve the issue.</p>
<p>According to the Bulgarian, his Norwegian landlord arranged the board position to help him financially.</p>
<p>However, he never received the money he was promised and left the board because he realized something was wrong, the Bulgarian says. He does not understand the police's suspicion towards him.</p>
<p>“I had no idea what they were doing. I have nothing to hide,” says the Bulgarian to NRK. He has been contacted by the police and says he is fully cooperating with them.</p>


<h2>The consequences of uncovering the scam</h2>
<p>After NRK's revelation in March, several flag states have issued <a href="https://www.nrk.no/vestland/flaggstater-verden-rundt-stanser-skip-og-palegger-tiltak-etter-avsloring-fra-nrk-og-danwatch-1.17363840" ec-id="pp:1.17363840" ec-name="stop orders to ships that used Ro Marine">stop orders to ships that used Ro Marine</a>.</p>
<p>Panama alone has banned 16 ships from sailing because the ships have not shown new, real insurance within the deadline they were given.</p>
<p>The UK has sanctioned Ro Marine. Ro Marines’s website has been taken down. In July, the Oslo District Court forcibly dissolved the company for breach of accounting obligations, because Ro Marine had not submitted annual accounts for 2023.</p>
<p>However, the Russian company in St. Petersburg, which received payments worth millions of NOK marked for Ro Marine, is still active.</p>
<p>One month after NRK's revelation in March, another ship in the Russian shadow fleet presented a fake insurance certificate from Ro Marine. Inspectors at the oil port of Primorsk were presented with a document "signed in Oslo."</p>
<p>The expiration date of the fake insurance?</p>
<p>April next year.</p>
<p><em>NRK has contacted the companies that operate the mentioned ships "Agattu" and "Blint", with no response. We have not been able to contact Gatik. Novatek has not responded to our questions. </em></p>


</div><p><span>
<span>
<span>Publisert</span>
<time datetime="2025-09-12T07:00:00+02:00">
12.09.2025, kl. 07.00
</time>
</span>
</span>
</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Chat Control faces blocking minority in the EU (327 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/TutaPrivacy/status/1966384776883142661</link>
            <guid>45221580</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 12:52:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/TutaPrivacy/status/1966384776883142661">https://twitter.com/TutaPrivacy/status/1966384776883142661</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45221580">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ScriptLoadFailure"><form action="" method="GET"><div><p><span>Something went wrong, but don’t fret — let’s give it another shot.</span></p><p><img alt="⚠️" draggable="false" src="https://abs-0.twimg.com/emoji/v2/svg/26a0.svg"><span> Some privacy related extensions may cause issues on x.com. Please disable them and try again.</span></p></div></form></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Treasury Is Expanding the Patriot Act to Attack Bitcoin Self Custody (476 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tftc.io/treasury-iexpanding-patriot-act/</link>
            <guid>45221274</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 12:10:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tftc.io/treasury-iexpanding-patriot-act/">https://www.tftc.io/treasury-iexpanding-patriot-act/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45221274">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                        <h2 id="martys-bent">Marty's Bent</h2><figure><img src="https://www.tftc.io/content/images/2025/09/Screenshot-2025-09-11-at-9.59.52---PM.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="593" height="1060"><figcaption><span>via </span><a href="https://www.therage.co/us-government-to-bring-patriot-act-to-digital-assets/?ref=tftc.io"><span>The Rage</span></a></figcaption></figure><p>We warned a couple of months ago when the Trump administration's "Crypto Brief" was released that there was some language in the brief that advised the government to expand the Patriot Act to account for digital assets. Well, it looks like FinCen and the Treasury have been working on guidelines and a rough outline is shared above courtesy of The Rage, and they are absolutely horrid.</p><p>It seems that FinCen and the Treasury are preparing to outlaw the use of CoinJoin, atomic swaps, single address use, and transaction broadcast timing delays. All of which are common <strong>best use </strong>practices that I would recommend any bitcoiner leveraging self-custody practice. This is an all out attack on financial privacy within bitcoin. If enacted, any user who leverages these tools will be flagged as a suspicious, any attempts to send a UTXO that has touched any of these tools will be rejected by regulated services, and could potentially be sent to prison.</p><p>This is an absurd affront to common sensibilities and freedom in the digital age. The fact that they want to prevent people from using single addresses for individual UTXOs is patently absurd. Not only is it a massive infringement on privacy, but it makes bitcoin usage less economically efficient and degrades the security of every bitcoiner. Loading up a single address with too many UTXOs degrades the entropy of a public-private key pair and makes it easier to brute force a user's private key.</p><p>Instead of expanding the Patriot Act, it should be abolished. Instead of trying to eliminate financial privacy for the 99.9% of law abiding citizens in this country, the government should be actively trying to foster an environment in which it can be improved. The proposed solutions will do nothing but put good Americans in harm's way and degrade the security of their savings.</p><p>We shouldn't have to live in a world where standards cater to the lowest common denominator, in this case criminals, and make things worse off for the overwhelming majority of the population. It's crazy that this even has to be said. The onus is on law enforcement to be so good at their jobs that they are able to prevent crimes from happening before they occur and effectively bring criminals to heel after they commit crimes. It shouldn't be on a neutral protocol and the industry being built on top of it that, when used effectively, provides people with a stable monetary system that respects user privacy and equips them with the tools to receive and spend in a way that provides them with peace of mind.</p><p>Why should everyone have to suffer because of a few bad apples? Isn't that letting the terrorist win? </p><h3 id="bitcoin-is-becoming-less-volatile-as-it-integrates-into-traditional-finance-infrastructure">Bitcoin Is Becoming Less Volatile as It Integrates Into Traditional Finance Infrastructure</h3><p>Mel Mattison revealed a fascinating shift in Bitcoin's market dynamics that challenges conventional crypto wisdom. He pointed out that Bitcoin futures now exhibit lower volatility than platinum futures - a remarkable transformation for an asset once synonymous with wild price swings. The proliferation of ETFs, options, futures, and other traditional financial instruments has fundamentally altered Bitcoin's behavior, creating what Mel calls "volatility suppression." This institutionalization comes with trade-offs: while reducing dramatic downswings, it also caps explosive upside potential.</p><blockquote>"Bitcoin is becoming a TradFi security instrument and it's getting TradFi vol." - <a href="https://x.com/MelMattison1?ref=tftc.io">Mel Mattison</a></blockquote><p>Mel argued that the relationship between volatility and returns means investors must recalibrate expectations. Where 100% annual gains once seemed routine, he now considers 50% returns "massive" for this new era of Bitcoin. This maturation reflects Bitcoin's evolution from speculative experiment to financial infrastructure - less exciting perhaps, but ultimately more sustainable for long-term adoption.</p><p>Check out the <a href="https://youtu.be/QEyxOwaQFzo?ref=tftc.io" rel="noreferrer">full podcast here</a> for more on China's gold strategy, Fed independence battles, and housing market manipulation plans.</p><hr><h3 id="headlines-of-the-day">Headlines of the Day</h3><p>New Bill for Strategic Bitcoin Reserve - via <a href="https://x.com/TFTC21/status/1965148899565600991?ref=tftc.io">X</a></p><p>SEC to Host Crypto Roundtable October 17 - via <a href="https://x.com/TFTC21/status/1965140430838006076?ref=tftc.io">X</a></p><p>Research Proposes Bitcoin for Mars Trade Standard - via <a href="https://x.com/TFTC21/status/1965135337543664112?ref=tftc.io">X</a></p><hr><h3 id="secure-your-bitcoin-the-hard-way">Secure Your Bitcoin The Hard Way</h3><p>Tom Honzik has helped 1,000+ people secure more than 5,000 BTC. Now, TFTC and Unchained are teaming up for a live online session on bitcoin custody.What you’ll learn:</p><ul><li>Biggest mistakes that cause lost coins</li><li>Tradeoffs of exchanges, ETFs, singlesig, and multisig</li><li>How to get optimal security without blindly trust custodians or DIY risk</li></ul><p>Stick around for the AMA to ask Tom Honzik and Marty Bent anything—from privacy considerations to the tradeoffs of different multisig quorums.</p><figure><img src="https://www.tftc.io/content/images/2025/08/D1--9--1.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="344" srcset="https://www.tftc.io/content/images/size/w600/2025/08/D1--9--1.png 600w, https://www.tftc.io/content/images/size/w1000/2025/08/D1--9--1.png 1000w, https://www.tftc.io/content/images/size/w1600/2025/08/D1--9--1.png 1600w, https://www.tftc.io/content/images/size/w2400/2025/08/D1--9--1.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption><a href="https://www.unchained.com/o/secure-your-bitcoin-the-hard-way?utm_campaign=sybthw&amp;utm_medium=affiliate&amp;utm_source=tftc&amp;utm_content=newsletter"><span>Register Now</span></a></figcaption></figure><h3 id="obscura-%E2%80%93-the-world%E2%80%99s-best-vpn-built-by-bitcoiners">Obscura – The World’s Best VPN Built by Bitcoiners</h3><p>Created by Carl Dong (former Bitcoin Core contributor), unlike other VPNs, it <em>can’t</em> log your activity by design, delivering verifiable privacy you can trust.</p><figure><a href="https://obscura.net/?ref=tftc.io"><img src="https://www.tftc.io/content/images/2025/08/newsletter-1.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1920" height="505" srcset="https://www.tftc.io/content/images/size/w600/2025/08/newsletter-1.jpg 600w, https://www.tftc.io/content/images/size/w1000/2025/08/newsletter-1.jpg 1000w, https://www.tftc.io/content/images/size/w1600/2025/08/newsletter-1.jpg 1600w, https://www.tftc.io/content/images/2025/08/newsletter-1.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></a><figcaption><a href="https://obscura.net/?ref=tftc.io" rel="noreferrer"><span>USE CODE TFTC25</span></a></figcaption></figure><p><strong>Outsmarts internet censorship</strong>: works even on the most restrictive Wi-Fi networks where other VPNs fail.<br><strong>Pay with bitcoin over Lightning:</strong> better privacy and low fees.<br><strong>No email required: </strong>accounts are generated like bitcoin wallets.<br><strong>No trade-offs</strong>: browse freely with fast, reliable speeds.</p><p><strong>Exclusive Deal for TFTC Listeners:</strong><br>Sign up at <a href="https://obscura.net/?ref=tftc.io" rel="noopener">obscura.net</a> and use code <strong>TFTC25</strong> for <strong>25% off your first 12 months</strong>.</p><p>Now available on <strong>macOS, iOS, and WireGuard</strong>, with more platforms coming soon — so your privacy travels with you wherever you go.</p><hr><p><em>Ten31, the largest bitcoin-focused investor, has deployed $200M across 30+ companies through three funds. I am a Managing Partner at Ten31 and am very proud of the work we are doing. Learn more at </em><a href="https://ten31.vc/invest?ref=tftc.io" rel="noreferrer">ten31.vc/invest</a><em>.</em></p><hr><p><strong>Final thought...</strong></p><p>Rest in peace, Charlie Kirk. Pray for humanity and for peace. </p><hr><p><em>Download our free browser extension, <strong>Opportunity Cost</strong>: </em><a href="https://www.opportunitycost.app/?ref=tftc.io">https://www.opportunitycost.app/</a> start thinking in SATS today. </p><p><em>Get this newsletter sent to your inbox daily: </em><a href="https://www.tftc.io/bitcoin-brief/"><em>https://www.tftc.io/bitcoin-brief/</em></a></p><p><em>Subscribe to our YouTube channels and follow us on Nostr and X:</em></p>
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->
  <!--[if mso]>
        <noscript>
        <xml>
        <o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
          <o:AllowPNG/>
          <o:PixelsPerInch>96</o:PixelsPerInch>
        </o:OfficeDocumentSettings>
        </xml>
        </noscript>
        <![endif]-->
  <!--[if lte mso 11]>
        <style type="text/css">
          .mj-outlook-group-fix { width:100% !important; }
        </style>
        <![endif]-->
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  

 
<!--kg-card-end: html-->

                        <div id="referral-container-end">
        <div>
          <p><img src="https://www.tftc.io/content/images/2022/02/TFTC_03_Cream.png" alt="TFTC"></p><svg viewBox="2190 54 2569 417" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg">
                        <path d="M2223.75,408 L2223.75,240 L2285.25,240 L2384.75,408 L2422.25,408 L2319.25,238 C2328.91667,236.666667 2339.08333,234.333333 2349.75,231 C2360.41667,227.666667 2370.16667,222.583333 2379,215.75 C2387.83333,208.916667 2395.16667,200 2401,189 C2406.83333,178 2409.75,164 2409.75,147 C2409.75,131.666667 2407.25,118.666667 2402.25,108 C2397.25,97.3333333 2390.91667,88.5 2383.25,81.5 C2375.58333,74.5 2366.91667,69.1666667 2357.25,65.5 C2347.58333,61.8333333 2338.08333,59.1666667 2328.75,57.5 C2319.41667,55.8333333 2310.75,54.8333333 2302.75,54.5 C2294.75,54.1666667 2288.41667,54 2283.75,54 L2283.75,54 L2190.75,54 L2190.75,408 L2223.75,408 Z M2293.75,210 L2223.75,210 L2223.75,84 L2293.75,84 C2311.08333,84 2325.16667,86.1666667 2336,90.5 C2346.83333,94.8333333 2355.25,100.166667 2361.25,106.5 C2367.25,112.833333 2371.33333,119.666667 2373.5,127 C2375.66667,134.333333 2376.75,141 2376.75,147 C2376.75,153 2375.66667,159.666667 2373.5,167 C2371.33333,174.333333 2367.25,181.166667 2361.25,187.5 C2355.25,193.833333 2346.83333,199.166667 2336,203.5 C2325.16667,207.833333 2311.08333,210 2293.75,210 L2293.75,210 Z M2761.75,408 L2761.75,378 L2570.25,378 L2570.25,240 L2742.25,240 L2742.25,210 L2570.25,210 L2570.25,84 L2753.75,84 L2753.75,54 L2537.25,54 L2537.25,408 L2761.75,408 Z M2981.25,408 L3070.75,93 L3071.75,93 L3161.25,408 L3201.75,408 L3304.75,54 L3270.75,54 L3182.75,367.5 L3181.75,367.5 L3092.25,54 L3050.25,54 L2960.75,367.5 L2959.75,367.5 L2871.75,54 L2837.75,54 L2940.75,408 L2981.25,408 Z M3385.25,408 L3425.25,314 L3612.75,314 L3651.25,408 L3688.25,408 L3539.25,54 L3505.25,54 L3350.75,408 L3385.25,408 Z M3600.75,284 L3438.25,284 L3520.75,90 L3600.75,284 Z M3822.25,408 L3822.25,240 L3883.75,240 L3983.25,408 L4020.75,408 L3917.75,238 C3927.41667,236.666667 3937.58333,234.333333 3948.25,231 C3958.91667,227.666667 3968.66667,222.583333 3977.5,215.75 C3986.33333,208.916667 3993.66667,200 3999.5,189 C4005.33333,178 4008.25,164 4008.25,147 C4008.25,131.666667 4005.75,118.666667 4000.75,108 C3995.75,97.3333333 3989.41667,88.5 3981.75,81.5 C3974.08333,74.5 3965.41667,69.1666667 3955.75,65.5 C3946.08333,61.8333333 3936.58333,59.1666667 3927.25,57.5 C3917.91667,55.8333333 3909.25,54.8333333 3901.25,54.5 C3893.25,54.1666667 3886.91667,54 3882.25,54 L3882.25,54 L3789.25,54 L3789.25,408 L3822.25,408 Z M3892.25,210 L3822.25,210 L3822.25,84 L3892.25,84 C3909.58333,84 3923.66667,86.1666667 3934.5,90.5 C3945.33333,94.8333333 3953.75,100.166667 3959.75,106.5 C3965.75,112.833333 3969.83333,119.666667 3972,127 C3974.16667,134.333333 3975.25,141 3975.25,147 C3975.25,153 3974.16667,159.666667 3972,167 C3969.83333,174.333333 3965.75,181.166667 3959.75,187.5 C3953.75,193.833333 3945.33333,199.166667 3934.5,203.5 C3923.66667,207.833333 3909.58333,210 3892.25,210 L3892.25,210 Z M4240.75,408 C4271.41667,408 4297.41667,404.25 4318.75,396.75 C4340.08333,389.25 4357.83333,379.666667 4372,368 C4386.16667,356.333333 4397.33333,343.416667 4405.5,329.25 C4413.66667,315.083333 4419.66667,301.5 4423.5,288.5 C4427.33333,275.5 4429.75,263.75 4430.75,253.25 C4431.75,242.75 4432.25,235.333333 4432.25,231 C4432.25,226.666667 4431.75,219.25 4430.75,208.75 C4429.75,198.25 4427.33333,186.5 4423.5,173.5 C4419.66667,160.5 4413.66667,146.916667 4405.5,132.75 C4397.33333,118.583333 4386.16667,105.666667 4372,94 C4357.83333,82.3333333 4340.08333,72.75 4318.75,65.25 C4297.41667,57.75 4271.41667,54 4240.75,54 L4240.75,54 L4131.25,54 L4131.25,408 L4240.75,408 Z M4232.25,378 L4164.25,378 L4164.25,84 L4232.25,84 C4255.58333,84 4277.41667,86.9166667 4297.75,92.75 C4318.08333,98.5833333 4335.75,107.5 4350.75,119.5 C4365.75,131.5 4377.58333,146.75 4386.25,165.25 C4394.91667,183.75 4399.25,205.666667 4399.25,231 C4399.25,256.333333 4394.91667,278.25 4386.25,296.75 C4377.58333,315.25 4365.75,330.5 4350.75,342.5 C4335.75,354.5 4318.08333,363.416667 4297.75,369.25 C4277.41667,375.083333 4255.58333,378 4232.25,378 L4232.25,378 Z M4649.25,417 C4663.58333,417 4677.41667,414.833333 4690.75,410.5 C4704.08333,406.166667 4715.83333,399.75 4726,391.25 C4736.16667,382.75 4744.25,372.333333 4750.25,360 C4756.25,347.666667 4759.25,333.5 4759.25,317.5 C4759.25,295.5 4754.75,278.25 4745.75,265.75 C4736.75,253.25 4725.5,243.5 4712,236.5 C4698.5,229.5 4683.83333,223.916667 4668,219.75 C4652.16667,215.583333 4637.5,210.75 4624,205.25 C4610.5,199.75 4599.25,192.25 4590.25,182.75 C4581.25,173.25 4576.75,159.666667 4576.75,142 C4576.75,130.666667 4578.91667,120.833333 4583.25,112.5 C4587.58333,104.166667 4593.33333,97.25 4600.5,91.75 C4607.66667,86.25 4616.08333,82.0833333 4625.75,79.25 C4635.41667,76.4166667 4645.58333,75 4656.25,75 C4671.58333,75 4684.83333,77.9166667 4696,83.75 C4707.16667,89.5833333 4716.91667,98.3333333 4725.25,110 L4725.25,110 L4753.75,89.5 C4741.75,73.5 4727.5,62.0833333 4711,55.25 C4694.5,48.4166667 4676.58333,45 4657.25,45 C4642.25,45 4627.91667,47.0833333 4614.25,51.25 C4600.58333,55.4166667 4588.5,61.5833333 4578,69.75 C4567.5,77.9166667 4559.16667,88.0833333 4553,100.25 C4546.83333,112.416667 4543.75,126.333333 4543.75,142 C4543.75,158.666667 4546.33333,172.666667 4551.5,184 C4556.66667,195.333333 4563.58333,204.75 4572.25,212.25 C4580.91667,219.75 4590.66667,225.833333 4601.5,230.5 C4612.33333,235.166667 4623.5,239.333333 4635,243 C4646.5,246.666667 4657.66667,250.333333 4668.5,254 C4679.33333,257.666667 4689.08333,262.083333 4697.75,267.25 C4706.41667,272.416667 4713.33333,279 4718.5,287 C4723.66667,295 4726.25,305.166667 4726.25,317.5 C4726.25,328.166667 4724.16667,337.75 4720,346.25 C4715.83333,354.75 4710.16667,362 4703,368 C4695.83333,374 4687.41667,378.666667 4677.75,382 C4668.08333,385.333333 4657.75,387 4646.75,387 C4629.08333,387 4613.33333,383.333333 4599.5,376 C4585.66667,368.666667 4574.41667,357.5 4565.75,342.5 L4565.75,342.5 L4534.25,363.5 C4548.25,382.833333 4565.08333,396.583333 4584.75,404.75 C4604.41667,412.916667 4625.91667,417 4649.25,417 Z" fill="currentColor"></path>
                    </svg>
        </div>
        <h4>Spread the signal, <br>earn Bitcoin.</h4>
        <p>Get your unique referral link when you subscribe.</p>
        <p><a href="https://www.tftc.io/rewards">Learn more →</a>
      </p></div>
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Becoming the person who does the thing (184 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fredrivett.com/2025/09/10/becoming-the-person-who-does-the-thing/</link>
            <guid>45220656</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 10:24:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.fredrivett.com/2025/09/10/becoming-the-person-who-does-the-thing/">https://www.fredrivett.com/2025/09/10/becoming-the-person-who-does-the-thing/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45220656">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>It can be disorienting when our beliefs shift. The world we helped create no longer exists, and our role in it transforms too.</p>
<p>It can be unsettling, naturally. But that's kind of the point.</p>
<p>Looking back at times when I held certain beliefs—about how the world works, and what my role in this story is—it can feel less like a mod was installed and more like an entirely new operating system was swapped in.</p>
<p>Up until my late twenties, I could count the number of times I had been to the gym on one hand.</p>
<p>And worse, as a nerd, I was quietly proud of it. Why waste hours a week on something that hardly mattered? I have better things to do. I pitied the jocks who slaved away in the gym chasing vanity. What for? I don't need that. Who cares?</p>
<p>Like all childish thinking, it contained some truth. Physical fitness is less important than spiritual, emotional, and mental fitness; but it’s still important.</p>
<p>Even Paul, one of history’s most influential figures, with a worldview shaped by the utter centrality of spiritual health, <a href="https://www.bible.com/bible/111/1TI.4.8.NIV" target="_blank">said as much</a>.</p>
<p>Your beliefs—and therefore approach to what a healthy life looks like—are foundational. It might sound obvious, but what you believe a "life well lived" looks like has a pretty transformative impact on both what life you end up building and how well lived it looks.</p>
<p>So if we’re a product of our beliefs and our most formative preconceptions are imposed by others, then where’s the hope?</p>
<p>We build, layer upon layer, and the layers laid first—now deeply buried within—are the ones we had the least say in.</p>
<p>We didn't pick them, but they shape everything we are and do. Bad luck, I guess.</p>
<p>Thankfully, we are dynamic beings. Old beliefs can peel off, and new ones take their place. Later layers can somehow seep deeper. Some recent beliefs can even become cornerstones.</p>
<p>For me, something shifted in my late twenties. Growing up I guess you could call it. I don’t remember the exact straw that broke the camel’s back, but a desire for change grew. I started working out.</p>
<p>It began slowly, but I began. Knee press-ups to start, later adding assisted pull-ups.</p>
<p>If anyone was watching, it would have looked stupid. A grown man barely able to push himself off the floor. But I showed up and put in my reps, day by day, week by week, in the privacy of my bedroom.</p>
<p>As the weeks and months passed, my strength grew.</p>
<p>Eventually, I graduated to full press-ups and pull-ups, no mods required.</p>
<p>Every small win reinforced the last and led me further away from who I used to be.</p>
<p>Fast forward almost to a decade and I feel a lot more friction <em>not</em> going to the gym than I do <em>going</em>. Cognitive dissonance is wonderful when it’s on your side, and it pops up whenever my healthy-Fred self-identity and actions diverge.</p>
<p>I'm far from a gym junkie—it hasn't become my life—but I go every weekday, 20 minutes a day. I arrive, do my workout, and leave, while most people are just getting started.</p>
<p>Our self-identity dictates everything, but it is not set in stone.</p>
<p>Changing our beliefs isn’t easy. Both those about the world around us and the world within. We can't simply will our way there and snap our fingers. We must journey. As with all great things, it's a process.</p>
<p>But it is possible. A well-trodden path is ahead for those who wish to walk it.</p>
<p>So how do you? How do you <em>become the person who does the thing</em>?</p>
<p>Earlier this week I spent a couple hours crafting my digital <a href="https://www.fredrivett.com/shelf" target="_blank">/shelf</a>, a place where I can put the things that have impacted me the most up for all to see, so others can take them for themselves should they wish.</p>
<p>On it are these two quotes that have been living rent-free in my head from the beginning. Together, they create a twin-cog flywheel that cannot be stopped:</p>
<blockquote>
<a href="https://seths.blog/2013/07/people-like-us-do-stuff-like-this/" target="_blank">“People like us do things like this”</a>
<cite>Seth Godin</cite>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<a href="https://jamesclear.com/quotes/every-action-you-take-is-a-vote-for-the-type-of-person-you-wish-to-become" target="_blank">“Every action you take is a vote for the type of person you wish to become”</a>
<cite>James Clear</cite>
</blockquote>
<p>Your actions follow your self-beliefs.</p>
<p>If you identity as a failure, incapable of achievement, unfit, unlovable, destined to play a bit-part role in your own story, then by heck no matter how much willpower you put in to push that boulder up the hill, it will return to its place.</p>
<p>But there's a way through: every action you take is a vote for who you wish to become. Every day you wake up, look your old identity in the eye and say "thanks for your service, but you're not needed around here anymore," step forward and lean in, is a day your new identity is built.</p>
<p>It takes time. You have to actually want it. You have to choose to adopt a new mindset. Rome wasn't built in a day. But it comes, a little like how <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2018/08/08/all-at-once/" rel="nofollow noreferrer" target="_blank">Hazel Grace Lancaster describes falling in love in The Fault In Our Stars</a>: <em>"slowly, and then all at once."</em></p>
<p>The path is there, should you choose.</p>
<p>Identify where your identity needs to shift. Then take a step. Cast today’s vote. Find your way through.</p>
<p>Do that day by day, then soon enough, your inner world will shift and recalibrate around the new reality you're co-creating.</p>
<p>Then one day you'll see it.</p>
<p>People like us really do things like this.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I made a generative online drum machine with ClojureScript (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dopeloop.ai/beat-maker/</link>
            <guid>45220069</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 08:44:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dopeloop.ai/beat-maker/">https://dopeloop.ai/beat-maker/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45220069">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Qwen3-Next (478 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://qwen.ai/blog?id=4074cca80393150c248e508aa62983f9cb7d27cd&amp;from=research.latest-advancements-list</link>
            <guid>45219228</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 06:32:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://qwen.ai/blog?id=4074cca80393150c248e508aa62983f9cb7d27cd&#x26;from=research.latest-advancements-list">https://qwen.ai/blog?id=4074cca80393150c248e508aa62983f9cb7d27cd&#x26;from=research.latest-advancements-list</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45219228">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://qwen.ai/blog?id=4074cca80393150c248e508aa62983f9cb7d27cd&from=research.latest-advancements-list: Error: getaddrinfo ENOTFOUND qwen.ai]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Debian 13, Postgres, and the US time zones (255 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rachelbythebay.com/w/2025/09/11/debtz/</link>
            <guid>45218111</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 02:33:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rachelbythebay.com/w/2025/09/11/debtz/">https://rachelbythebay.com/w/2025/09/11/debtz/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45218111">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://rachelbythebay.com/w/2025/09/11/debtz/: Error: Request failed with status code 404]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The challenge of maintaining curl (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/Articles/1034966/</link>
            <guid>45217858</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 01:42:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/1034966/">https://lwn.net/Articles/1034966/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45217858">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<blockquote>
<b>Benefits for LWN subscribers</b>
<p>
The primary benefit from <a href="https://lwn.net/Promo/nst-nag5/subscribe">subscribing to LWN</a>
       is helping to keep us publishing, but, beyond that, subscribers get
       immediate access to all site content and access to a number of extra
       site features.  Please sign up today!
</p></blockquote>
<p>
Keynote sessions at Open Source Summit events tend not to allow much time for
detailed talks, and the 2025 <a href="https://events.linuxfoundation.org/open-source-summit-europe/">Open
Source Summit Europe</a> did not diverge from that pattern.  Even so,
Daniel Stenberg, the maintainer of the <a href="https://curl.se/">curl</a>
project, managed to cram a lot into the 15&nbsp;minutes given to him.
Like the maintainers of many other projects, Stenberg is feeling some
stress, and the problems appear to be getting worse over time.
</p><p>

<a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/1034968/"><img src="https://static.lwn.net/images/conf/2025/osseu/DanielStenberg-sm.png" alt="[Daniel Stenberg]" title="Daniel Stenberg"></a>

Curl, he began, is "<q>a small project with a big impact</q>".  It began in
1996 with all of 100&nbsp;lines of code; it has since grown to 180,000
lines that have been contributed by 1,400 authors.  In any given month,
there are 20-25 developers who are actively contributing to curl.  The
project has exactly one full-time employee — that being Stenberg himself.
</p><p>
The program is widely used, having been deployed in at least one-billion
devices.  Just about anything that occasionally connects to the net, he
said, uses curl to do it.  But using curl is different from supporting its
development.  As an example, he put up a slide listing the 47 car brands
that use curl in their products; he followed it with a slide listing the
brands that contribute to curl.  The second slide, needless to say, was
empty.  (A version of both slides can be seen on <a href="https://mastodon.social/@bagder/115025727082593712">this page</a>).
</p><p>
Companies tend to assume that somebody else is paying for the development
of open-source software, so they do not have to contribute.  He emphasized
that he has released curl under a free license, so there is no <i>legal</i>
problem with what these companies are doing.  But, he suggested, these
companies might want to think a bit more about the future of the software
they depend on.
</p><p>
Open-source software is the best choice, he said, but maintaining it is a
tough job.  Most projects out there have a single maintainer, and that
person is often doing the work in their spare time, without funding.
Maintenance involves a lot of tasks, including taking care of security,
reviewing patches, writing documentation, keeping the web site going,
administering the mailing list, and a long list of other tasks.
Occasionally, if a little time is left over, it might also be possible to
do a bit of feature development.  That is a lot for one person to
keep up with.
</p><p>
Companies have a certain tendency to make things worse.  He put up an
excerpt of a message from Apple support, referring a customer to the curl
project for help with their (Apple) device.  He has received demands from
companies for
information on the project's development and security practices, often with
tight deadlines for a response.  He typically replies by sending back a
support contract; that usually results in never hearing from the company
again, he said.  More recently, he has been getting demands from European
companies seeking information on the curl project's Cyber Resilience Act
compliance practices.
</p><p>
Some communications are rather less humorous than that; one email
came with a subject reading "<q>I will slaughter you</q>".  He gets emails
from people who found his address in the license notices shipped with their
automobiles asking for support.  But he also gets nice thank-you emails at
times.
</p><p>
Problematic email takes other forms as well.  There is an increasing crowd
of people who ask a large language model to "<q>find a problem in curl,
make it sound terrible</q>", then send the result, which is never correct,
to the project, thinking that they are somehow helping.  Dealing with these
useless problem reports takes an increasing amount of time.
</p><p>
Recently, the curl project, like many operators of web sites, has been
contending with distributed denial-of-service attacks by scrapers run by AI
companies.  He put up a link to <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/1008897/">LWN's article
on this problem</a> for those who are unfamiliar with it.  The curl site
consumes a massive amount of bandwidth every month, but only 0.01% of that
is source downloads.  Most of the rest is bot traffic.  That, too, adds to
the difficulty of maintaining the project.
</p><p>
He concluded the brief talk with one last email; it was from an 11-year-old
child who had found curl useful in some project they were working on.  It
included an expression of gratitude that, Stenberg said, was truly
heartwarming.
</p><p>
[Thanks to the Linux Foundation, LWN's travel sponsor, for supporting our
travel to this event.]<br clear="all"></p><table>
           <tbody><tr><th colspan="2">Index entries for this article</th></tr>
           <tr><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/ConferenceIndex/">Conference</a></td><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/ConferenceIndex/#Open_Source_Summit_Europe-2025">Open Source Summit Europe/2025</a></td></tr>
            </tbody></table><br clear="all">
<hr>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The effects of algorithms on the public discourse (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tekhne.dev/internet-resist/</link>
            <guid>45217545</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:39:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tekhne.dev/internet-resist/">https://tekhne.dev/internet-resist/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45217545">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    

    
        
    

    
        

        <p>
            <i>
                <time datetime="2025-09-09T23:59Z">
                    09/09/2025
                </time>
            </i>
        </p>
    

    <p>Come listen to the "old man yelling at clouds" in me for a bit.</p>
<p><img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/tekhne/metaimageinternet.webp" alt="Old Man Yelling at Cloud"></p>
<blockquote>
<p><em><strong>tl;dr:</strong></em> The internet is changing for the worse (or getting 'enshittified'). In this post, I write about the effects of algorithms on the public discourse to illustrate a greater point on the enshittification of the internet. Then, I offer my personal notes and curated resources to guide you on your personal internet <em>de</em>shittification journey.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I miss the old internet, and I don't mean the slow dial-up internet. No, I miss the internet specifically before it collapsed into a single, endless feed that we access through proprietary apps (now with AI slop!). I miss how it was a network that's both human, and humane. Back when it wasn't (primarily, at least) an algorithmic black hole made to just suck us in. Maybe it's the increasing corporate ownership of the internet that took people's agency from their hands. Who knows?</p>
<p>I want to remember, for example (and hopefully help rebuild) the internet where actual humans discovered each other's work by following trails others cared enough to leave behind; not because an LLM or some billionaire brat's<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1">1</a></sup> algorithm 'fed' it to them. We used to use our curiosity to find stuff we liked, which felt more satisfying than any algorithm's statistically-determined aggregation.</p>
<p>I've had this blog hosted on <a href="https://bearblog.dev/">BearBlog</a> for more than a month now, and thanks to the community here, I've rediscovered the indie web. What's left of it, I mean. Still, it has been an absolute joy to read human-written words on all kinds of things I'm interested in. Many of my thoughts on the internet and the digital world as a whole were shaped by those. How cool is that! If this kind of an internet is still possible, why is it such a small part of the general network? Well, money. Here are examples to what makes money on the internet:</p>
<h2 id="context-collapse">Context Collapse</h2><p>I recently watched a great video from Technology Connections titled 'Algorithms Are Breaking How We Think' (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QEJpZjg8GuA">YouTube Link</a>/<a href="https://invidious.nerdvpn.de/watch?v=QEJpZjg8GuA">Invidious Link</a>).</p>
<p>Technology Connections talks about something known as 'context collapse'. The idea behind the term is that by combining multiple audiences into one single context, algorithmic media platforms bring out (usually) negative reactions from unrelated audiences. This means that even though every one of the billions of internet users have entirely different lives and backgrounds, social media platforms (even the seemingly-personalised ones like TikTok) have one single context on their main tabs. That context is that the user is a number among many that must be kept positive at all costs. Consequently, the ideal user of modern media platforms has no individual identity, and is perfectly happy with what's given to them by the algorithm.</p>
<p>As an example, think of how many of the posts you see on Instagram are actually from people or accounts that you deliberately chose to see. On the other hand, think of how many posts are from accounts you couldn't care less about, but the algorithm thinks you should (don't forget the 1/1 ad-to-post ratio!). The same thing goes for many other platforms. Even though some, like YouTube, at least <em>allow</em> you to use the platform with almost full agency over what you see<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2">2</a></sup>, not many platforms do this. You have no choice but to use the official app with their own black-box algorithm<sup id="fnref-3"><a href="#fn-3">3</a></sup>. This way, the user's individual identity is replaced with that of the "average internet user", which they share with billions of other 'averages'.</p>
<p>The effect that this has on online discourse is immense. As every internet user must know, the internet (as it is today) is full of negativity. You might look at this and say, "Humans are inherently evil," and lose all hope in humanity given how horribly they treat each other on the internet. The truth is, the way we have constructed this space deindividualizes, alienates and aggregates us to such an extent. In other words, when billions of us are thrown into one large melting pot of context, the output of that pot becomes as impure as it could possibly be. It does not reflect how we form groups, act, and react in other areas of life.</p>
<h2 id="interpretive-communities">Interpretive Communities</h2><p>Literary theorist Stanley Fish argued that we as individuals interpret any given text (in this case, social media content) "because each of us is part of an interpretive community that gives us a particular way of reading a text."<sup id="fnref-4"><a href="#fn-4">4</a></sup> That interpretive community usually isn't there when we are fed what the algorithm thinks we'll consume. We may share something thinking that people like us will see it share their opinions. However, because of the way that algorithms work, engagement is the main driver of a post's visibility; so here comes 10 million people who have no clue of the context on that thought you shared about your niche interest.</p>
<p>Suddenly your post is full of over-the-top jokes and non-content-related quips from members of a completely random mix of audiences. As the algorithm prioritizes engagement, your post's new mixing pot of clueless audiences outnumbers the genuinely-interested audience of your own niche corner of the internet (if that even exists anymore), and they comment about everything BUT the content.</p>
<h2 id="think-thats-a-stretch">Think That's a Stretch?</h2><p>Okay, that was a hypothetical scenario, but here's a <em>real</em> community that massively benefited from all this: the incel community. Adam Aleksic’s book <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/776856/algospeak-by-adam-aleksic/">Algospeak: How Social Media Is Transforming the Future of Language</a> tackles with this exact topic. He argues that algorithms contributed to the wide-spread use of pseudo-scientific incel terms by way of increased exposure. Here are two of my highlights:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Once algorithms got involved, the incel terms were amplified by the online <em>Matthew effect</em>: a phenomenon where content that is slightly better at grabbing your attention performs exponentially better on social media."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Then, when these pseudo-scientific terms (think: 'alpha/beta male', 'chad', 'canthal tilt', 'looksmaxxing' etc.) are taken outside their respective interpretive communities and made hyper-visible, the mixing pot works its magic. From here, these terms make their way to the general public discourse:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Poe’s law explains how dangerous ideas spread as memes. If something is meant genuinely, but it is also crazy enough to be interpreted as a joke, people may reward it with “likes” and other engagement because they find it funny. Meanwhile, if something ironic is interpreted as genuine, people will be offended by it, which then also drives engagement as a form of ragebait. Either way, “edgy” humor is able to worm its way into the mainstream via the algorithm."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So, if you want to get more people to know about your extreme views, package them as 'dumb jokes' for the algorithm to advertise to billions of people. At least that's what the incel community did, and succeeded. Can you even count how many times you heard or read those terms?</p>
<h2 id="okay-what-can-i-do">Okay, What Can I Do?</h2><p><img src="https://bear-images.sfo2.cdn.digitaloceanspaces.com/tekhne/resist-keithharring.webp" alt="Resist"></p>
<p>Now, this is the part where I stop being the old man yelling at the cloud and start proposing a new way of using the internet. In this section, I have gathered some links to things that I either use or have used in the past, some personal notes on media I consumed, and quotes by brilliant writers. I'm doing this because I want to share a little bit of what I learned during my research on the open internet, even if they are not directly related to algorithmic feeds.</p>
<h3 id="use-and-support-free-libre-software">Use and Support Free (Libre) Software</h3><ul>
<li>Use RSS reader apps. Just go to a site blog or news site you like, then copy and paste its RSS link into your app of choice (almost all websites have an RSS link). With that, you've created your own algorithm. One that is owned and controlled by you, instead of silicon valley tech-bros.</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://www.theverge.com/24063290/fediverse-explained-activitypub-social-media-open-protocol">federated social media</a> instead of centralized ones that impede free speech and breach your right to privacy.</li>
<li>For secure messaging, <a href="https://signal.org/">use Signal where possible</a>, instead of WhatsApp or iMessage. Did you know that the US Government can access your messages if they have a warrant, regardless of your encryption settings? See: "<a href="https://propertyofthepeople.org/document-detail/?doc-id=21114562">Jan. 2021 FBI Infographic re Lawful Access to Secure Messaging Apps Data</a>"</li>
<li>If you're using Android, have a look at the many apps in <a href="https://f-droid.org/">F-Droid</a>: a FOSS (Free and Open Source Software) alternative to Google's Play Store.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linuxmint.com/">Use GNU/Linux on your personal computer</a> to make technology fun again, and to say "F**K YOU" to Microsoft<sup id="fnref-5"><a href="#fn-5">5</a></sup>. If you're using a Mac, see: <a href="https://asahilinux.org/">Asahi Linux</a></li>
<li>If you want your Android phone to have better battery life, longer security support, increased privacy and more features; consider not using Google's version of Android at all! (See: <a href="https://grapheneos.org/">GrapheneOS(Only for Pixel devices)</a>, Others: <a href="https://e.foundation/e-os/">/e/OS</a>, <a href="https://lineageos.org/">LineageOS</a>)</li>
<li>(Advanced) If you have an old and unused laptop or desktop PC around, re-purpose it to create your own cloud (with your own music and video streaming services, storage, photo library and more)! See: <a href="https://casaos.zimaspace.com/">CasaOS</a> or <a href="https://yunohost.org/">YunoHost</a></li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>"The tech stack we use is an endorsement of the companies behind it. Technological platforms are not neutral. If we truly want to resist the digital coup that is currently under way, we need to normalize the use of free, open source solutions."</p>
<p><strong>--- and ---</strong></p>
<p>"We constrain our imaginations when we subordinate our creations to names owned by fascist tycoons. Imagine the author of a book telling people to "read my Amazon". A great director trying to promote their film by saying "click on my Max". That's how much they've pickled your brain when you refer to your own work and your own voice within the context of their walled garden. There is no such thing as "my Substack", there is only your writing, and a forever fight against the world of pure enshittification."</p>
<p><strong>---</strong> <em>highlights from "<a href="https://news.elenarossini.com/this-is-what-resistance-to-the-digital-coup-looks-like/">This is what resistance to the digital coup looks like</a>" by Elena Rossini</em></p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="curate-over-engage">Curate Over Engage</h3><ul>
<li><p><a href="https://bearblog.dev/">Start a blog</a> if you want. Share your experiences or thoughts about <em>anything</em>. You don't have to write something that has never been written before. Just have fun, and some people will probably benefit from, and enjoy your writing <em>at some point.</em></p>
</li>
<li><p>Scavenging for information used to be optimal, but now we live in a world of information overload. Notice the algorithm's firm grip over your attention.</p>
<ul>
<li>Prioritize discernment; focus on what information is needed and how it connects to your existing knowledge.</li>
<li>Set boundaries on information consumption by using attentional filters.</li>
<li>Block out redundant, overwhelming, or poor-quality information to avoid constant distraction.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p><em>On helping revive the human network of the internet:</em></p>
<p>"Regardless of the kind of site you have, whether its a modern site for a business or arts practice, or if its a personal homepage; setup a links page on your site and add links to your friends, people you’ve worked with, tools you’ve used, blogs you enjoy, other businesses, anything and everything that deserves to be seen; because it does deserve to be seen, and so do you!"</p>
<p>---<em>highlight from "<a href="https://thoughts.melonking.net/thoughts/every-site-needs-a-links-page-why-linking-matters">Why linking matters</a>" by Melon's Thoughts</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'll add more to this list as time goes on, and use it as my personal rolling list of apps, services, or notes for a more open and free internet. You can bookmark it if you like the list.</p>
<p>But for now, thank you for visiting my corner of the internet.</p>
<hr>
<p>This post was last edited <strong>1&nbsp;hour, 10&nbsp;minutes ago</strong>.</p>
<hr>
<section>
<ol>
<li id="fn-1"><p>Elon Musk, Mark Zuckerberg et al.<a href="#fnref-1">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn-2"><p>You can turn off recommendations and 'watch history' in YouTube. Either with in-app settings or, on desktop, with extensions like 'Minimal YouTube'. You can even use <a href="https://invidious.io/">Invidious</a>, even though Google absolutely hates it. Eat it, Google.<a href="#fnref-2">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn-3"><p>You technically have <em>some</em> options to get rid of algorithms and AI-slop on other platforms too, but they only work on Android devices and aren't stable. See: <a href="https://www.distractionfreeapps.com/">DistractionFreeApps for Instagram</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/crimera/piko#:~:text=Details">Piko for Twitter</a><a href="#fnref-3">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn-4"><p>Fish, Stanley (2000). "How to Recognize a Poem When You See One". <em>Falling into Theory: Conflicting Views on Reading Literature</em>: 267–278.<a href="#fnref-4">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn-5"><p>See: <a href="https://blog.boycat.io/posts/microsoft-israel-gaza-war-leaked-documents-complicity">"Everything you need to know about how Microsoft aided Israel’s war on Gaza"</a><a href="#fnref-5">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>


    

    
        
            <p>
                
                    <a href="https://tekhne.dev/arsiv/?q=algorithm">#algorithm</a>
                
                    <a href="https://tekhne.dev/arsiv/?q=apps">#apps</a>
                
                    <a href="https://tekhne.dev/arsiv/?q=en">#en</a>
                
                    <a href="https://tekhne.dev/arsiv/?q=libresoftware">#libresoftware</a>
                
                    <a href="https://tekhne.dev/arsiv/?q=list">#list</a>
                
                    <a href="https://tekhne.dev/arsiv/?q=tech">#tech</a>
                
                    <a href="https://tekhne.dev/arsiv/?q=theinternet">#theinternet</a>
                
            </p>
        

        
            


        
    


  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Float Exposed (376 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://float.exposed/</link>
            <guid>45217415</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:11:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://float.exposed/">https://float.exposed/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45217415">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="container">
		<div id="body">

			<p><span id="fp16">half</span><span id="bf16">bfloat</span><span id="fp32">float</span><span id="fp64">double</span>
			</p>

			<div id="value_section">
				<p>Value</p>
				</div>

			

			<div id="bits_section">
				<p>Bit Pattern</p>
				
			</div>

			

			

			


			<div id="slider_section">
				<p>Position within Significand–Exponent Range</p>
				
				<div id="slider_container">
					<p>0</p>
					<p>2<sup>52</sup>-1</p>
					<div id="slider_gutter_min">
						<p>0</p>
					</div>
					
					<div>
						<p>1</p>
					</div>
					
					<div>
						<p>30</p>
					</div>
					
					<div id="slider_gutter_max">
						<p>30</p>
					</div>
					
					
					
					
					
				</div>
			</div>

			

			<p>Evaluation in Base-2</p>

			<p>(−1<sub>2</sub>)<sup><span id="sign_2_component"></span><sub>2</sub></sup><span>×​</span>10<sub>2</sub><sup>(<span id="exponent_2_component"></span><sub>2</sub>&nbsp;−&nbsp;<span id="exponent_2_bias"></span><sub>2</sub>)</sup>​<span>×​</span><span id="implicit_bit_2_component"></span>.<span id="mantissa_2_component"></span><sub>2</sub>
			</p>

			<p>Evaluation in Base-10</p>

			<p><span id="sign_10_component"></span><span>×​</span>2<sup><span id="exponent_10_component"></span></sup><span>×​</span><span id="implicit_bit_10_component"></span>.<span id="mantissa_10_component"></span>
			</p>

			<p>Exact Base-10 Value</p>
			

			

			


			<div id="next_prev_delta_container">
				<p>Delta to Next/Previous Representable Value</p>
				
			</div>

			<div id="next_delta_container">
				<p>Delta to Next Representable Value</p>
				
			</div>

			<div id="prev_delta_container">
				<p>Delta to Previous Representable Value</p>
				
			</div>

			


		</div>
		<div id="footer"><p>Copyright © 2025 – <a href="https://ciechanow.ski/exposing-floating-point/">Bartosz Ciechanowski</a></p></div>

		<div>
			<p>A</p>
		</div>
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Toddlerbot: Open-Source Humanoid Robot (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://toddlerbot.github.io/</link>
            <guid>45217372</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:04:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://toddlerbot.github.io/">https://toddlerbot.github.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45217372">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
  <div>
            
            
            

            <p><span><sup>*</sup>Equal contribution,</span>
              <span><sup>†</sup>Equal advising</span>
            </p>

            <p><span>Stanford University</span>
            </p>

            
          </div>
  <!-- 
  <section class="hero teaser">
    <div class="container is-max-desktop">
      <div class="hero-body">
        <video id="teaser" autoplay muted loop playsinline height="100%">
          <source src="./static/videos/teaser.mp4" type="video/mp4">
        </video>
        <h2 class="subtitle has-text-centered">
          RoboCraft shapes elasto-plastic objects into various 3D target shapes in the real
          world.
        </h2>
      </div>
    </div>
  </section> -->

  <!-- <section class="section">
    <div class="container is-max-desktop"> -->
  <!-- Abstract. -->
  <!-- <div class="columns is-centered has-text-centered">
        <div class="column is-four-fifths">
          <h2 class="title is-3">Abstract</h2>
          <div class="content has-text-justified">
            <p>
              Learning-based robotics research driven by data demands a new approach to robot hardware design—one that
              serves as both a platform for policy execution and a tool for embodied data collection to train policies.
              We introduce ToddlerBot, a low-cost, open-source humanoid robot platform designed for scalable policy
              learning and research in robotics and AI. ToddlerBot enables seamless acquisition of high-quality
              simulation and real-world data. The plug-and-play zero-point calibration and transferable motor system
              identification ensure a high-fidelity digital twin, enabling zero-shot policy transfer from simulation to
              the real-world. A user-friendly teleoperation interface facilitates streamlined real-world data collection
              for learning motor skills from human demonstrations. Utilizing its data collection ability and
              anthropomorphic design, ToddlerBot is an ideal platform to perform whole-body loco-manipulation.
              Additionally, ToddlerBot's compact size (0.56m, 3.4kg) ensures safe operation in real-world environments.
              Reproducibility is achieved with an entirely 3D-printed, open-source design and commercially available
              components, keeping the total cost under 6,000 USD. Comprehensive documentation allows assembly and
              maintenance with basic technical expertise, as validated by a successful independent replication of the
              system. We demonstrate ToddlerBot's capabilities through arm span, payload, endurance tests,
              loco-manipulation tasks, and a collaborative long-horizon scenario where two robots tidy a toy session
              together. By advancing ML-compatibility, capability, and reproducibility, ToddlerBot provides a robust
              platform for scalable learning and dynamic policy execution in robotics research.
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div> -->
  <div>
      <p>
          <strong>TL;DR: ToddlerBot is a low-cost, open-source humanoid robot platform designed for
            scalable policy learning and research in robotics and AI.</strong>
        </p>
    </div>
  <!--/ Abstract. -->

  <!-- Paper video. -->
  <!-- <div class="columns is-centered has-text-centered">
        <div class="column is-four-fifths">
          <h2 class="title is-3">Video</h2>
          <div class="publication-video">
            <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o2LPhcZRtSo?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0"
              allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div> -->
  <!--/ Paper video. -->
  <!-- </div>
  </section> -->

  <div>
      <div>
          <h2>2.0 Release</h2>
          <p>
              <strong><em>See <a href="https://github.com/hshi74/toddlerbot/blob/main/CHANGELOG.md">CHANGELOG.md</a> for
                  details. 1x Speed unless otherwise noted.</em></strong>
            </p>

          <h3>New Capabilities</h3>
          <div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Cartwheel:</strong> Toddy successfully performs a highly dynamic cartwheel, showcasing its
                  agility and balance capabilities.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Cartwheel Failures:</strong> With naive <a href="https://xbpeng.github.io/projects/DeepMimic/index.html">DeepMimic</a> and domain
                  randomization,
                  the success rate is still low. But the good news is that Toddy is extremely robust—it almost never
                  breaks. Even if it breaks, it is super easy to fix.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Crawling:</strong> Toddy can crawl like a toddler, using its arms and legs in a
                  coordinated manner.
                </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <br>

          <div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Walking Faster:</strong> Toddy can walk faster in all directions (up to 0.25m/s) and rotate
                  faster in place (up to 1 rad/s).
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>VR Teleoperation:</strong> Real-time VR teleoperation with Meta quest 2.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Foundation Stereo Depth</strong> On-board (Jetson Orin NX 16GB) real-time (10Hz) depth
                  estimation from stereo fisheye cameras with <a href="https://github.com/NVlabs/FoundationStereo">Foundation
                    Stereo</a>.
                </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <br>
        </div>

      <div>
          <h2>Design</h2>
          <p>
              We present ToddleBot's mechatronic design in the figure below. We highlight ToddlerBot's 30
              active DoFs with orange markers: 7 DoFs per arm, 6 DoFs per leg, a 2-DoF neck, and a 2-DoF waist. Green
              markers indicate two end-effector designs—a compliant palm and a parallel-jaw gripper. Purple markers
              denote the sensor and electronics layout with exploded views, featuring two fisheye cameras, a speaker,
              two microphones, an IMU, and a Jetson Orin NX computer.
            </p>
          <div>
            <p><img src="https://toddlerbot.github.io/static/images/design.png" alt="Mechatronic Design.">
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>

      <div>
        <div>
          <h2>Results</h2>
          <p>
              <strong><em>1x Speed unless otherwise noted.</em></strong>
            </p>

          <h3>Capability: Arm Span, Payload, and Endurance</h3>
          <div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Arm Span Test:</strong> With a torso volume of 13x9x12 cm³, ToddlerBot
                  successfully grasps objects 14 times its torso volume (27x24x31 cm³) using its compliant palm
                  gripper.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Payload Test:</strong> ToddlerBot lifts 1,484 g (40% of its total weight) while
                  maintaining balance. To determine the limit, screws are incrementally added to a 3D-printed gripping
                  cup until it falls.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Endurance Test:</strong> Running a walking RL policy, ToddlerBot lasts 19 minutes before
                  overheating affects stability. It withstands up to 7 falls before breaking, but repairs take only 21
                  minutes of 3D printing and 14 minutes of assembly for full restoration.
                </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <br>

          <h3>Capability: Conversation, Push-ups, and Pull-ups</h3>
          <div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Conversation and Push-ups:</strong> This is achieved by integrating OpenAI's Realtime API
                  with GPT-4o for speech-to-text and text-to-speech. Push-ups are zero-shot sim-to-real transfer of
                  open-loop keyframe animation.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Pull-ups:</strong> We use an AprilTag to help ToddlerBot accurately locate the horizontal
                  bar. The rest is a zero-shot sim-to-real transfer of open-loop keyframe animation.
                </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <br>

          <h3>ML-Compatibility: Locomotion and Manipulation</h3>
          <div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Omnidirectional Walking:</strong> ToddlerBot achieves omnidirectional walking with RL and
                  zero-shot sim-to-real.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Bimanual Manipulation:</strong> This is an RGB-based diffusion policy trained with 60
                  demonstrations.
                </p>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Full-body Manipulation:</strong> This is also an RGB-based diffusion policy trained with 60
                  demonstrations.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Skill Chaining:</strong> ToddlerBot first executes a diffusion policy to grasp the handle,
                  while maintaining that pose, switched to the RL policy to push the wagon forward.
                </p>
            </div>
          </div>

          <h3>Reproducibility: Hardware and Policies</h3>
          <div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Manipulation Policy Zero-Shot Transfer:</strong> We successfully transfer manipulation
                  policy trained with data collected on Toddlerbot instance to another.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Two-Instance Collaboration Task:</strong> To demonstrate their equivalent performance of two
                  Toddlerbot Instances, both robots collaborate on a long-horizon room tidying task.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
              
              
              <p>
                  <strong>Easy-to-Build Test:</strong> We show that ToddlerBot is easy to build with fully
                  open-source assembly manuals and videos.
                </p>
            </div>
          </div>
        </div>
        <br>
      </div>
    </div>

  

  <div id="BibTeX">
      <h2>BibTeX</h2>
      <pre><code>@article{shi2025toddlerbot,
  title={ToddlerBot: Open-Source ML-Compatible Humanoid Platform for Loco-Manipulation},
  author={Shi, Haochen and Wang, Weizhuo and Song, Shuran and Liu, C. Karen},
  journal={arXiv preprint arXiv:2502.00893},
  year={2025}
}</code></pre>
    </div>

  <div id="Acknowledgement">
      <h2>Acknowledgement</h2>
      <p>The authors would like to express their gratitude to Kaizhe Hu for assembling the second instance of ToddlerBot
        and assisting with keyframe animation and demo recording. We also extend our thanks to Huy Ha, Yen-Jen Wang, Pei
        Xu, and Yifan Hou for their insightful discussions on locomotion, and to Sirui Chen, Chen Wang, and Yunfan Jiang
        for valuable input on manipulation policy deployment.
        We are grateful to Albert Wu for his guidance on mathematical formulation and notation. Additionally, we thank
        João Pedro Araújo for his assistance with the motion capture system.
        Finally, we appreciate the helpful discussions from all members of TML and REALab. This work was supported by
        National Science Foundation NSF-FRR-2153854, NSF-2143601, NSF-2037101, Sloan Fellowship, Stanford Institute for
        Human-Centered Artificial Intelligence, and Stanford Wu Tsai Human Performance Alliance.</p>
    </div>

  



</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why our website looks like an operating system (632 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://posthog.com/blog/why-os</link>
            <guid>45217269</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 23:45:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://posthog.com/blog/why-os">https://posthog.com/blog/why-os</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45217269">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>I have a problem with many large, technical websites.</p><p>Often times, I’ll want to refer to different pages at the same time. So I’ll <code>CMD</code> + click “a couple times” while browsing around and before I know it, I have 12 new tabs open – all indistinguishable from each other because they share the same favicon.</p><p>PostHog.com has the same problem – especially as the site has grown from supporting a handful of paid products to over a dozen.</p><p>As I looked for ways to solve this explosion of pages, I started to question many of the typical patterns that marketing &amp; docs websites have today.</p><p>Long-form scrolling. Oversized footers. Absurd whitespace.</p><p>These website <em>encourage</em> scrolling, but just to get people to the bottom of the page? And then what?</p><p>Why are we doing this? What if we just made better ways to consume content?</p><p>That’s the idea behind the new PostHog.com. You can multitask, open a few articles simultaneously, and move them around as you please. If anything there's a whitespace deficiency, and your fingers will be jealous you're not scrolling with them as much (because you're so engaged with our content).</p><p>It has window snapping, keyboard shortcuts, and a bookmark app. It works as well as you’d expect an operating system to work in a browser.</p><p>You can be reading the latest newsletter from Product for Engineers while watching a demo video in the corner and also playing Hedgehog Mode, the game.</p><p>I’ll be the first to admit it – an OS interface for a “website” is initially a jarring experience. I felt this as I built it. The human brain expects certain patterns within the confines of a browser viewport, and when it doesn’t get that assurance, it revolts.</p><p>But the more I used the new site, the more I started to like it. And the experience was the same for colleagues. And now I can’t imagine using anything else.</p><p>I had a lot of fun in building it with <span><a href="https://posthog.com/community/profiles/28804"><span><span><span>Eli Kinsey</span></span></span></a></span>. Throughout the site you’ll find:</p><ul><li>A <span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/products">Windows File Explorer</a></span> clone that also acts as the UI for <span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/merch">our merch store</a></span></li><li><span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/llm-analytics">Product pages</a></span> that resemble PowerPoint presentations</li><li>A <span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/customers">document editor</a></span> where you can actually edit content</li><li><span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/questions">Forums</a></span> designed to look like you’re reading newsgroups in Outlook Express</li><li>A <span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/demo">QuickTime clone</a></span></li><li>A lot of pages you’d expect to be well-designed that are… just <span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/changelog">formatted as spreadsheets</a></span></li><li>A screensaver and a <span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/display-options">library of desktop backgrounds</a></span></li><li>A plethora of <span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/kbd">keyboard shortcuts</a></span></li></ul><p>It was also an interesting learning curve for me in figuring out how to organize five years worth of content while making it scalable for the future. Some of the technical highlights:</p><ul><li>Separation of visual layer from content<ul><li>All product pages are now powered from JSON files (<span data-state="closed"><a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/PostHog/posthog.com/blob/windows-n-such/src/hooks/productData/session_replay.tsx" target="_blank"><span><span>example</span><svg width="100%" fill="currentColor" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7.995 5.75a.75.75 0 0 1 .75-.75h8.505c.966 0 1.75.784 1.75 1.75v9.496a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0V7.56L7.03 18.03a.75.75 0 0 1-1.06-1.061L16.44 6.5H8.744a.75.75 0 0 1-.75-.75Z" clip-rule="evenodd"></path></svg></span></a></span>). This means that JSON dictates page layouts, content presentation, feature-level competitor comparison charts, and more. It also contains an array of screenshots used in various places (both in light and dark mode, of course).</li><li>Eventually this will move to a repository that’s shared with the PostHog app, so all the information is powered from the same source.</li></ul></li><li>Skinning a site with themes <em>and</em> color schemes<ul><li>How do you maintain light and dark mode, along with themes across a handful of accent variations (primary, secondary, tertiary) in a way that all play well together? (I found this out, and I’ll write about it sometime!)</li></ul></li><li>A reference customer database<ul><li>I’ve created a single customer record <span data-state="closed"><a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/PostHog/posthog.com/blob/61ad1a9ea079d6e0422a95ab453acbddf4cdd5a4/src/hooks/useCustomers.tsx#L364" target="_blank"><span><span>in code</span><svg width="100%" fill="currentColor" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7.995 5.75a.75.75 0 0 1 .75-.75h8.505c.966 0 1.75.784 1.75 1.75v9.496a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0V7.56L7.03 18.03a.75.75 0 0 1-1.06-1.061L16.44 6.5H8.744a.75.75 0 0 1-.75-.75Z" clip-rule="evenodd"></path></svg></span></a></span> that contains: a) which products they use, b) quotes from specific people about individual products c) SVG logos that work in light and dark mode</li><li>This means that any quote can be presented on any page for any product without having to be hard-coded. It pulls in their name and photo, quote, and company logo, and can be filtered in reference to a specific product.</li></ul></li></ul><p>For a lot of this site, I was designing it <em>while</em> I was building UIs in Typescript and Tailwind. (The entire site is just a Git branch off our current site – it's all technically the same codebase. I just merged along the way over the last few months.)</p><p>Prototyping in a production-level environment was a great way to ideate and develop features along the way – stuff I never would have built if I were just going off of mockups. I did find myself <span data-state="closed"><a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://x.com/ninepixelgrid/status/1936994050625679692" target="_blank"><span><span>popping open Balsamiq while I was building</span><svg width="100%" fill="currentColor" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7.995 5.75a.75.75 0 0 1 .75-.75h8.505c.966 0 1.75.784 1.75 1.75v9.496a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0V7.56L7.03 18.03a.75.75 0 0 1-1.06-1.061L16.44 6.5H8.744a.75.75 0 0 1-.75-.75Z" clip-rule="evenodd"></path></svg></span></a></span> – but just long enough to flesh out some ideas.</p><p>So how will this pan out? Well, we’re about to find out. This feels like an early MVP – there’s a ton of stuff to improve upon from here.</p><p>But in the meantime, I hope you enjoy the new PostHog.com. Be curious, click around, and have some fun. I hope you enjoy your time here as much as we enjoyed building it.</p><p>If you're curious, <span data-state="closed"><a href="https://posthog.com/handbook/engineering/posthog-com/how-posthog-website-works">read more about how the site technically works</a></span>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fartscroll-Lid: An app that plays fart sounds when opening or closing a MacBook (215 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/iannuttall/fartscroll-lid</link>
            <guid>45216844</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 22:41:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/iannuttall/fartscroll-lid">https://github.com/iannuttall/fartscroll-lid</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45216844">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">FartScrollLid 💨</h2><a id="user-content-fartscrolllid-" aria-label="Permalink: FartScrollLid 💨" href="#fartscrolllid-"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A hilarious macOS app that plays fart sounds as you open and close your MacBook lid - inspired by the classic "fart scroll" browser extension!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>🎵 <strong>Dynamic Fart Sounds</strong> - Pitch changes based on lid angle (deep bass when closed, high squeaks when open)</li>
<li>🎯 <strong>Motion-Activated</strong> - Only farts when you're actively moving the lid</li>
<li>📊 <strong>Real-Time Monitoring</strong> - Shows lid angle, velocity, and fart parameters</li>
<li>😄 <strong>Funny Status Messages</strong> - "Maximum pressure!", "Gas escaping!", and more</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How It Works</h2><a id="user-content-how-it-works" aria-label="Permalink: How It Works" href="#how-it-works"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">FartScrollLid uses the MacBook's internal lid angle sensor (discovered through reverse engineering) to detect the angle between your laptop lid and base. When you move the lid, it triggers fart sounds with:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Pitch modulation</strong> based on lid angle (0-130 degrees)</li>
<li><strong>Volume control</strong> based on movement speed</li>
<li><strong>Instant response</strong> - farts stop immediately when you stop moving</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Requirements</h2><a id="user-content-requirements" aria-label="Permalink: Requirements" href="#requirements"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>macOS 11.5 or later</li>
<li>MacBook with lid angle sensor (most modern MacBooks)</li>
<li>A sense of humor</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Option 1: Build from Source</h3><a id="user-content-option-1-build-from-source" aria-label="Permalink: Option 1: Build from Source" href="#option-1-build-from-source"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Clone this repository:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/iannuttall/fartscroll-lid.git
cd fartscroll-lid"><pre>git clone https://github.com/iannuttall/fartscroll-lid.git
<span>cd</span> fartscroll-lid</pre></div>
<ol start="2" dir="auto">
<li>Open in Xcode:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="open FartScrollLid.xcodeproj"><pre>open FartScrollLid.xcodeproj</pre></div>
<ol start="3" dir="auto">
<li>Build and run (Cmd+R)</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Option 2: Download Release</h3><a id="user-content-option-2-download-release" aria-label="Permalink: Option 2: Download Release" href="#option-2-download-release"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Download the latest <code>.app</code> from the <a href="https://github.com/iannuttall/fartscroll-lid/releases">Releases</a> page.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Launch FartScrollLid</li>
<li>Click "Start Farting"</li>
<li>Move your MacBook lid up and down</li>
<li>Enjoy the symphony of farts!</li>
<li>Stop moving to silence the farts</li>
<li>Click "Stop Farting" when you've had enough fun</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Technical Details</h2><a id="user-content-technical-details" aria-label="Permalink: Technical Details" href="#technical-details"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Lid Angle Sensor</h3><a id="user-content-lid-angle-sensor" aria-label="Permalink: Lid Angle Sensor" href="#lid-angle-sensor"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Device</strong>: Apple HID device (VID=0x05AC, PID=0x8104)</li>
<li><strong>HID Usage</strong>: Sensor page (0x0020), Orientation usage (0x008A)</li>
<li><strong>Data format</strong>: 16-bit angle value in centidegrees (0.01° resolution)</li>
<li><strong>Range</strong>: 0-360 degrees</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Audio Engine</h3><a id="user-content-audio-engine" aria-label="Permalink: Audio Engine" href="#audio-engine"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Uses AVFoundation for real-time audio playback</li>
<li>Varispeed unit for pitch modulation (0.5x to 2.0x)</li>
<li>Smooth parameter ramping to avoid audio artifacts</li>
<li>Movement threshold: 2 deg/s minimum to trigger farts</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Project Structure</h2><a id="user-content-project-structure" aria-label="Permalink: Project Structure" href="#project-structure"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="FartScrollLid/
├── FartScrollLid.xcodeproj/    # Xcode project
├── FartScrollLid/              # Source code
│   ├── AppDelegate.m/h         # Main app controller
│   ├── FartScrollLid.m/h       # Lid angle sensor interface
│   ├── FartAudioEngine.m/h     # Fart sound engine
│   ├── NSLabel.m/h             # Custom label class
│   └── FART.wav                # Fart sound file
└── README.md                   # This file"><pre><code>FartScrollLid/
├── FartScrollLid.xcodeproj/    # Xcode project
├── FartScrollLid/              # Source code
│   ├── AppDelegate.m/h         # Main app controller
│   ├── FartScrollLid.m/h       # Lid angle sensor interface
│   ├── FartAudioEngine.m/h     # Fart sound engine
│   ├── NSLabel.m/h             # Custom label class
│   └── FART.wav                # Fart sound file
└── README.md                   # This file
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Credits</h2><a id="user-content-credits" aria-label="Permalink: Credits" href="#credits"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Based on the original <a href="https://github.com/samhenrigold/LidAngleSensor">LidAngleSensor</a> app by Sam Henri Gold</li>
<li>Fart sound from <a href="https://github.com/74656c/fart.js">fart.js</a></li>
<li>Inspired by the original fart scroll browser extension by The Onion</li>
<li>Built with assistance from Factory Droid</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">MIT License - see <a href="https://github.com/iannuttall/fartscroll-lid/blob/main/LICENSE">LICENSE</a> file for details</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Pull requests are welcome! For major changes, please open an issue first to discuss what you would like to change.</p>
<p dir="auto">Ideas for improvements:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Additional fart sound variations</li>
<li>Customizable pitch/volume curves</li>
<li>Fart statistics tracking</li>
<li>Network multiplayer farting</li>
<li>Apple Watch companion app</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Disclaimer</h2><a id="user-content-disclaimer" aria-label="Permalink: Disclaimer" href="#disclaimer"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This app is for entertainment purposes only. Please use responsibly in appropriate settings. Not recommended for:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Business meetings</li>
<li>Libraries</li>
<li>First dates</li>
<li>Job interviews</li>
<li>Funerals</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">But highly recommended for:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Pranking friends</li>
<li>Amusing children</li>
<li>Breaking awkward silences</li>
<li>General tomfoolery</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Author</h2><a id="user-content-author" aria-label="Permalink: Author" href="#author"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Created by Ian Nuttall with Factory Droid</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><em>Remember: Life is too short not to laugh at fart sounds from your laptop</em> 💨😄</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Danish supermarket chain is setting up "Emergency Stores" (320 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://swiss.social/@swaldorff/115186445638788782</link>
            <guid>45216805</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 22:35:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://swiss.social/@swaldorff/115186445638788782">https://swiss.social/@swaldorff/115186445638788782</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45216805">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Palantir is mapping the nation’s data (224 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theconversation.com/when-the-government-can-see-everything-how-one-company-palantir-is-mapping-the-nations-data-263178</link>
            <guid>45215984</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 20:50:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theconversation.com/when-the-government-can-see-everything-how-one-company-palantir-is-mapping-the-nations-data-263178">https://theconversation.com/when-the-government-can-see-everything-how-one-company-palantir-is-mapping-the-nations-data-263178</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45215984">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>When the U.S. government signs contracts with private technology companies, the fine print rarely reaches the public. <a href="https://www.palantir.com/">Palantir Technologies</a>, however, has attracted more and more attention over the past decade because of the size and scope of its contracts with the government. </p>

<p>Palantir’s two main platforms are Foundry and Gotham. Each does different things. Foundry is used by corporations in the private sector to help with global operations. Gotham is marketed as an “<a href="https://www.palantir.com/platforms/gotham/">operating system for global decision making</a>” and is primarily used by governments.</p>

<p>I am <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=JnTFiOQAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">a researcher</a> who studies the intersection of data governance, digital technologies and the U.S. federal government. I’m observing how the government is increasingly <a href="https://theconversation.com/from-help-to-harm-how-the-government-is-quietly-repurposing-everyones-data-for-surveillance-254690">pulling together data from various sources</a>, and the political and social consequences of combining those data sources. Palantir’s work with the federal government using the Gotham platform is amplifying this process.</p>

<p>Gotham is an investigative platform built for police, national security agencies, public health departments and other state clients. Its purpose is deceptively simple: take whatever data an agency already has, break it down into its smallest components and then connect the dots. Gotham is not simply a database. It takes fragmented data, scattered across various agencies and stored in different formats, and transforms it <a href="https://assets.applytosupply.digitalmarketplace.service.gov.uk/g-cloud-14/documents/92736/801146272055049-service-definition-document-2024-11-26-1253.pdf">into a unified, searchable web</a>.</p>

<p>The stakes are high with Palantir’s Gotham platform. The software enables law enforcement and government analysts to connect vast, disparate datasets, build intelligence profiles and search for individuals based on characteristics as granular as a tattoo or an immigration status. It transforms <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/revealed-this-is-palantirs-top-secret-user-manual-for-cops/">historically static records</a> – think department of motor vehicles files, police reports and subpoenaed social media data like location history and private messages – into a fluid web of intelligence and surveillance.</p>

<p>These departments and agencies use Palantir’s platform to assemble <a href="https://epic.org/epic-settles-ice-lawsuit-about-palantir-and-profiling/">detailed profiles of individuals</a>, mapping their social networks, tracking their movements, identifying their physical characteristics and reviewing their criminal history. This can involve mapping a suspected <a href="https://www.nola.com/news/crime_police/how-a-tech-firm-brought-data-and-worry-to-new-orleans-crime-fighting/article_33b8bf05-722f-5163-9a0c-774aa69b6645.html">gang member’s network</a> using arrest logs and <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/drive-los-angeles-police-track-every-move/">license plate reader data</a>, or flagging individuals in a specific region with a particular immigration status.</p>

<p>The efficiency the platform enables is undeniable. For investigators, what once required weeks of cross-checking siloed systems can now be done in hours or less. But by scaling up the government’s investigative capacity, Gotham also alters the relationship between the state and the people it governs.</p>

<figure>
            <a href="https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1000&amp;fit=clip"><p><img alt="A large outdoor sign with a round logo and text mounted on a stone base." data-src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" data-srcset="https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 2262w" sizes="(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/687583/original/file-20250826-55-ovh07.jpg?ixlib=rb-4.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip"></p></a>
            <figcaption>
              <span>The U.S. Department of Homeland Security uses Palantir’s technology to support its investigations.</span>
              <span><a href="https://newsroom.ap.org/detail/HomelandSecurity/31caf5fd39964032b7cf11830e82d210/photo">AP Photo/Jose Luis Magana</a></span>
            </figcaption>
          </figure>

<h2>Shifting the balance of power</h2>

<p>The political ramifications of Palantir’s rise come into focus when you consider its influence and reach across the government. U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement alone has <a href="https://fedscoop.com/dhs-renews-software-contract-with-palantir-for-investigative-case-management-services">spent more than US$200 million</a> on Palantir contracts, relying on the software to run its <a href="https://fedscoop.com/dhs-renews-software-contract-with-palantir-for-investigative-case-management-services">Investigative Case Management system</a> and to integrate travel histories, <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/ice-palantir-immigrationos/">visa records</a>, biometric data and social media data. </p>

<p>The Department of Defense has awarded Palantir billion-dollar contracts to <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/08/01/palantir-lands-10-billion-army-software-and-data-contract.html">support battlefield intelligence</a> and AI-driven analysis. Even domestic agencies like the <a href="https://www.palantir.com/newsroom/press-releases/palantir-expands-longstanding-cdc-partnership-for-disease-monitoring-and/">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</a> and the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/30/technology/trump-palantir-data-americans.html">Internal Revenue Service</a>, and local police departments like the <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/palantir-contract-dispute-exposes-nypds-lack-transparency">New York Police Department</a>, have contracted with Palantir for data integration projects.</p>

<p>These integrations mean that Palantir is not just a vendor of software; it is becoming a partner in how the federal government organizes and acts on information. That creates a kind of dependency. The same private company helps define how investigations are conducted, how targets are prioritized, how algorithms work and how decisions are justified.</p>

<p>Because Gotham is proprietary, the public, and even elected officials, cannot see how its algorithms weigh certain data points or why they highlight certain connections. Yet, the conclusions it generates can have <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/palantir-what-the-company-does/">life-altering consequences</a>: inclusion on a deportation list or identification as a security risk. The opacity makes democratic oversight difficult, and the system’s broad scope and wide deployment means that mistakes or biases can scale up rapidly to affect many people.</p>

<h2>Beyond law enforcement</h2>

<p>Supporters of Palantir’s work argue that it modernizes outdated government IT systems, bringing them closer to the kind of integrated analytics that are routine in the private sector. However, the political and social stakes are different in public governance. Centralized, attribute-based searching, whether by location, immigration status, tattoos or affiliations, creates the capacity for <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/0306396810377002">mass profiling</a>.</p>

<p>In the wrong hands, or even in well-intentioned hands under shifting political conditions, this kind of system could normalize surveillance of entire communities. And the criteria that trigger scrutiny today could be expanded tomorrow.</p>

<p>U.S. history provides warning examples: <a href="https://time.com/6097712/muslim-american-surveillance-supreme-court-sept-11/">The mass surveillance of Muslim communities after 9/11</a>, the targeting <a href="https://www.lib.berkeley.edu/about/news/fbi">of civil rights activists in the 1960s</a> and the <a href="https://sk.sagepub.com/ency/edvol/the-sage-encyclopedia-of-surveillance-security-privacy/chpt/antiwar-protest-surveillance-1960s">monitoring of anti-war protesters during the Vietnam era</a> are just a few. </p>

<p>Gotham’s capabilities may enable government agencies to carry out similar operations on a much larger scale and at a faster pace. And once some form of data integration infrastructure exists, its uses <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-38619-0">tend to expand</a>, often into areas far from its original mandate. </p>

<h2>A broader shift in governance</h2>

<p>The deeper story here isn’t just that the government is collecting more data. It’s that the structure of governance is changing into a model where decision-making is increasingly influenced by what integrated data platforms reveal. In a pre-Gotham era, putting someone under suspicion of wrongdoing might have required specific evidence linked to an event or witness account. In a Gotham-enabled system, suspicion can stem from patterns in the data – patterns whose importance is defined by proprietary algorithms. </p>

<p>This level of data integration means that government officials can use potential future risks to justify present action. The predictive turn in governance aligns with a broader shift toward what some scholars call “<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/ips.12042">preemptive security</a>.” It is a logic that can erode <a href="https://legaltimelines.org/accessible-timeline/safeguards-of-justice/">traditional legal safeguards</a> that require proof before punishment.</p>

<figure>
            <p><iframe data-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DZ95Gmvg_D4?wmode=transparent&amp;start=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" width="100%" height="400"></iframe></p>
            <figcaption><span>This short documentary about Palantir includes a former employee expressing concern about how algorithms are transforming government.</span></figcaption>
          </figure>

<h2>The stakes for democracy</h2>

<p>The partnership between Palantir and the federal government raises fundamental questions about accountability in a data-driven state. Who decides how these tools are used? Who can challenge a decision that was made by software, especially if that software is proprietary? </p>

<p>Without clear rules and independent oversight, there is a risk that Palantir’s technology becomes normalized as a default mode of governance. They could be used not only to track suspected criminals or terrorists but also to manage migration flows, monitor and suppress protests, and enforce public health measures. The concern is not that these data integration capabilities exist, but that government agencies could use them in ways that undermine civil liberties without public consent.</p>

<p>Once put in use, such systems are hard to dismantle. They create new expectations for speed and efficiency in law enforcement, making it politically costly to revert to slower, more manual processes. That inertia can lock in not only the technology but also the expanded scope of surveillance it enables.</p>

<h2>Choosing the future</h2>

<p>As Palantir deepens its government partnerships, the issues its technology raises go beyond questions of cost or efficiency. There are civil liberties implications and the potential for abuse. Will strong legal safeguards and transparent oversight constrain these tools for integrated data analysis? The answer is likely to depend on political will as much as technical design.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Palantir’s Gotham is more than just software. It represents how modern governance might function: through data, connections, continuous monitoring and control. The decisions made about its use today are likely to shape the balance between security and freedom for decades to come.</p>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unusual Capabilities of Nano Banana (Examples) (512 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/PicoTrex/Awesome-Nano-Banana-images/blob/main/README_en.md</link>
            <guid>45215869</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 20:35:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/PicoTrex/Awesome-Nano-Banana-images/blob/main/README_en.md">https://github.com/PicoTrex/Awesome-Nano-Banana-images/blob/main/README_en.md</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45215869">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      

      <div>
        <div>
            <div>

                  <ul>
                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_copilot&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_copilot_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          GitHub Copilot

        </p><p>

        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_spark&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_spark_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/spark">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          GitHub Spark

            <span>
              New
            </span>
        </p><p>

        Build and deploy intelligent apps
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_models&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_models_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/models">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          GitHub Models

            <span>
              New
            </span>
        </p><p>

        Manage and compare prompts
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/security/advanced-security">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          GitHub Advanced Security

        </p><p>

        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;actions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;actions_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          Actions

        </p><p>

        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                  </ul>
                </div>
            <div>

                  <ul>
                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;codespaces&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;codespaces_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          Codespaces

        </p><p>

        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;issues&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;issues_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          Issues

        </p><p>

        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_review&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_review_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          Code Review

        </p><p>

        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;discussions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;discussions_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          Discussions

        </p><p>

        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_search&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_search_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-search">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          Code Search

        </p><p>

        Find more, search less
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                  </ul>
                </div>
            
        </div>

          <p>
            <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;view_all_features&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;view_all_features_link_platform_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features">
              View all features
              
</a>          </p>
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
      

      
</li>


                <li>
      

      <div>

                      <p><span id="resources-explore-heading">Explore</span></p><ul aria-labelledby="resources-explore-heading">
                      <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/learn/pathways">
      Learning Pathways

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;events_amp_webinars&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;events_amp_webinars_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/resources/events">
      Events &amp; Webinars

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;ebooks_amp_whitepapers&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ebooks_amp_whitepapers_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/resources/whitepapers">
      Ebooks &amp; Whitepapers

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;customer_stories&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;customer_stories_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/customer-stories">
      Customer Stories

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;partners&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;partners_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://partner.github.com/">
      Partners

    
</a></li>

                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;executive_insights&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;executive_insights_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/solutions/executive-insights">
      Executive Insights

    
</a></li>

                  </ul>
                </div>
</li>


                <li>
      

      <div>
                <div>

                  <ul>
                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          GitHub Sponsors

        </p><p>

        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                  </ul>
                </div>
                <div>

                  <ul>
                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          The ReadME Project

        </p><p>

        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                  </ul>
                </div>
                
            </div>
</li>


                <li>
      

      <div>

                  <ul>
                      <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/enterprise">
      
      <div>
        <p>
          Enterprise platform

        </p><p>

        AI-powered developer platform
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                  </ul>
                </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;platform&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;global&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;platform_link_global_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:PicoTrex/Awesome-Nano-Banana-images" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="NARmv_pWnukPmOEPnOjiJVgOmsRdJT7RJn3BnoJxDBlCyiEk77toRNjqpgJuhJzP-ceBiIcNk9YzLE-BbyViDw" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="PicoTrex/Awesome-Nano-Banana-images" data-current-org="PicoTrex" data-current-owner="" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-nl-search-enabled="false" data-retain-scroll-position="true">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>


            

              <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E%2Fblob%2Fshow&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=PicoTrex%2FAwesome-Nano-Banana-images" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/PicoTrex/Awesome-Nano-Banana-images/blob/main/README_en.md&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="abe673b73fe0ea0203765afa7975dbcca910ef27ee3c7f8cc40d8b4ccbf839ba" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>/blob/show;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
                Sign up
              </a></p><p>
    <react-partial-anchor>
      <tool-tip id="tooltip-dcaad3be-f903-4b42-afdd-74f903b01a32" for="icon-button-c79d178a-31e0-4681-b1aa-b92fbd90a1bf" popover="manual" data-direction="s" data-type="label" data-view-component="true">Appearance settings</tool-tip>

      <template data-target="react-partial-anchor.template">
        <link crossorigin="anonymous" media="all" rel="stylesheet" href="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/primer-react.2473a867603eb9e3f3ac.module.css">
<link crossorigin="anonymous" media="all" rel="stylesheet" href="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/appearance-settings.c82a4db79200850fb016.module.css">

<react-partial partial-name="appearance-settings" data-ssr="false" data-attempted-ssr="false" data-react-profiling="false">
  
  <script type="application/json" data-target="react-partial.embeddedData">{"props":{}}</script>
  <div data-target="react-partial.reactRoot"></div>
</react-partial>


      </template>
    </react-partial-anchor>
  </p>

          </div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>